the following is a conversation with
anya farnald co-founder of belkampa
farms
that was founded with the purpose to
create meat that's good for people
the planet and the animals specifically
treating their animals as ethically as
possible
in this she sought to revolutionize the
meat industry
from the inside out she's also a scholar
and practitioner
of regenerative agriculture and she's a
chef
who has appeared many times as a judge
on iron chef
plus she has one of my favorite food
related instagrams
on top of that she's also a long time
friend of andrew huberman
which is how we first got connected
quick mention of our sponsors
gala games athletic greens four sigmatic
and fun to rise check them out in the
description to support this podcast
as a side note let me say that i got the
chance to visit
and spend a few days with anya at
belcampa farms in northern california
i met many animals there from cows to
pigs
and saw the amazing land on which they
grazed
i butchered meat i watched anya cook
many amazing meals
i ate raw meat and cooked meat and
spend long hours at the bonfire talking
with friends
and listening to the sounds of nature i
hiked
swam in a cold mountain lake and slept
in a tent
underneath the stars it was an amazing
eye-opening experience
especially in my first ever visit to a
slaughterhouse
the term slaughterhouse is haunting in
itself
the animals i met lived a great life but
in the end
they were slaughtered in the most
ethical way possible
but slaughtered nevertheless seeing
animals with whom just the day before i
made a connection
be converted to meat that i then
consumed
was deeply honest to me this ethical
farm
valcampo represents less than one
percent of animals raised in the united
states
the rest is factory farmed i could not
escape the thought
of the 40 to 50 billion animals
worldwide
raised in terrible conditions on these
factory farms
i've spent most of my life thinking
about and being in contact with
human suffering but the landscape of
suffering in the minds of conscious
beings
is much larger than humans i must admit
that i still am haunted by human
suffering more than animal suffering
perhaps i will one day see the wrong in
me drawing such a line
either way the visit to belcample farms
made me realize
that i have not thought deeply enough
about the ethics of my choices
and the choices of human civilization
with respect to animals
and more importantly i have not thought
or learned enough
about large-scale solutions to alleviate
animal suffering
belcampo is paving the way on this and
is the reason i wanted to show my
support
for their and anya's efforts in
regenerative farming
and ethical treatment of animals this is
the lex friedman podcast
and here is my conversation with anya
fernald
if you're watching the video version of
this and are asking yourself why we're
in nature right now there's actually
a beautiful mountain in the background
there's an incredible vast landscape
there's a farm
we're sitting behind a table
nevertheless i'm wearing a suit and tie
amidst nature we're at the beautiful
belcample farms
we're going to talk about that this
incredible place you have here but
you cook some meat yesterday it tasted
delicious
so i'd love to talk about just the the
science and art of cooking first
you as a chef when you think of cooking
is it a science or is it an art
art and service together probably
uh art to me because it's about
creating something of beauty and being
responsive and creating something that's
expression of creativity and love
cooking
also has a very strong element of
service and it doesn't mean necessarily
service to another person but like
service to health
wellness environment there's an element
of supporting through food
in how i approach cooking so it's bigger
than just like the
how the ingredients come together to
form a taste it's the whole pipeline
like
the fact that uh there's a lot of work
that went
into bringing the ingredients together
and then
you know making you uh giving you the
ability to make the
the meal and then who gets to consume
the meal and the whole thing
and you see that as service as opposed
to just the taste
yeah i also think of food as one of the
key ways that
we interact with our environment right
we
it's the part of our environment that
goes inside us most visibly right of
course we interact with our environment
we could have
skin creams that have certain things in
them or our clothes can then be absorbed
there's things in the air there's our
water and there's food right it's like
how we're engaging
in the world physiologically it's the
most significant way we engage in our
environment
we're extracting resources calories
energy from the environment of various
ways
in order to preserve our bodies
there's also so many feedback loops that
i don't think we know
the beginning of that our bodies are
picking up on
around nutrients available nutrients
immune response
like there's deep levels of sensory
evaluation
that lead to health and alertness and
wellness you you hear about this a lot
like with babies that you know
um if there's a risk of an infection
that a mom's breast milk will
help the baby develop a resistance like
there's this way that
our bodies can tune into health and
can't extrapolate from that in a
specific way but
think about that as an example of like
the many ways in which our bodies are
reading available nutrients and food
to signal other aspects of wellness and
health
that said the final
product of cooking is uh when done well
is really delicious
and what we yesterday was really
delicious so that aspect of it
bringing the ingredients together in a
way that tastes delicious
do you see that as a science art that's
the art of it
i mean the art is like creating
temptation
and indulgence and giving people pause
you know like giving creating experience
that's like so sensual and
like i love that about when i make
something really simple and beautiful
and delicious the way that like there's
that moment of silence
at the table and that to me is the
moment of art like
appreciation what about the build up i
mean we got we got to watch you make the
stuff over a fire so the
the calmness of the air i mean that's an
experience we don't often get to have to
see that experience
of the the prep it's the anticipation
like you said maybe that's the most
delicious part of a meal is the
anticipation of it
that's something that i'm glad you bring
up because it's an element that
with eating so many of our meals like
out of a bag
and you know the instance where you
start to eat the meals when the delivery
shows up
and you might smell something when you
open the bag right and no judgment on
that that's something i do too right
but that does take away a whole element
of
of surprise and delight and also i think
of your body's ability to prepare for it
you think about our most common memories
of childhood
for those of us who grew up in homes
with with parents who cooked is
smell of things cooking and it's not the
eating of it it's the smell of things
cooking
so why is that so memorable it's an
anticipatory
piece of food that's what you remember
about your experiences of food is the
moment of like sweet anticipation of
some of this great sensual experience
that's going to be
really gratifying on these emotional and
physical levels so i think
we're also resonating on those memories
because it's like
it's an experience of food where the
sensuality of it is kind of extended so
it's a long kind of arc of build
up and then you're eating it and it's
amazing and then you're enjoying it and
your body feels good
so all those pieces together it's a much
more memorable experience than just
grabbing the cookie
out of a bag right so look at our own
and
just revisit in your mind like the
memories of food the most compelling
ones it's
the smell yeah and then the experience
and then sometimes how one felt right
yeah and the people involved with the
smell so like somehow it's all tied in
together whether it's family or people
close to you
or even if it's just chefs there's
something about
the the personality of the human
involved in making the food that kind of
sticks with you in the memory
and for me i recently did a 72-hour fast
and there's a kind of sadness after you
eat
that it's over i think the most
delicious part was the
i went to a grocery store and just
actually walking around
and looking at food with like everything
looked delicious even like the crappiest
stuff look delicious
and i i missed that i i really enjoyed
that anticipation and then i picked out
the meal
i went home and i cooked it and the
whole thing took i don't know
maybe two three hours like the whole
process and that was
the most delicious part and the first
taste of course and then
after after it was over there's a bit of
a sadness
because the part i remember is the the
build up the anticipation
and then once you eat it's over
we kind of focus on the destination but
it's the whole journey
the whole like even if you go to a
restaurant it's the
the conversations leading up to the meal
and the first taste of the meal
that's where the joy is and if you get
to watch the making of that meal that's
incredible that's where the
the smell the visual how the ingredients
come together
and especially as we were looking over
the fire
like watching it the fire play
with the raw meat and you know over time
bring out the colors bring out the i
don't know like you can visually
associate the flavor
you know how it becomes uh a little bit
burnt on the outside you know it has a
crispiness to it it starts to gain that
crispiness and immediately
your past memories of the delicious
crispiness of various foods you've eaten
are somehow mapped into your
immediately you start to taste it
visually i don't know yeah that
experience is magical
it's and of course maybe it's the
russian thing but i'm almost like
saddened when it's over i think
fasting is gaining in popularity because
we're having to
relearn the importance of being hungry
yeah in anticipation and delight
yeah we have such a fear of hunger
um and that's really you know functional
and evolution
right but we have this deep fear of
hunger and part of the great american
experience has been
that we don't have to be afraid of
hunger at all because there's food
everywhere and it's really cheap
in all that abundance we've lost
this edge of hunger and we don't let
ourselves get hungry and that's
one thing that i learned in part of my
journey as a cook and chef has been
you know moving abroad was the first
time when i
lived out of the u.s it was the first
time that i regularly experienced hunger
because the time between meals was
really long
and that was just what everybody did and
so i was hungry for two hours before
lunch
and that was the first time in my life
that there hadn't just been regularly
available snacks
so i i wonder if they the intermittent
fasting and part of the popularity
around it
it i'm sure there's all these amazing
metabolic things that are happening but
also
people might also feel better because
they're really anticipating
and enjoying food and then if you look
at the feelings of fullness
there's a really interesting thing that
happens when you cook
and your sense of fullness which is
if you cook and you're hungry
the experience of being around the food
smelling it touching it
sampling it you'll take your hunger down
by 40
and this is my own observation but as i
mean we've all had the experience
of cooking thanksgiving and the cook
never kind of wants to eat that much
thanksgiving that's an extreme
experience
but when you really dive in and you're
cooking for a few hours and you're
smelling and smelling and smelling
it totally changes your threshold of
satiety and
fullness because of other sensory things
that are
happening yeah and for those of us
looking to you know to maintain weight
and
something to consider in this is that
cooking is also
part of the part of what your appetite
when you're hungry what are you hungry
for
right so we tend to think about calories
but when you're hungry you might also be
hungrier for a wider range of things
and it might be smells it might be
stopping there's other elements and
that's something
think as a cook that it's it's powerful
to
explore and be with and observe how your
hunger changes
when you're cooking well let me ask the
romantic question
when did you first fall in love with the
cooking
me falling in love with cooking was
about a
solving a problem in my family and it
had to do
with my mom feeling very anxious
about uh cooking and
overwhelmed frequently when it came to
meals and
i'm naturally very good at juggling a
lot of things
and it was just something i could dive
in and help
and help my dad who's very i'm very very
close to
so it was a very it was a very
functional role where i would see
this kind of crescendo of anxiety um
around meal times as a kid
and would be able to dive in and and
solve things
and i also loved women who cooked like
my father's mother is a great cook she
was
i remember her telling me as a kid i you
know i was asking her about
church and why she went to church and
she's like i mostly go to church because
i get to cook
for the for the you know potlucks and so
there was a there was an openness around
that that but she just loved to cook for
people and it was
and there was a real tenderness and
expression of that love
so seeing women in my life who had this
like real tenderness and
love that they shared through food and
then also being able
in my own home to kind of pitch in and
add value and
and help my mom and dad was
really powerful for me because i felt
like i had a superpower
you know i felt like oh man i just made
this stressful thing
go away um that was huge it's kind of
interesting i don't know if you can
comment on
especially for me growing up in russia
it's probably true in a lot of cultures
maybe every culture that food and
especially like in a family
the mother that cooks is the source of
love
and like ties the family together it
creates events where everyone comes
together
it's uh it's one of the only chances of
togetherness uh the thing that
bonds a family is like dinner or
food eating together and i don't know
what to do with that
it ties up with like dieting and so on
when i was on stricter diets especially
competing and cutting weight and stuff
it felt like i was almost like losing
opportunity to connect with friends and
family
it's interesting it almost like cultures
we cannot fully experience love and
family without
eating and on the flip side of that
eating enables us to experience
love and family i don't know what to do
with that
it's a tough one because there's lots of
layers around kind of
gender roles and um families changing
and things
yeah i'd say i agree around the
alienation
and i've done carnivore diet and i've
tried some of these extreme protocols
and i too
i suffered from loneliness you know it
was like doing carnivore and
and not being able to eat what my kids
ate and talk about at the same time
those pieces are real and i wonder with
all these diets
if that structure is actually helping or
just taking away from
people's kind of sensual understanding
um but i think that there's some rigor
around that that helps people discover
what's good for them
by eliminating and then growing towards
more intuitive
food is a good evolution from that base
i love to cook for people
i love to pay attention to their
their way of being and read what they'd
like to eat
and it's my my purest way of love and
that's for
everybody in my life i actually love to
cook for people i love
you know i don't i i would struggle to
be you know putting out food all the
time
it's like something for me it's a real
act of care taking so i definitely have
that
in my makeup um and and i definitely
notice um in times of like
of of real stress that's the piece that
drops off
right then and it's like if i'm unable
to care for myself i have a hard time
cooking
so it's for me it's very emotional it's
very connected to love
and individualistic so like focused on
the particular individual
it's almost like a journey of
understanding what that person
is excited about in the in the landscape
of flavors
like figuring that person out what they
like what they what they love to eat
yeah uh i see cooking from i mostly cook
for myself
so i see that it's almost a oh this is
gonna be like the worst term but like
an act of uh self-love
this is going to be clipped out but
that like it's almost an exploration of
like what brings me joy
and it's surprising because i usually
don't share because the things that
bring me joy
are the simplest ingredients like i'm
one of those people
i don't know if you can psychoanalyze me
because you also like basic ingredients
i like a single ingredient two
ingredients because
i feel like i can deeply appreciate the
particular ingredient then
i get easily distracted you know people
who are really good at listening to
music they can hear a piece of music
and in their mind extract the different
layers and enjoy
different layers at a time like the bass
the drums
the different layering of the piano the
beats and all that kind of stuff
that's what it means to truly enjoy
music to listen to a piece over and over
like almost like as a scholar in that
same way for food i just can't do more
than like three because then it's just
i have to give in to the chaos of it i
guess but when it's just a basic
ingredient
like just meat or just a vegetable like
basic grilled without sauces without any
of that
that i've discovered is what brings me a
lot of joy but that's boring to a lot of
people
so i usually have to be kind of private
about that joy
so but that's mine so yeah i figured
that out and i guess as a
as a chef you have to figure that out
about everybody that you care for
well also for you
you're very interested in things and
and interested in things being done well
and appreciating them so
the single ingredient also allows you to
control for perfection and cooking that
which is probably really
appealing to you and i think
sometimes i see people also in the
beginning of their journey of
culinary trying to do too many things
right so there's another piece too
that you'll notice if you recall last
night i grilled us the salad
right and then i did all those pieces
separately and that's something in
general
to be really attentive of when you're
building flavor to make sure you
pay attention to every piece separately
um you know the idea that you can okay
with the soup or something or stew
there's there's workarounds
but like to make a great dish that's got
four or five vegetables in it
cook them all separately to their
optimal deliciousness and then combine
them
so that's another way to approach that
is that you may also be able to look at
the different ingredients separately
and still have that sense of like
understanding of it
but there's too often that we're
layering together like four or five
things and then cooking them all at once
and then surprised that it's not
delicious
yeah because you can't you can't really
optimize on multiple variables at the
same time for peak
awesomeness and that's actually you know
the number one way you see this is
roasting a whole chicken
which is a really difficult it's the
simplest dish but it's very difficult
because you have the breast meat which
is bigger chunks they cook faster you
have the
thighs and drums which are smaller and
they cook slower
to optimize that and pay attention to it
and do it all right they're you're
actually solving for different outcomes
so there's a there's one example but
oftentimes food is less delicious with
multiple ingredients at the start
because we're not able to pay attention
to how each one needs to end up
so there's a way to parse that apart and
achieve a better outcome
i don't know if you've seen jiro dreams
of sushi it's a documentary about
yeah so there's an obsession
that particular first of all set of
humans
but also the particular uh cuisine
that focused on the basics of the
ingredients um
what do you think of that kind of trying
to achieve mastery through repeating
the making of the same meal over and
over and over for like decades
like do you find beauty in that journey
towards mastery or do you think
it should be always an exploration to
where you're always trying things
you're always kind of injecting new
flavors
new experiences all that kind of stuff
i think you have to decide on a palette
you know if we're talking about an art
it's equivalent to saying am i a
sculptor or a painter
yeah that the sushi lexicon think that's
a very very narrow small canvas that
you're painting on
and that is a beautiful road right
there's there's a there's a beauty and a
perfection to that it's like i mean
there's many things culturally around
that that you could extrapolate for
specifically for japan but i i i
encourage people on and the journey in
food to choose
like kind of a language that they're
working within
and if you want to step out of that
occasionally and have one or two dishes
but if you want to get mastery with food
you probably
aren't going to be able to get more than
say 20 ingredients that you use
regularly that you really understand
and so we often see you know i see the
american pantry it's got tons of sauces
and tons of spices and tons of spice
blends
and then really people only use just a
couple things
and the idea that you can sort of splash
out and do korean one night and then
tacos the next time you can
absolutely but to get in a regular
cadence of specific ingredients you're
probably going to get more mastery with
that sooner
and i think as much as you can do to get
an understanding of the you know the
basics around salt and acid
and understand your palette like for me
it's lemon and usually sherry vinegar
right so that's my acid palette
um and i my fat palates you know suet
and butter olive oil so you can sort of
choose your language what you're
painting with
but i wouldn't splash out and say do i
use sesame oil yeah every once in a
while
but that's not part of my base palette
right can you say again what your
fat palate is it'd be butter suet and
olive oil
and olive oil so not uh why olive oil is
it your roots and illegal
i like the flavor for finish because of
the bitterness that it adds
so i like the bitter and acid contrast
on meat
and vegetables which is mostly what i
eat and so i love that
that that way that the bitterness and
astringency complements and allows the
flavors to come out what do you think
about coconut oil
there's i recently discovered that
there's a
i don't know there's a sweetness there's
something to it that
that i really enjoy um maybe because
it's new
it's it's good with heat and i really
love it for some reason
as a chef do you do you ever tried what
do you think about it i like it in
coffee like i like it as a
like a treat a little bit i find the
flavor a little bit
challenging in foods i also find that
it's difficult um on the quality of that
ingredient
so i've found often that i buy a high
quality coconut oil and there's
rancidity in it
um and i don't totally know why i think
it's just the cold chain and how that
products packaged
so i've had some issues with product
quality in that but i
for me it's a little bit too much
sweetness in my foods
but then again i don't cook in like a
southeast asian palette i try to not
have much sweetness in my foods in
general so
i just because of the palette that i
like to cook with so for me coconuts got
a little bit too much of those high
notes
and earthiness which is a nice
combination but it's more like a treat
yeah it is almost like a tree it has it
has a flavor of its own
that almost stands on its own like i
could probably just
eat cook that's probably the only oil i
could enjoy by itself
it sounds weird to say but it feels like
fat is often a thing that enriches the
flavor of something else
coconut can almost stand on its own you
might also be responding to that it's a
complex flavor
right so there's also a there's an
analogous
you know if you look at butter for
example a lot of the butter that we eat
in the u.s
is just sweet cream butter it's not
cultured
if you explore like a cultured fermented
butter
maybe a grass milk grass-fed and finish
butter you're gonna get a ton more
complexity
and so you may also just be responding
to having fats with
more flavor which is the
the journey in the u.s has been towards
refined foods
that are very neutral and then you have
to combine more of them to make things
taste like things
and so if you're coming from a
background of using mostly just
generic butter or let's say canola oil
to cook with those are very neutral oils
so you can also take some of your
favorite fats and look for versions of
them that are more flavorful
i mean i love olive oil as a treat in a
spoon
really like a good california extra
virgin olive oil it's like cabbage i'll
eat a piece of butter as a treat
yeah that's like or butter with salt on
it like good fats
can all of them can be if they're
minimally processed
and they're fabulous it's so delicious
right but there are things that you have
to
like look for a version of them that's
got that full palette of flavor well for
me also the flavors
are inextricably tied to the memories
i've had with those flavors so
for better or worse back when i used to
eat a lot of ice cream
i for some reason had a lot of pleasant
experience with coconut ice cream
so that particular flavor just permeates
throughout my life not like i'm stuck
with it uh for better or worse
as a flavor that brings up pleasant
memories
and i have a few such flavors i have i
have such relationship with all kinds of
meat too
like it's just so many pleasant memories
and that's it
like you're almost tasting the memories
yeah and
uh that there's no way to separate the
flavor from the memories
i suppose and that's a powerful thing
what's your favorite meal to cook
i i'll roast a couple chickens and then
i'll poach them like i'll boil them and
let it cool that's complicated one
i'll let them cool down i'll pull all
the meat off put the bones back into the
pot
and then cook that for like three or
four hours um
and then add in like shiitake mushrooms
and all the chicken meat and
the and they they'll throw in a bottle
of white wine into the into the stock as
well a bunch of thyme and garlic
and i love it because it's
it's the way the house smells it's very
laborious it's
soothing for me to spend time picking
apart me and chopping things up there's
like a lot of manuality around it
um so i'd say from a personal like i
mean i love grilling a steak and doing
those things as well but there's
something about making a
stock from scratch and the way it smells
the way i feel
the time it takes the kind of checking
in on it
that i really really love there's many
things i love to make that i don't even
love to
to eat you know i think you see this a
lot in like baking and bakers people who
bake a ton
and they love the process of it even if
they don't eat that many baked goods so
anything
for me that's really like enjoyable is
typically things like making cinnamon
buns i don't eat very many cinnamon buns
but
i love making them because it takes all
the sort of like fussing around and
taking your time and watching it
the way it smells the way the house
smells all of that stuff is like
very it's like almost like a like a
meditative exercise for me
is there a science is there an art to
cooking meat well and the different
kinds of meats
is there something you can convert into
words
in um to say ideas
how to bring out the best out of what
particular meat
whatever steak we're talking about
whatever beef we're talking about
is there something that can be said the
basic approach
to cooking any type of meat
beyond the artistry of it is pretty
scientific
and it's what type of muscle is it in
the animal
and what's the surface area to volume
ratio
okay so let's look at those two
questions so the first piece is
what's the type of muscle in the animal
what's the functionality
you don't necessarily need to know that
um to evaluate it but you need to
understand
is it a tender muscle that's not used
very frequently in the animal
or is it a big load-bearing muscle that
gets a lot of action like the cheek
right or the shin or the those pieces
the muscles like um those along the
spinal cord that make up
rib eyes and new york stakes and things
those aren't very exercised
they're they're right next to the spinal
cord spinal cord is doing most of the
work there they're kind of like
stabilizing muscles around this big
functional piece of
of skeletal structure in the animal
other muscles like the ones around the
diaphragm with the flat iron stakes and
skirt stakes and things those are
those are really functional muscles that
are doing a ton and moving and
if they're moving a lot what happens
well
functionally they've got lots of muscle
sheaths
because muscles that move frequently
have to do a lot of like complex
contraction that's why you know there's
um
in the cheek for example there's tons of
visible fiber of
like collagenous connective tissue
that connective tissue is everything
in how the meat cooks because connective
tissue doesn't respond
to high heat with becoming more tender
muscles
do right they can get a sear on them you
can cut them and eat them the collagen
stitches will glom up
and get really tough so you either have
to liquefy it with really low
slow heat with moisture right
or you have to barely cook it and that's
so that's the major piece that's the
question of like why wouldn't you just
throw a brisket on the grill
okay it's not about the fat you can cut
the fat out the reason you're not going
to throw a brisket on the grill and cook
it hot and fast it's got too much
collagenous connective tissue in it
those are these giant muscles that have
all this collagen and these fibers and
tendons in them effectively
so you're never going to be able to just
cook that up hot fast so that's the
first piece it's like what where's this
muscle in the architecture of the animal
and then
what does that mean for what's going on
in the muscle
and that's actually more important than
fat content we get really
kind of we pay a lot of attention to fat
content in muscles
you can make a steak tender if it
doesn't have a ton of fat in it it
actually has more to do if
there's if there's collagen and
connective tissue in it
that's fascinating i never even thought
about that i just
i thought it kind of uh universe i mean
adds to the
the texture of the meat the chewiness of
the meat
but you're saying it's also adds to uh
how
heat how it reacts to heat how the
entirety of the meat reacts to heat
and the fat is not as important to that
as the the calories the fat will make
the flavor more delicious
right like it'll add punctuousness and
mouth feel and things like that but
the all the connective tissue in meat
and in some of the cuts like that we ate
a skirt steak last night you could see a
web
of that collagen sheath on the outside
on a ribeye that same collagen sheath is
this big there's only one it goes around
the outside okay because it's just
that muscle there's one large muscle
fiber so
that specific it's a myelin sheath right
that's
that material needs moisture and low and
slow heat to become
tender the other side of that is that
when it becomes tender it liquefies
and it adds all this beautiful
gelatinous consistency that's what bone
broth is that's why
like a slow cooked pork shoulder is so
delicious
it's not that it's full of all that fat
that fat's also great but
a lot of that mouth feel comes from that
really beautiful
dissolved collagen so when you're
looking like how do i understand
how i'm going to cook a piece of meat
that first fork in the road is
how is this going to respond to heat and
what's the appropriate cooking technique
then the second piece
is that surface area to volume ratio and
that's
important because the heat is going to
impact the meat through the surfaces
of the meat that are in contact with the
heat
so if i have a steak that's three inches
thick i'm going to cook it extremely
diff differently from my
from a steak that's a half inch thick or
three quarters of an inch thick
and that's the major and that's the
truth if i have a piece of pork shoulder
that's cut into cubes versus having a
whole pork shoulder
that surface area to volume ratio that's
going to totally change how i cook it
and same things like pot roast and a
beef stew would be the same cut of meat
right but how i cook them is going to
change based on the surface area of
volume because you've got to let
moisture and heat work its way into the
center of the meat
and that's going to be determined by the
amount of surface of the meat that's in
contact with whatever cooking liquid or
heat you've got
is there different sources of heat to
play with like a big flame
versus a small or maybe even like
almost no flame like over coals all that
kind of stuff is there some
science to the source of heat in how it
plays with the meat
there's indirect heat and direct heat
and
that really is mostly about temperature
okay
in more than actual i mean smoke is
important
as well that can permeate but really the
smoke doesn't go into the center of most
cuts that you barbecue it'll come it's
like the smoke ring it's it's a
it's a you know it's maximum like half
an inch on the outside
maybe a little bit deeper on a really
long slow cook so they
but this the smoke that does create a
ton of flavor on the surface of the meat
um but that's so the indirect allows you
to have smoke contacting it and then a
very very low and slow heat
and what that does is indirect heat
will be low and slow enough
that the center of the meat will get
warm at the same time as the exterior of
the meat
and it'll all cook equally and all get
equally tender
if you go very hot and fast you risk the
interior of the meat
not getting right you kind of create a
shell on the on it um and you slow down
the interior or the meat which you
actually want to do with something like
a steak
where you want to keep it rare on the
inside so it's really indirect versus
direct then once you get into
direct heat right like in that category
there's wood
charcoal gas right that's about it and
those are
meaningfully different they're
meaningfully different charcoal and wood
that's more of there's more poetry and
wood there's a little bit more flavor
not functionally very different but gas
versus charcoal wood
is very different um and that's because
of the actual
scent of the of the cook right the scent
of the flavor
um and then there's a i think an
evenness of heat distribution that comes
off of charcoal
that's different from gas because no
matter how awesome your gas grill is you
do have hotter
and cooler spots so gas grills are
typically
you can kind of control for that if you
just are going really hot and fast
yeah which is why grass grills are fine
if you're just like throwing that steak
on get a hard sear on
those burgers put a crust on it that's
fabulous for that that's perfect
when you're doing things that do better
with a low and slow
cook like let's say a whole tenderloin
or
chicken thigh that's going to be a
little bit
less elegant on gas than on charcoal
versus wood so when you have more
more kind of nuance in the low slow cook
over the natural fuels
talking about like smoke and flame and
charcoal versus gas
it also adds to the experience and the
smell and the whole
thing of the cooking or like versus just
like the taste it creates
there's a certain experience to like
when there's a bit of smoke
maybe i don't know what the chemistry of
it is but i feel like with smoke the
smell is distributed more effectively
i don't know if that's true but there
there's there's a there's a smell
and a visual aspect to the experience
that's almost enriched with a bit of
smoke
and and uh or like an open flame like if
you could see the flame
this is magic to that and it goes to the
experience piece that
we're talking about we were talking
exactly about that like the nuance and
the beauty of like that long
slow cook and your house smelling like
something why do people
freak out about barbecue yeah why
because you go and it smells bomb it
smells so
good it smells like heaven right it
smells fatty and delicious and the
smells
everywhere and everyone's smelling the
same smell so there's like this
collective experience
it's incredible that's i mean i i think
that's why barbecue is so
sticky for people yeah it's like so
yummy and you get this huge like
anticipatory thing
about it it's like because it smells
incredible what was that incredible
grill that we used yesterday
what is that that's called a sea island
forge it's a wood fire grill that's
inspired by like a south american style
cooking
so it's like it's big it has also the
the things with the crank it allows you
to control the distance from the flame
it's awesome really key with the wood
fire so when we evolved
um from cooking over wood to charcoal
right when when that became more popular
the reason that we did that is that
allowed us to
skip the whole part of making our own
charcoal right so when you're cooking
over wood
all you're doing is making your own
charcoal you don't ever cook over wood
with the
red fire like we don't like throw a
steak on when the flames are orange and
leaping up because you're just gonna get
you know carbon like char all over your
meat so you're when you're cooking over
wood
you first cook down the wood you create
the coal base the natural coal base
and then you cook over that so you saw
yesterday i built my fire i let it burn
down added some fresh wood so i could
reinforce
my coals with new coals coming in but
then
i was actually cooking over the embers
you shorten that cycle with carbon
with with charcoal it's more it's more
efficient but what you lose is that
whole cycle
of you know that really beautiful
experience of smelling
now if you're cooking on a traeger
you're going to get awesome smoke smell
you know like you're
there's plenty of ways to do this it
doesn't always have to be wood fire i
love
all the different ways right but i i
really like
the experience of the campfire and i
love that kind of just like sitting by
it building it having to take the time i
like building the fire
going inside preparing all my meats
bringing them out cooking them that
whole experience start to finish
is really just like something that it's
my favorite it's my favorite way to
spend it
spend time you know so i think and why
is that is the food that different than
cooking it
in a in a more conventional grill
probably not you know like in a pure
experience but i think the actual
experience is super memorable
because you are outside you are slowing
your role you're enjoying the
this you know you're just taking in
you're watching
you're anticipating i love that whole
experience does the
origin of the meat itself make a
difference
so we're here about campbell farms and
we'll maybe you could talk about
what your vision your dream is on in uh
in terms of like food in terms of where
food comes from
where meat comes from but food broadly
and how that affects
the entirety of the the culinary journey
on the question of where does it come
from and does that matter
i'd say though the way that meat is
raised is
massively important for flavor and for
how it cooks
um i think most
cooks who try cooking grass-fed versus
corn fed that's the
first moment where they realize that
right where corn fed
meat cooks much more slowly it's got
bigger veins of fat that slow the
heat transfer throughout the muscle of
the animal compared to grass-fed which
is leaner
heat moves through it more quickly those
steaks will cook much much faster so
there's very kind of technical reasons
why how meat is raised
uh and that we're aware of and there's
other things that
i've noticed like um that slower growing
poultry has a very very different
musculature and fiber to it
than fast-growing poultry that's
confinement animals it's just
it has to do with the way that the
muscles are built they tend to be
finer and thinner and more tender and a
little bit more susceptible to heat so
they the character of the meat's
radically different
it's also much more flavorful when it's
grown more naturally
and i think some of the the reliance in
the u.s on like
sugary sauces and lots of salts and
flavors and things like that's actually
based on having the broadly available
meat out there is pretty low on flavor
and so we're
adding in a lot to compensate for that
so to your point of like
enjoying things very simply and and
with like salt and nothing else like the
more flavorful that product is i think
the more
people will find that enjoyable let's
paint a vision
i mean you're a visionary you have you
have a vision to have
basically meat in every store that comes
from a a farm like belcampo
that's uh that's basically doing
regenerative farming
how do we get there it's about
a network of smaller producers working
together with
shared values and
it's true that there's a limit on
regenerative farming
in that it requires more human knowledge
so regenerative farming is
more difficult to scale in a single
operation it'd be really challenging to
have a regenerative farm that was like
200 000 acres
because of the amount of manpower needed
to pay attention
can you first and i apologize to
interrupt but can you
say what is regenerative farming sure
so they if you're looking at scaling
regenerative
farming it's a traditional system of
agriculture
regenerative farming is how we used to
farm
we used to farm with an eye towards the
long term
you might be on the friedman farm
thinking about your heirs
five generations from now farming that
same land
are you going to leave that land
nutritionally empty
no okay it's a long-term thinking also
in traditional ag you don't have inputs
that are very convenient
you can put some chicken manure on but
you can't
spray or dump something that massively
increases
the growing potential of the land
that was not available until the past 60
years
so regenerative agriculture is
an approach to farming where you're
increasing soil fertility
through your farming you increase soil
fertility
by feeding the soil you feed the soil
through carbon that's why regenerative
farming is better for the environment
it sequesters carbon and puts carbon
into the soil
now it's interesting plants
need carbon and put it into the soil
when they're going through growth
so if you have a beautiful field of
grass that's just waving in the wind
that's not sequestering as much carbon
as plants that have been damaged
and are regrowing plants that have been
damaged and are re-growing
are repairing and they're doing that by
drawing down carbon as one of the
nutrients that feeds them
to damage the plants effectively that's
what we're doing with regenerative
grazing
so the cows or you know lambs whatever
out there they're eating and taking
the grass down and that then cause a
regrowth cycle
that sequesters carbon wow there's a
limit to it there's an edge
because if those plants are so damaged
that they can't regrow
then it turns into a dirt patch and that
doesn't sequester any carbon
so it's a balance how do you find that
uh balance so
that has to do with like the frequency
and the scale the grazing essentially
exactly and so you have to find the
right balance and that that connects to
the
both the the grass i mean is is the
ultimately
the focus here is that the life cycle of
whatever is grazing
whether it's cows or lambs or so on
that's why the scalability question so
all that stuff that i
just talked about like think about all
the actions
that that requires somebody's out there
looking and paying attention
and understanding how far the grass is
remembering what happened in that field
last year
there's a huge human intelligence need
and human
kind of availability of attention
now industrial farming has done a great
job at de-skilling
agriculture
industrial farming has taken agriculture
from being art science to being
entry-level employment yeah
so that's the limiting factor on regen
and that's why i think the human
intelligence piece exactly
i gotta ask uh i don't know if you think
about this kind of stuff i mentioned to
you offline that i spent
a bit of time with some robots and
boston dynamics do you think there's a
way to use artificial intelligence to
help
so data collection so automating some of
the
some of the things that makes humans
special make some of that decision some
of that memory that's then utilized
converted into knowledge to make
decisions about the crops and so on
is there a way if ai can help do you
think i totally
i mean that's that's that would be
incredible that's one of the
ingredients that could help with the
regenerative number of discrete decision
points
that could completely be automated
as well in order to supplement and work
with somebody like a farmer in managing
it
about the the the performance on land
and a bit of that's being done right now
with some
aerial mapping and but that type of ai
would be
huge in this i mean there's estimates
that if
the um damage and underutilized range
land
in the world was converted to
regenerative agriculture at somewhere
between
like 20 and 40 percent of the world's
carbon could be sequestered
so there's a huge potential the problem
is
cultural we've
like lost the generational threat of
knowledge about how to do this it's kind
of been two generations that haven't
farmed this way
also the science around it is
limited by the scale and longevity so
the data
collection around regenerative farming
is also limited by the fact it's kind of
piecemeal
there's small operations that are doing
it they're learning and developing as
they go
and they haven't been documenting it and
doing it for too long
is the ethical treatment of animals a
part of
regenerative farming so in
the way you do things about campo that's
a huge part
uh is that necessarily part of the life
cycle so like the things that you're
trying to measure
is like uh like the way
like like not damaging the land too much
make sure
that the sort of the land is constantly
healthy and producing
and then the grazing process and also
the carbon piece
the the fact that it's like carbon
neutral or something like that
i mean are all those pieces of the
regenerative farming
or is this an extra part to your vision
that you're thinking about it's all
implicit and regenerative
yeah i call it out separately because we
are certified humane
right which is another layer of welfare
that has to do with density and a couple
other things
but regenerative i mean think about if
you're a cow and you're in a
regenerative operation where
the whole life cycle of the pasture
means that you only eat the top six
inches of the grass
and then when there's whatever a couple
inches left then that feels left dormant
that's a better experience right okay so
just think about it kind of functionally
that way well grazing period is a better
experience right
yeah and that's that's not what's done
in i mean that's the grass-fed
piece that's the other piece with you
know
certified organics amazing there's
you know there's plenty of
certifications that you know grass-fed
and finish is also
great but there are workarounds for
those you can have certified organic
feedlots
you can have grass-fed and finished
which is uh in an animal-fed a grass
seed pellet
those aren't things that we do here
right and regenerative captures that
because if you're it's anything you're
isolating these very specific
certifications
it doesn't have a holistic approach
regenerative though unfortunately isn't
certified yet
we've gotten usda approval to use that
word based on our carbon sequestration
data
but it's not a regulated term so that's
kind of the mix right now is to figure
out
how to document it and it's not totally
clear what it means like for pigs and
chickens which
are omnivores it's very clear for
ruminants which are animals that have a
rumen that eat grass
for omnivores which is like what we are
they eat primarily grain
in farming operations and that's a
little bit more complex so it's kind of
a
moving landscape but regenerative as a
word
is the better definition of the whole
life cycle approach of letting
animals and nature work together is it
true that it's possible to have a farm
that doesn't produce sort of is carbon
neutral
we have been third party verified
to be carbon impact negative so
belcampo's 25 000 acres and the animals
here
they in the all of the carbon including
from our shipping
on our mail order is all offset by the
amount of
grazing that's happening also that that
encompasses our partner farms we
we buy a number of live animals in from
other partner farms
that's their impacts also incorporate in
that i mean first of all that's
incredible
and second of all is that possible to
scale i don't see why
it isn't i mean it's it's complex to
scale
but i mean we're putting people on the
moon and you have a robotic dog
i mean but those are that's more that's
less about scale that's more about
innovation
so like in many ways what belcamp has
done is innovative
at a small scale the question is whether
that innovation could be scaled that's
where i feel like
we in the industry need more help you
know the ai piece
the intelligence the the thinking about
ways to do things
differently is where we need more
support and i think it's
been a you know a kind of a
swing in the past couple years where
it's
it meets a mess it's terrible so let's
ditch meat
and our opt for these hyper processed
you know
plant-based solutions and
i am saying there's a way to make meat
this a part of the solution
and it's going to mean eating less of it
it's going to mean paying more for it
it's going to mean that the farming
systems are more complicated
it's not the easiest path but i think in
the long term it's the better path
and it's also better for human health
can you comment on the certified humane
piece so how do you run a farm
like what does it mean to raise an
animal from
the beginning of its life to the end of
its life in a way that's ethical that's
humane
i think the first piece you need to just
be comfortable with is that
making an animal into meat you know is
is something you're comfortable with
because i think that's the biggest
question right
and so certified humane actually goes
all the way through
the death of the animal how it's killed
and handled that at processing
so i put that out there just to say well
that's you know this is all about
producing an animal
to die for me that's not necessarily
that's something people struggle with
with the word humane and i understand
that like i have space and empathy for
that it's a it's a complicated decision
and when you have to be comfortable with
at the outset to say this is an animal
it's going to die to feed me
yeah so we should pause on that because
i actually just uh
the two days ago read a paper that
argued that
you know the killing of an animal period
cannot be humane so it's impossible
and so and that's an argument just like
you're saying
we could make but if we now on the table
kind of
take as a starting point the idea that
it's possible to kill an animal for food
in an ethical way
if we take that as a starting point so
we won't argue about that
it is worth arguing about it elsewhere
and it probably will
i will probably talk to a few vegan
folks and
we'll talk about the vegan diet i'm
fascinated by it as well so i'm torn in
the whole thing
but if we just take that as a starting
point
what then is an ethical humane way to
treat an animal
i look at ethical humane animal
treatment as
the major phases of life so
um conception birth and mothering
diet those are kind of the major touch
points of life
so what we're
looking at is evolutionary approach
which means is the animal eating what it
evolved to eat primarily
is the animal primarily outdoors
which is how all animals evolved um
given
when the climate's appropriate for it
there's certain you know times when you
can't have
animals fully outdoors like here on our
ranch we
um have had issues with like you know
cold weather and things
but um so if you have if you have you
know appropriate weather conditions does
animal outdoors
um is the animal able to nurture and
engage with its young
um those are the kind of key touch
points but it's really the
the birth of it let me start this one
from the scratch um
okay so when i'm looking at when i when
i consider what's humane setting aside
the death part
i look at the evolutionary diet
access to the outdoors and ideally
spending the majority of its life
outdoors
low density so animals spread out
and um engagement with young
social interactions and that's all kind
of social interaction is a cool one
i mean i also read an article that like
they're that like cows for example
have social like they have friends yeah
yeah that's fascinating i mean that
piece with a young
social interaction with young social
interaction with each other
that uh at a basic level i'm sure that
interaction is not as rich as humans
but they're that that piece seems to be
part of the humane picture
and you said also just a quick comment
uh
evolutionary diet meaning the diet that
they were evolved
to have and that's pretty simple you can
look at the physiology of the animal
and figure that out so ruminant species
are
lamb goats and beef and they have five
stomachs
there they evolved eating really low
calorie
high fiber foods that's why they've got
all the stomachs they need a lot of
processing you or i
were to eat grass die in a week right we
our physiology can't handle it
cows were built and evolved to eat this
very low calorie very high fiber very
low density food
and they walk around slowly they're
moving constantly and they're eating it
when we put them on a corn fed diet
that's the opposite of their
evolutionary diet and their systems
really struggle with it
now pigs and chickens are different pigs
and chickens are omnivores
and pigs will happily eat
chickens for example yeah our pigs on
the farm will hunt and kill rattlesnakes
yeah and eat them um you know
it's they're they they have they enjoy
the they enjoy all of it
they're they're they're omnivores so
that you often see and i
i've seen people try to raise like a
grass-fed chicken and
that doesn't exist i mean they need a
higher omnivores
eat everything they're what's called
monogastric they got one stomach
and that one stomach needs higher
density nutrients
so in the case of um chicken if you're
to do
you know look back in american history
and in the 1950s it took you know
commercial chickens took like 54 weeks
to come to full weight
and now it's two and a half weeks in the
in confinement farming on our
in our systems it's like eight to ten
weeks typically
so it's a very you have to give them
some amount of nutrient density
um but there's a the idea that no grain
because you that's a misinformation for
any type of commercial operation
free range regenerative pastured
everything you're going to have to have
a grain feed to get any type of it's
actually
i think for the case of chickens unless
you're in a place with like tons of
natural seeds and
grubs and worms and stuff to eat really
challenging for the chicken
so you got to give them some high
density high calorie food different from
that that's the evolutionary diet
is a really key thing that's the
fundamental thing for health
and it's also interesting because that
the evolutionary diet ties to human
health
i've looked at the nutritional analysis
on on all of our products and
it's the evolutionary diet is
for the case of beef and lamb gets
their omega three to six ratio is the
same as wild game
so it's not like beef is really
radically different from elk
a ruminant species right if you feed
beef and evolutionary diet
their nutritional profile is the same as
wild meat there's a wild room in it
i got a chance to witness neurolink i
don't know if you're familiar with that
company's brain
brain computer interfaces and they have
i got the chance to see
in in person just a bunch of pigs who
had neurolink chips implanted
and taken out those pigs are so happy
with life
i don't know i've never seen a happier
animal uh
i mean because they get to eat you
because you were mentioning sort of
diets and stuff
they basic pigs seem to love a lot of
stuff
if they're easy they're easily made to
be happy i don't know if uh you can
comment on your
thoughts of um
of you know exploring the capacity of
the pig
mind through some of this testing when
you're a link whether that's exciting to
you whether maybe on the humane side
it's a little bit concerning
um if there's something to be said
and sort of like um yeah on the
i don't know if it's even the ethical
side but just because of your connection
to me
and to nature and understanding these
living beings
well pigs are incredibly intelligent so
i'm not surprised that they're a subject
matter for neurolink
um they're smarter than dogs and they're
empathetic and emotional
um and they're we'll go look at our pigs
afterwards and
see but they're they're they're kind of
like joyful and exuberant when they're
in good health
and um so that that makes sense
i i'm interested in open i feel
um that the
kind of bleeding edge agriculture
movement that i'm
you know on the edge of in some ways
we're a larger operator but
we as a movement have to we have to get
into the game we have to move forward in
a way that allows us to scale if we want
to be viable
so i think there has to be openness to
how that can happen yeah and i also
think there needs to be more
thoughtful and noisy data about how
regenerative ranching can sequester
carbon
i mean thousands of american ranchers
are selling carbon credits right now
the data is that valid and they're not
selling carbon credits from like
grassland that just got a fence around
it they're selling carbon credits for
verified data from
animals assisting in carbon
sequestration right so there's got
to be a way to to get the tech community
involved
in ways to help regenerative agriculture
scale in different creative ways
and actually yeah that'd be interesting
if like neuralink somehow has
i mean especially because the elon musk
is involved in kimball mosques
like has his whole effort and
appreciation of
regenerative agriculture that i wonder
if neurolink has a role to play
like exploring the the neurobiology of
the animal
if that somehow will create innovations
that uh
lead to uh improved
uh scaling of regenerative agriculture
it'd be interesting but
you're saying you should be open to all
those possibilities i don't think i
don't know the landscape to know
what yeah but my sense is that it's very
hard
it's very hard and our farming operation
to scale has been
incredibly complex and challenging we
now work with partner farms
i see their operations they're
incredibly complex you know it just
seems like there's got to be a way to
make some of these things
simpler and easier to share information
yeah um
i don't know what that answer is you
know what would be cool
is if we can understand deeper ways to
measure
the happiness of an animal because then
we can optimize
like a certified humane could be
literally an optimization problem just
make sure
as opposed to kind of uh using our
projecting our own human values
actually measuring what the what the
animal is happy doing that could be so
understanding the pig brain
might help us understand pig happiness
and
like reframe what it means for a happy
animal and then maybe it's a lot easier
to make a happy animal
to make the animal happy than we think
it might have to do with a variety of
delicious food in the case
is there something you can say about
grass-fed meat is it all
just out of my own curiosity whenever
people say
sort of grass-fed meat is better for you
are all grass-fed meat
made the same is there different like
le it's like the word organic uh is
there a lot of variety within that
like the way belcampa does it with it
others do it just
more color if you could add to this
whole word and what it means
grass-fed beef has been on grass its
entire life and you want to look for the
words 100 grass-fed
or grass-fed and finished now
the challenge with feeding
beef grass its whole life is that
it gains weight more slowly
although beef didn't evolve eating corn
and things
um it can't eat them and in eating them
it gains weight
more rapidly and has like a version of
like an
inflammatory response if you actually
look inside the rumen
of the animal inside the stomach it's
like
black and shiny inside compared to
grass-fed animals like greens smells
like compost
so the animals themselves their whole
physiology is is damaged by that
food but they also gain weight really
quickly and they put on a lot of fats
like if you or me were to eat
a bunch of processed food compared to
eating a bunch of greens it's the same
impact you're going to blow up
so the problem for grass-fed is
getting the animals to gain weight
they're getting a ton of exercise
they're eating really clean right and
they're super chill
so that's different from the animals
that are kept still
eating really nutrient dense foods and
under a ton of stress
which is a confinement animal so are all
grass-fed meats created the same
the diet yeah nutritional profile
broadly
but the length of time that the animal
lives is extremely important for
the flavor of the meat we're taking
our beef to 24 to 26 months conventional
is around 18 months
so i'm always looking and if you're
evaluating grass-fed animals
you want to get animals that are
typically allowed to live for longer
because their flavor is going to be
better there's going to be a bit more
fat
and their omega ratios also vary
very differently and i've seen omega
ratios you know on our farm
everywhere from one to three to one to
one you ideal as one to one game is
typically one to one or one to two omega
three to sixes
but in operations where you don't have
year-round grass
it's more complicated you know you're
feeding hay and you don't get that three
to six ratio
omega-3s come from green grass um they
they're the fat in greens and so they're
scarce
and costly right so you can have
grass-fed and finished animals that
don't have that perfect ratio because
maybe they're in a climate or for
whatever reasons we've had to do it too
during the droughts do hay finishing
it's not optimal it changes the ratio
but
so there's a little bit of variance
within it i'd say though
the the variance within grass fed is
still
small compared to the variance between
conventional and grass-fed
right so there's definitely things to
look for within it but the
the real difference is between those two
also thing
to notice is that it's not a verified
word okay so grass fed
means animals that have been on grass at
some point in their life
the way the cattle industry is in the
u.s
there's segmentation so there's cow calf
operations
there's then those calves get sold to
stalker operations which raised
animals in their teens basically and
then those get sold to feedlots
and so those three phases that that
first phase of the cow calf is always on
grass
it's mother cows and mom cows are
amazing they can thrive on
anything and still put all their
nutrients into their baby and their
babies will be healthy
so you never are putting weather cows on
really premium pasture
so it's usually just kind of like okay
pasture dirty life if you ever see kind
of like
you know scrubby lots with lots of you
know cows and cats on that's a cow-calf
operation
so there's also a worm a loophole
unfortunately where people use the term
grass fed
and they're actually referring to
animals that at some point in their life
had grass but that might be
pretty far in the rearview mirror so you
need to see look at that uh
grass-fed and finished or grass-fed 100
percent
that ratio of omega-3s to six is it
changes in like a week
on grain wow so it's radically different
unfortunately it's the same thing for
you and me you could eat clean for a
month
you eat you know junk for three days
you're garbage right it's not like you
can just like coast on that
right we know what that's like same
thing for animals our physiology changes
food's the number one way we interact
with our environment yeah
and our body changes really rapidly and
dramatically so
so we know about campo and just the way
sort of this regenerative farming
approach of belcampo and the certified
humane is good for the land
is good for the animal can you comment
on
ways it's good for the human that eats
the meat
is is this meat better for you yes
it's and this is where you know the kind
of focus on the joy
and animals doing yoga and all this sort
of like cynical stuff about
about this type of agriculture say just
like
set that aside you know it really is
better for your health
yeah it's got a better fat ratio it's
less inflammatory
it's got higher protein um it's just
better product
i mean in the case of beef it's lower in
fat
and that fat is a better quality it's
higher in poultry and pork is also
higher in protein so
all the nutritionals are better it's got
higher density of vitamins got higher
density of minerals
and none of this stuff is radically
different than you know it's like not
like
it's the product is is black and white
but their
every metric meaningfully is better in
the right direction
across the board so why wouldn't you i
hesitate
to take anecdotal evidence
as like final scientific conclusions but
it does seem
i've eaten quite a bit of belcampo meat
for example it's just my body seems to
respond
like is less bothered by it meaning like
uh less inflamed i just feel better
because i
mostly eat a meat diet and it does seem
to be a little bit of a difference what
kind of meat i eat
where it comes from i don't know if
that's
my own psychology also i mean there is
an aspect to like
when you know that the meat came from a
good place and all the ways we've
we've defined good you feel better about
it
and that has an effect like decreased
stress so i'm a huge believer in that
like
outside of just nutrition how you feel
about the whole experience is a huge
impact but
it does feel like the meat itself is
actually just leading to less
inflammation for me or like less
like the bloat bloat bloated feeling and
all those negative effects that
could come with me versus like certain
other ground beefs that i eat
like store bought chicken breast
or steak all those kinds of things my my
body is a little bit more
uh works a little bit harder to process
that food it feels like
i don't know if there's science to that
but sort of anecdotally that seems to be
the case omega-6s are a big part of that
for in the case of the
you eat a lot of beef yes you love beef
yeah and so in
a conventional beef product it's a 1 to
30 ratio
of omega-3s to sixes and it can
sometimes 1 to 20 1 to 30 but
that's the wrong direction in our beef
it's
you know as low as one to one right so
that and the omega-6s are what's part of
inflammation
right now you know they the magic in
animals is that they're incredibly
efficient processors
right and in the same way that you know
they the
the body can protect uh us from you know
can process and take out tons of
things that are toxic out of the
environment i mean animals bodies can do
that too
so the beauty of meat is that it can be
pretty clean you know things like
roundup and stuff don't end up in the
meat
when we have antibiotics in our meat
we're not worried about getting like
tetracycline from the chicken breast
what we're worried about is the workers
getting tetracycline the chicken growing
faster than it should the meat being
chewier and not as
high quality so they but the actual
antibiotics don't the animals
great at filtering that right they get
that out so you have to think about
meat not as like contamination of like
oh there's going to be some of that
garbage they used
in the farming in my meat um but it's
the more subtle things it's the fat
ratio it's the protein density
and there's also just i think in my
experience um
there's just more complex flavor and
things that taste
more complex this is you know science
backs this up
they fill you up faster so if you're
looking to limit
you know to to eat for fullness and but
not eat as many calories
more complex foods are the way to do
that and that hit
you know you hit your satiety he'll help
you hit that society so things like i
mean
all the key um you know amino acids that
help you feel full
mostly from meat right so those are
that's part of it like it but all meats
have those
then there's other kind of
micronutrients and things around that
complex flavor that help you feel full
faster
forgive me for this question but it is
kind of an interesting one that
people are curious about what does it
feel like
to be a uh or what does it take to be a
woman
ceo of a meat company i mean you're no
longer ceo of campo but you did you ran
you co-founded belcampo you ran it for
many many years
is there something that you could say in
terms of challenges associated with that
and how did you personally overcome it
said to be a female running a
meat and livestock operation i felt very
alone
a lot you know for a long time um i felt
very
uh like everybody waiting for me
to fail or watching and
assuming that i was like just good at
marketing or whatever else and
and um so it it's taken me
a while to
not internalize that
i think the only reason i've i'm here
is we have our own supply chain in
slaughterhouse and i think had i really
been playing in the broader meat
industry it would have been a shorter
journey you know it would have been very
hard to make it
even get to this phase um
but i do you know i think
the mission is my life's work
the mission of cleaner ingredients that
taste so amazing you don't need to
do too much to them you know i i like
creating food that's
in support of good health yeah and then
secondary to that
it's the environment but like i want
healthy food to be a joy to eat
right and um
that that's you know creating
innovation the space for this company
has been about building
a brand that people understand and is
transparent and
that people believe in in an industry
that's broadly perceived as pretty
corrupt
so those are things i feel enormously
proud of um so you focused on the
mission and the com
the the push back all the mess
the of the industry you try not to
internalize it trying not to let it
affect you
focus on the mission you know and it's
in the joy of it and the part where it's
gotten fun for me has been returning to
what i love about it
and i've only had the privilege of doing
that pretty recently
um so i think for me personally
you know starting i hosted these events
on the farm called meat camps
where i cook and teach people to cook
and and you know
taste and talk about flavor and all the
like sensual aspects of it that i
that are my fire like thank goodness i
did that stuff because
otherwise it was just such a beating you
know so there were parts of it where i
got to feed my fire
and then now in the you know the past
year since resigning i've been
i do all the recipe development i shoot
all the content i
you know taste product i'm developing
all of our new products i launched our
meatballs i'm just about to launch our
chicken meatballs
doing a high protein bone broth like
those are that's what
why i did this was to be able to build
this great product that i could build on
so i'm kind of at that place now um but
it's taken a lot longer
and i think you know looking at the
landscape of
what to do in food this is definitely
we tackled the most complicated problem
well i can imagine you know and did it
look like in the most old-fashioned way
yeah
right so it's been super complex and
then i also look and i'm like yeah and
it's been messy and it's going to
continue to be hard
but i'm proud of having tackled the
heart problems
so the hard problem here is not in the
space of technologies
it's in the space of bringing something
that we've done
for a long long time in our human
history
and uh scaling it
in the face of all the other economic
pressures
like doing so successfully also
communicating to the rest of the world
that this
is a powerful solution so inspiring the
rest of the world that regenerative
farming
like running a company in this kind of
way that's humane for animals
good for the land good for people even
if it costs
like if there's an increased cost to the
meat uh even if that
if you have a broader vision that means
eating less meat overall
that that is that is like inspiring the
world that this is a future we want
and just taking that on and getting that
done
i got a chance to eat a little bit of
cheese which uh
which is a good opportunity to talk
about your experience in italy
he spent some time or as south of europe
i'm not sure if it was italy yeah i
lived in italy but
and uh there's cheese involved right
like what uh what what did you take away
from that experience
both as a chef and as a human being i
moved to europe right after my early 20s
and i
worked as a cheese maker and
i lived in really small rural farms in
the countryside and i got up early and
milked animals
made cheese and i got to live in a
traditional
agricultural society and learn
how they ate so it shaped me as a cook
because it was
a chance to have incredible ingredients
learn how to cook very simple food
i had been immersed and thought that i
wanted to be like a chefy chef right
um because i love food and i love
cooking and i and i was just drawn to
that world
but i don't like um the experience of
that sort of like fancy food experience
is not my
not what what is exciting for me about
it so i
loved working in that environment
because
i got to eat lunches and dinners and
everything with
the farm that i lived on and just
very traditional simple way to eat
the other piece of it is you know i went
to high school in the 90s
child of like the low-fat fat generation
right and
it was just really liberating and
amazing to eat
tons of super fatty foods and um
olive oil all over the place and bleak
slabs of bread and salami
and be in this like vibrant health like
be leaner
you know happy no skin stuff
you know stop getting split ends like i
stopped having flaky nails
like just stuff that had bothered me my
whole life including
like just moodiness and that all just
changed and
granted i was also like living on a farm
in italy and
getting up with the sunlight and like
there were lots of great aspects of my
life
as well that happened in that time but i
was just
immersed in this diet that i realized
like man this is so simple and i also
loved that i had
like you know you'd have dinner and it
was just like some ricotta cheese with
some olive oil some bread and like a
bowl of
fava beans it's like that's dinner and
it kind of broke down my
assumptions too about like dinner always
has to be this you know a protein and a
vegetable and
you know being more fluid and more
seasonal
was exciting for me so i just learned
kind of a lot about
paying attention to food simple
preparation
and the vibrancy of health
that i personally experienced kind of
made me double down on that our mutual
friend andrew huberman mentioned
something offline to me about
something involving the the mob
is there is there something you could
share or is this or or are people going
to hurt if you share this
it's far enough in the rearview mirror i
mean i was
hired by this group in sicily on
and this is you know i was all of like
21 years old
and to get a permit to work there you
have to show that you have a competency
that nobody else in italy has
and that competency for anya farnald at
the time was cheese expert
so it's like this like stupid american
girl being like
going to the consulate so i already knew
that it was like there was something
wobbly about this organization
but i went to work for them and um my
boss from that time
did end up in federal prison for
corruption um
many years later um embezzlement
primarily
but so i was definitely in an
environment that was
um answering to multiple masters
and the best way to put it it was it
wasn't
i couldn't have asked for a better way
to to kind of get with life
and understand how things happen in the
world though you know
of learning as somebody who tends to be
super direct
and um not very subtle it was amazing to
be in this world where like
everybody communicates in multiple
levels like my
we're going to lunch with my boss with
somebody we're going to do a business
deal with and
by the they ordered a glass of wine and
with that
order communicated like disappointment
yeah because that the father the person
who had made that wine
had offended that other guys yeah and
like that level of stuff where
like nothing happened directly i'm like
what are we talking about afterwards i'm
like what happened at lunch it's like oh
i just
you know i told him this by ordering
that whatever you know that kind of
thing
so understand that there's different
ways of communicating um
but it was also you know it it was
interesting to see and i think i you
know it's kind of the struggle that i've
lived again and again in my life
fundamentally what we were doing in that
operation was there's a very traditional
cheese called the raguzano cheese
in southeastern sicily where i lived
raguza and
it was about scaling that operation so
it was european union money
that my boss was also unfortunately
using for other things but fundamentally
it was to take that this type of very
small-scale cheese get them exported
help them scale and we did it
and it was really challenging i learned
a lot about the safety issues and
collaboration issues and creating groups
of farmers
for scale so it's kind of been doing the
same thing again and again
um but sicily it
you know it was also just the first
place where i
would regularly forage for food
yeah you know like there i'd go to
friends houses and we'd like go out and
pick nettles or go out and pick
wild asparagus so every season there was
stuff that you would be gathering and
that was just part of how you lived
and it was part of your your health so
that was i just learned a ton
in that time about like simple eating
and
and and uh really
that healthy food the simpler it is
the better right like this sort of sense
that healthy food isn't in a tiny
packaged granola bar lots of labels lots
of powders it's like the more simple
essential close of the land can actually
lead to optimal health
you've learned to appreciate the
simplicity of food uh
the the the beauty within the simplicity
i think it's because of the first time
that i had amazing
food quality wow okay because
in the where i grew up there wasn't that
food quality like i had some stuff for
my garden and things that were great
but that's the kind of place where when
artichokes in season all of a sudden
there's guys selling artichokes on their
bicycles
in the street and they're just
fresh-picked and you'd get that one
thing
or the torpedo onions or they like so
there's a seasonality and celebration of
things in their peak moment
and you just had that one thing and that
was the first time i'd ever eaten in
that way
you were a judge several times on an
iron chef
how do you judge a good meal
like what uh your own other people's
like what rating system is good
i mean i go on experience and think
about how many of your like most
memorable fantastic meals are like three
star michelin
meals it's more about the experience
right it's more about that slow down who
are you with
um and some of our best meals are like
the most simple things yeah so iron
chef you know those are those were fun
experiences um
it's a lot of sous-vide though it's a
lot of sauces
it's a lot of powders i mean it's kind
of like magic food
so that's not i mean it's incredible to
watch it as science
um but i don't know if those are my most
memorable meals so
the experience is how you judge a good
meal for you personally if you were a
judge of the entirety of the human
experience
in terms of the the culinary journey
that would be like the people you're
eating with
the environment like how you feel
the journey building up to that meal
like the whole thing you can't separate
it out when i was
learning as an apprentice cheese maker
in greece the one of the best meals my
life
is like a bowl of cold sheep milk yogurt
with like a crust of
cold fat on top so like the way that
these fatty you know sheep milk can have
double the percentage of fat than cow
milk so like there's the yogurt and then
there's this crust of fat and then they
pour
the fresh honey over the top and you
just eat like this bowl of
probably top five meals of my life right
i mean it just that's the simplicity
just the best thing and it was the fact
that's in terra cotta and i'd had this
amazing day and
you know all these things come together
but i still remember that feeling and i
think
most of us have those like really great
sensual memories
of food and they're not about
necessarily
that one ex fancy over-the-top
restaurant or something it's really
about the whole context of enjoyment
maybe you can help me with something uh
so we i think offline said
that we're both introverts a bit but i
certainly
find joy in repetition so i kind of hide
away
as an introvert and eat the same thing
over and over and over again
but at the same time i had this
conversation with tyler cohen who's an
economist but he's also a food critic
he writes these incredible posts about
different foods
um and we had this conversation about
what his last meal would be if he had to
choose like what is the best meal he's
ever eaten
that he would want to eat and he had a
good answer about it it had to do with
experience i think
for him it was a particular mexican
restaurant and it had in mexico because
of the ingredients because of the
experience
because of the work it took to get there
and all those kinds of things
but also made me realize like when i was
going home after that conversation
that i couldn't answer that question
myself like
what is the best meal i've ever eaten
because i really haven't experienced
much and so it almost was like
a challenge to myself like i feel like i
should journey out a little bit more
in this life and try stuff and
to try to see like what is the best meal
for me
in the world you know like both the
experience and the taste
right so i was kind of wondering first
i'd love to ask you like what your
last meal would be or what is the
greatest meal you've ever eaten
but also and you're still very young and
so the life is there's still more
experiences to be had right um and for
me
like how do you go about finding the
best meal in the world
is is there a device you could give
essentially
there's that sense of anticipation
right so if it's the best meal i'd say
for
for you it would need to be on the heels
of something where you'd pushed yourself
with a fast or with an athletic event
right or something
like you would be coming into it with a
sense of anticipation because of
deprivation
yeah you would be hungry for it in that
bigger sense of the word like hungry for
deep nutrition on your soul level and
your
as well as your belly so i'd say that
you'd have to think about it as a
as a phase of things like multiple
things um and then i also think
you know you you love me you love cheese
you have to have some things that come
together right like there's got to be
some specific elements of just your
favorite flavors in that
but there could be flavors yet to be
discovered that's a whole other thing
because
i just uh emotionally and physically
feel good
on me but that's not that doesn't mean
like maybe like
a rice based dish like sushi or
something like that
or uh or indian cuisine where it's like
sauces and the breads and whatever
you know i love that stuff too so we're
not talking about like
you know a meal is an experience that
could be
uh like a one-night sand but with a
with a piece of food right it could be a
totally different than what actually
makes you feel
good when you eat it every day yeah
absolutely completely
completely analogous i get that i mean
you also though there's elements of
comfort and love and those different
pieces for you
but i think you got to look at like
where would you go somewhere like would
you go
to a place where you could you know hike
in japan and then end up in a little
place where you'd eat something
that's right that's where i would think
you were going to have that magic moment
yeah you know maybe some place you go to
mongolia
and you're in a in a really extreme
environment for three or four days and
then you come back and you're
in a farm and you get something on the
table that's a surprise and you're
hungry like that's going to be
the moment where you're going to explode
in the instance of like
the culinary level yeah for a lex that
levels up right like that's the journey
for you it has to be
i think from understanding you like a
combination
of that pushing yourself anticipation
and and something about this of some
sort exactly and the environment well i
definitely
definitely like some fasting is part of
a great meal for me so like
24 hours is like the minimum you're
you're more sensitive to the richness of
any experience
for me when i fast 24 hours
like and so that's a requirement for a
good meal is 24 hour fast i think
it's just like you're able to taste i
don't know maybe psychological
but you're able to disassemble the
various flavors
in a meal as simple as like even a
chicken breast there's all kinds of
flavors going on
because like when you cook a chicken
breast there's like
the outside the inside i mean the volume
of the meat tastes different as you
eat like the different fibers and you
can like tell all those differences as
you're eating
when you're you've fasted and you can
appreciate that and of course
you're right part part of the the
journey is important it makes me think
like
whether restaurants is the right place
to explore
or i'm envisioning it on a farm for you
and i'm envisioning it in a place that's
like really
into ag and food you know like even a
place like romania
you know like these incredible farms
right where it's not gonna get any like
fancy restaurants there but you're
probably gonna have some amazing
little cheeses and cured meats and you
might go to some you know have some
experience and end up in a place with
like four things on the plate and each
of them blows your mind yeah you know
like or japan
is another place like that um i think
vietnam laos like i mean those are
countries where there's like these
incredible niche ingredients and
this essentialism around food that's
fascinating or maybe it's in russia with
putin
that might be the best meal with him on
the farm yeah
that'd be uh it's hard to reproduce that
if that is in fact a good meal it'd be
you know it's hard it's hard to get him
out to the farm but maybe one time
maybe the best meal what about you for
me like it's the
it's the ingredients that i associate
with like indulgence like
be fresh bread with like my favorite
cultured butter on it
be food in my childhood i grew up in
oregon we always had salmon
and i'd smoke salmon or salmon eggs like
really good salmon eggs i love
cheese i love goat cheese i love all
kinds of cheese there'd be cheese
i love meat obviously i'm imagining it's
sort of like an
abundance of like 10 things i love it's
not a dish you know it's like all the
yummy
all of your indulgences on the same
plate yeah yeah and there isn't like for
me there's not like a big cake or
something super like that it's like
really yummy things that i love like
really fresh crusty delicious bread
that's warm and it's got a bunch of
butter on it and i can put some salt on
it and
eat a big slab of that that's just
that's where i'm at that's funny and so
meat to you is not
like one of those indulgences oh
definitely that'd definitely be steak
there too i'm just imagining not like
there isn't a specific dish it's like
eight or ten things right it's the fresh
bread
it's something like fishy yummy probably
be
really good fresh berries too there'd be
a steak or a pork chop or something like
meaty and
delicious and savory there'd be some
cheese
just a bunch of different things that i
love to eat that like all kind of check
boxes for me is probably what would make
me happiest
i'm afraid of variety i like the focus
when you can just this is all you have
the scarcity of just this is the one
ingredient
yeah and really appreciating
appreciating it or maybe
one thing like one full complex flavor
whatever the heck that is
it's like the distraction this the
serial dating nature of
having a bunch of things in a plate is
uh
yeah for some reason that prevents me
from fully enjoying any one of them
i don't know why why that is the more
healthy way to do it is the varieties
your your way is the healthier way to do
it is alcohol involved
i don't drink very much okay i like red
wine um
but i just don't really i i love yeah i
love red wine with good food
um and i also co-founded a rum business
um that's an organic rum so i love that
product but that's not
that for me it's like i'm i'm more
interested in the in the food
i'd say is there some connection between
your
chef life cooking and music does this
music have a role in the experience
like i love artistic expression and
that's a
that's always had a role in my life in
the same way i love to paint and draw
and
um all the different things i was a
professional musician when i lived in
sicily
by definition technicality because i
played in the municipal band
so i would march around the town yeah um
with
all the funerals i get like 50 euro
every time i'd like march in a funeral
playing my oboe so
it's given me i like that because i like
to like you were talking about going to
farms like what i quested foreign was
experience and connection
right in places where i could learn
things that's been the through line of
my learning journey i've learned things
and
sought knowledge that i can't get in any
conventional learning environment and so
what are the tools that let me do that
it was like
being adaptable and comfortable in
different cultures but also having
common ground points right
that are that are that are allow you to
connect with people so music's one of
those things
so i love like you know music but i also
you know any
there's any number of enjoy of food
being able to pitch in and help in the
kitchen
um you know to play cards like those are
when you're dealing with getting into
like
farming communities and stuff that stuff
really helps right so
i basically have cultivated tools that
let me drop into places
where i can learn and so those are all
kind of of a piece
those are just tools to get in there
that said we did listen to some justin
bieber earlier today that was uh
i need to get more into them i need to i
need to understand the full complexity
of the biebs
you're trying to achieve what hunting
stands for but at a much larger scale
which is what kind of bill campos stands
for but what are your thoughts on
hunting as a source of meat
it's amazing 100 pro hunting
um i think the reason that hunting flips
a switch
for so many people is because it's the
first time they've had clean meat
in their lives wow okay so i think that
the hunter's journey
when people get so turned on by hunting
they're just like oh my god
i'm never going back yeah i'm saying
that's great if you've got access to
that if you know the guy he'll give you
the backstrap awesome
but like you that's not very that's not
achievable for most of us
yes um and i do think that talking to
hunters about their experiences what
they love about it
many of them are just outdoors and i say
that because most of them are men but
most
love the outdoors aspect of it and being
out in in the wild
but a lot of them it's because of how
they feel when they eat the meat
and it's because they're eating i mean
99 of meat in america is made a very
specific way
and it's in in a way that is pretty
inflammatory
not incredibly delicious and when you're
on that extreme
um and then you toggle to having this
totally different style of product
it feels radically different in your
body so of course you're like i'll never
go back
so when i talk about us being on that
spectrum it's like well it's
hunted me to i mean i can never on any
commercial operation create the variety
of
the biodiversity of species that an elk
gets when it's
wandering around of a zone i mean i
could there's no way you can do that on
a farm so there's always going to be
that extra five or ten percent that
those wild animals are going to have
you know and those wild animals also
fast for longer they go through periods
of starvation
and that creates an even like slower
growth for musculature that's going to
be create even more
unique flavor and characteristics and so
that's why there's that
that extra in the hunted meat but you
can come a lot closer
with regenerative traditional farming to
that flavor and health
um than with any other type of farming i
know so that's where i see it on the
spectrum i love that people are
getting excited about about game because
it's all it's better for your health
it's got all the same characteristics of
regenerative reformed meat
and it gets people turned on to like
simple delicious food
you know you shouldn't have to cover
food with sauce that's got corn syrup
and soy
a bunch of junk in it to make it
palatable if you got to put sauce on
your food you need to look at your
ingredients
you need to revisit what you're starting
from because if you have to
put a bunch of things to mask flavor
onto anything you're eating
you're trying to basically fool your
palate into doing what's not best for
your body
we're trying to to tell our palettes
like just make it through this plate so
you can get the calories in
and we're masking the fact that we don't
actually find it very appetizing
so we're kind of teaching ourselves to
overcome our instinct
with food we're saying here's this kind
of
based substrate not very interesting i'm
not like sparking to it
awesome put sugar and salt on it this up
the hyper-processed flavor profile
great done and then your spark to it
yeah that's not that's a very short road
and that's i think
a lot of the health problems we have now
is because we're
masking flavors and basically trying to
get ourselves to move down this path of
the same way we behave around all hyper
processed foods
yeah and that gets us into a mess with
our health so if we can get
things like game where people love the
flavor out of the gate but it's natural
simple mentally processed like that's a
win
yeah that it reverses that hyper
processing
trend that we're on as a human species
and that's uh that's the promise of
regenerative farming that's the promise
of hunting
obviously the former can be scaled the
hunting
i think cannot be scaled right but in
many ways the hunting
inspires the world that this is the
right way to eat yes
and and that naturally leads to then
uh the humane farming regenerative
farming idea
which is this idea that hunting
represents
how do you scale that well if you look
at like you know we're talking about
people use the sort of marketing
language of like happy cows or
that kind of thing you know if you're
talking about the happiest animals it's
wild animals right
so if you wonder why these practices are
good
talk to hunters you know you're talking
about animals that have lived in their
evolutionary capacity right who have
played their role in the ecosystem
who've
lived their meaning of life right and
that's
a very powerfully different kind of role
than
than livestock production so i think if
we can make our livestock production
as similar to wild as possible then
we're
a lot of steps closer so you said the
animals are happiest in the wild
and that's where they find meaning uh
what about us
the human animal what's the meaning for
us do you think
if you've uh monitored the life cycle of
a lot of living beings you ever look in
the mirror and think like
why the hell are we humans here ah
i mean thriving reducing suffering um
creating goodness i mean those are the
things i see in
in animals behavior they're mostly
interested in
in reducing suffering and and
um nurturing right those are the things
that i think evolutionarily
and we humans are just clever we want to
be able to try to do that at a bigger
and bigger scale
like as much as possible reduce the
suffering in the world
and somehow that alleviates us of our
own suffering
that's the russian thing let life is
suffering and somehow helping others
alleviates it and come up with creative
solutions to do that that's really
interesting
it's almost consciousness is the thing
that
led to suffering but it also led to the
desire to alleviate the suffering
it's a it's a feedback loop
consciousness creates suffering and the
desire to alleviate it
uh is there yet a pretty nonlinear life
your parents were professors you
have done a lot of sort of incredible
things that many would say kind of
like how the hell are you gonna get this
done is there advice you can give
to young people today like high school
college
about uh how to do uh how to live a
similarly non-linear crazy life and
accomplish
be as successful as you have been about
whether it's just their career
or life in general the greatest
gifts i've been given have come from
pursuing curiosity
just trying to understand the thing
you're curious about and allowing
yourself to be curious about and just
going with it and also pursuing things
that are like deeply joyful
for me not what society wants but you
just personally
just on your own you're happy and that's
something that in the times when i
strayed from that
my life has been harder right so
it's fundamentally what are we on earth
to do
you know to live and thrive and
so pursuing things that
are curious and satisfying and
interesting and joyful and allow me to
to grow so the
i made a number of choices to do things
that were more complicated and kind of
not
not considered like so cool at the time
although now
it's cool to work on farms it wasn't
when i started my career in animal
agriculture
and it was like but just deeply
interesting to me
and i felt like there was just lots to
learn and so
that's been the the path for me is like
going for something that's like curious
and hard
and kind of sticking with it and being
open to it and
growing elements that give me joy
through that
so i also you know for people who are
starting out in their careers and want
to do something different too it's like
get out of
your comfort go to a place that you've
got something to learn from and let it
teach you that and you'll
you'll get beat up like i got beat up by
that experience like it was really hard
you know i laugh about now working for
insistently for tease me i mean like and
the funny experiences i had there but it
was hard i was lonely i cried a lot it
was stressful it was like it was hard it
was really hard
when you inside of it you didn't know
how it's going to turn out you didn't
know it's going to
turn out like why didn't i get a job
doing something that all my friends were
doing and
and it and and i didn't speak the
language i had to learn foreign language
and
learn how to function and it like it was
very lonely and very challenging but
then
that's where my resilience started to
grow right so the things i learned there
ended up just being about resilience and
understanding
the language of subtlety and meaning so
that's something that's carried me
through my life
but it was a curiosity about cheese
making and about like just living in a
village that was there i'm like wouldn't
it be amazing just live in a really
rural village and you just went with it
and i just like this seems incredible
and
and have a place where you can you know
and these like the
the people seem interesting the food
seems good and let's just like try this
and see what i can learn
and that like putting yourself out of
your comfort zone
in a place where you have a chance to
learn and grow is
is the the secret because it's you grow
through discomfort
you know people think that you grow when
you get into this environment where
everything's like kind of
sailing along but like growth actually
comes through pain
you know it's like you you know growth
comes from being cut down and beat down
and having to re
regrow and double down and so that kind
of
that kind of opportunity you have to
seek it out you put yourself
in the line of fire but if the situation
sucks
it's a sign that you might be doing
something right in the sense that you're
on the path
at the end of which you'll be a better
person if you allow yourself to grow in
that way like as opposed to resisting it
just uh going along with a journey and
persevering
and that ended us up in this incredible
place
this whole conversation i'll probably
overlay a video
i'm i'm looking at a gorgeous mountain
and
it's an incredible farm thank you so
much for a meal yesterday that was
incredible
the cheese the fish eggs just everything
about this place
uh looking up you can see the stars
the stars at night are beautiful and
there's a peacefulness to it
i had a pretty hard week actually just
emotionally on many ways and just coming
here it's immediately so much of it is
lifted so
i really deeply appreciate anya that you
would invite me here and that you have
this conversation this was
this was really awesome so thank you so
much thank you
thanks for listening to this
conversation with anya fernald and thank
you to
gala games athletic greens four sigmatic
and fundrise check them out in the
description to support this podcast
and now let me leave you with some words
from the ancient chinese philosopher
lao tzu nature does not hurry
yet everything is accomplished thank you
for listening
i hope to see you next time
you