the following is a conversation with
brett weinstein
evolutionary biologist author co-host of
the dark horse podcast
and as he says reluctant radical
even though we've never met or spoken
before this we both felt like
we've been friends for a long time i
don't agree on everything with brett
but i'm sure as hell happy he exists in
this weird and wonderful world of ours
quick mention of our sponsors jordan
harbinger show
expressvpn magic spoon and four sigmatic
check them out in the description to
support this podcast
as a side note let me say a few words
about covet 19
and about science broadly i think
science is beautiful
and powerful it is the striving of the
human mind
to understand and to solve the problems
of the world
but as an institution it is susceptible
to the flaws of human nature
to fear to greed power and ego
2020 is the story of all of these that
has both
scientific triumph and tragedy we needed
great leaders
and we didn't get them what we needed is
leaders who communicate in an
honest transparent and authentic way
about the uncertainty of what we know
and the large-scale scientific efforts
to reduce that uncertainty
and to develop solutions i believe there
are several candidates for solutions
that could have all saved
hundreds of billions of dollars and
lessened
or eliminated the suffering of millions
of people
let me mention five of the categories of
solutions masks
at home testing anonymized contact
tracing
antiviral drugs and vaccines within
each of these categories institutional
leaders should have constantly asked
and answered publicly honestly the
following three questions
one what data do we have on the solution
and what studies are we running to get
more and better data
two given the current data and
uncertainty how effective
and how safe is the solution three what
is the timeline and cost involved
with mass manufacturing distribution of
the solution
in the service of these questions no
voices should have been silenced
no ideas left off the table open data
open science
open honest scientific communication and
debate was the way
not censorship there are a lot of ideas
out there that are bad
wrong dangerous but the moment we have
the hubris
to say we know which ideas those are is
the moment we'll lose our ability to
find the truth
to find solutions the very things that
make science beautiful
and powerful in the face of all the
dangers that threaten the well-being and
the existence
of humans on earth this conversation
with brett
is less about the ideas we talk about we
agree on some disagree on others
it is much more about the very freedom
to talk
to think to share ideas this freedom
is our only hope brett should never have
been censored
i asked brad to do this podcast to show
solidarity
and to show that i have hope for science
and for humanity
this is the lex friedman podcast and
here's my conversation
with brett weinstein what to you
is beautiful about the study of biology
the science the engineering
the philosophy of it it's a very
interesting question i must say
at one level it's not a
conscious thing i can say a lot about
why as an adult i find biology
compelling but
as a kid i was completely fascinated
with animals i loved
to watch them and think about why they
did what they did
and that developed into a very conscious
passion as an adult but i think uh
in the same way that one is drawn to a
person
i was drawn to
the never-ending series of
near-miracles that exists across
biological nature
when you see a living organism do you
see it from an
evolutionary biology perspective of like
this entire thing that moves around in
this world
or do you see like from an engineering
perspective
they're like uh first principles almost
down to the physics like the
little components that build up
hierarchies that you have cells if the
first proteins and cells and
organs and all that kind of stuff so do
you see low level or dc high level
well the human mind is a strange thing
and i think it's probably a bit like a
time sharing machine in which
i have different modules we don't know
enough about biology for them to connect
right so they exist in isolation and i'm
always aware that they do connect but i
basically have to
step into a module in order to see
the evolutionary dynamics of the
creature and the lineage that it belongs
to i have to step into a different
module to think of
that lineage over a very long time scale
a different module still to understand
what the mechanisms inside would have to
look like to account for
what we can see from the outside
and i think that probably sounds
really complicated but one of the things
about being
involved in a topic like biology and
doing so for
one you know really not even just my
adult life for my whole life
is that it becomes second nature and you
know when when we see somebody
do an amazing parkour routine or
something
like that we think about what they must
be doing
in order to accomplish that but of
course what they are doing
is tapping into some kind of zone right
they are
in a zone in which they are in such
um command of their center of gravity
for example
that they know how to hurl it around a
landscape so that they always
land on their feet and
i would just say for anyone who hasn't
found a topic
on which they can develop that kind of
facility it is
absolutely worthwhile it's really
something that human beings are capable
of doing
across a wide range of topics many
things our ancestors didn't even have
access to
and that flexibility of humans that
ability to
repurpose our machinery for
topics that are novel means really
the world is your oyster you can you can
figure out what your passion is and then
figure out
all of the angles that one would have to
pursue to really deeply understand it
and it is uh it is well worth having at
least one topic like that
you mean embracing the full adaptability
of the
both the the body and the mind so like
because i don't know what to attribute
to parkour too
like biomechanics of how our bodies can
move
or is it the mind like how much percent
wise
is it the entirety of the
hierarchies of biology that we've been
talking about or is it just
all the mind the way to think about
creatures is that every creature
is two things simultaneously a creature
is a machine of sorts right it's not a
machine in
in the you know it's it's i call it an
aqueous machine
right and it's run by an aqueous
computer right so it's not
identical to our our technological
machines
but every creature is both a machine
that does things in the world
sufficient to accumulate enough
resources to continue
surviving to reproduce it is also a
potential
so each creature is potentially
for example the most recent common
ancestor of some future clade of
creatures that will look very different
from it
and if a creature is very very good at
being a creature but
not very good in terms of the potential
it has going forward
then that lineage will not last very
long into the future because change
will uh throw at challenges that its
descendants will not be able to meet
so the thing about humans is we are
a generalist platform and
we have the ability to swap out our
software
to exist in many many different niches
and i was once watching a an interview
with
with this british group of parkour
experts who were
being you know just they were discussing
what it is they do and how it works and
what they essentially said is
look you're tapping into
deep monkey stuff right and i thought
yeah that's about right
and you know anybody who
is proficient at something like skiing
or skateboarding
you know has the experience of
flying down the hill on skis for example
bouncing
from the top of one mogul to the next
and
if you really pay attention you will
discover that your conscious mind is
actually a spectator it's there
it's involved in the experience but it's
not driving some part of you knows how
to ski and it's not the part of you that
knows how to think
and i would just say that the
what accounts for this flexibility in
humans
is the ability to bootstrap a new
software program
and then drive it into the unconscious
layer where it can be applied very
rapidly
and you know i will be shocked if the
exact
thing doesn't exist in robotics you know
if you
if you programmed a robot to deal with
circumstances that were novel to it how
would you do it it would have to look
something like this
there's a certain kind of magic you're
right
with the consciousness being an observer
when you play guitar for example
or piano for me music when you get truly
lost in it
i don't know what the heck is
responsible for the flow of the music
the kind of
the loudness of the music going up and
down the timing
the intricate like even the mistakes all
those things that doesn't seem to be the
conscious mind
uh it's it is just observing and yet
it's somehow
intricately involved more like because
you mentioned parkour
the dance is like that too when you
start i've been tango dancing
you if when you truly lose yourself in
it
then it's just like you're an observer
and how the hell is the body able to do
that
and not only that it's the physical
motion is also creating
the emotion the
like that damn is good to be alive
feeling
so but then that's also intricately
connected to the full biology stack
that we're operating in i don't know how
difficult it is to replicate that we
were talking offline about
boston dynamics robots
they've recently been they did both
parkour
they did flips they've also done some
dancing
and something i think a lot about
because what most people
don't realize because they don't look
deep enough is
those robots are hard-coded to do those
things
the robots didn't figure it out by
themselves and yet
the the fundamental aspect of what it
means to be human
is that process of figuring out of
making mistakes
and then there's something about
overcoming those challenges and the
mistakes and like figuring out
how to lose yourself in the magic of the
dancing uh or
just movement is what it means to be
human that learning process
so that's what i want to do with the
with the um
almost as a fun side thing with the the
boston dynamics robots
is to have them learn and see what they
figure out
even if it even if they make mistakes i
want to let
spot make mistakes and in so
doing discover what it means to be alive
discover beauty because i think that's
the essential aspect of mistakes
boston dynamics folks want spot to be
perfect
because they don't want spot to ever
make mistakes because it wants to
operate in the factories it wants to be
you know very safe and so on for me if
you construct the environment
if you construct a safe space for robots
and allow them to make mistakes
something beautiful might be discovered
but that requires a lot of brain power
so spot is currently very dumb and i'm
gonna add
give it a brain uh so first make it c
currently can't see
meaning computer vision he has to
understand his environment has to see
all the humans
but then also has to be able to learn
learn about his movement
learn how to use his body to communicate
with others
all those kinds of things that dogs know
how to do well humans know how to do
somewhat well i think that's a beautiful
challenge but first you have to allow
the robot to make mistakes
well i think um your objective is
laudable but you're going to realize
that the boston
dynamics folks are right the first time
spot poops on your rug
um i hear the same thing about kids and
so on yes i still want to have kids no
you should it's it's a great experience
um so let me step back into what you
said in a couple of different places
one i have always believed that the
missing element
in robotics and artificial intelligence
is a proper development right it is no
accident it is no mere coincidence that
human beings are
the most dominant species on planet
earth and that we have the longest
childhoods of any
creature on earth by far right the
development is the key to the
flexibility
and so the capability
of a human at adulthood is
the mirror image it's the flip side of
our helplessness at birth um so
i'll be very interested to see what
happens in your
robot project if you do not end up
reinventing childhood for robots which
of course is foreshadowed in
2001 quite brilliantly
but i also want to point out you can you
can see
this issue of your conscious mind
becoming a spectator
very well if you compare tennis
to table tennis right if you
watch a tennis game you could imagine
that the players are highly conscious as
they play
you cannot imagine that if you've ever
played ping pong
decently a volley in ping pong is so
fast
that your conscious mind if it had if
your reactions had to go through your
conscious mind
you wouldn't be able to play so you can
detect that your conscious mind
while very much present isn't there and
you can also detect where consciousness
does usefully intrude
if you go up against an opponent in
table tennis
that knows a trick that you don't know
how to respond to
you will suddenly detect that something
about your game
is not effective and you will start
thinking about what might be how do you
position yourself so that move that puts
the ball just in that corner of the
table or something like that
doesn't catch you off guard and
this i believe is we
highly conscious folks those of us who
try to think through things very
deliberately and carefully
mistake consciousness for like the
highest kind of thinking
and i really think that this is an error
consciousness is an
intermediate level of thinking what it
does is it allows you
it's basically like uncompiled code and
it doesn't run very fast it is capable
of being adapted to new circumstances
but once the code
is roughed in right it gets driven into
the unconscious layer and you become
highly effective at whatever it is
and that from that point your conscious
mind basically remains there to detect
things that aren't anticipated by the
code you've already written
and so i don't exactly know how
one would establish this how one would
demonstrate it
but it must be the case that the human
mind
contains sandboxes in which things are
tested
right maybe you can build a piece of
code and run it in parallel
next to your active code so you can see
how it would have done
comparatively but there's got to be some
way of writing
new code and then swapping it in and
frankly i think this has a lot to do
with things like sleep cycles very often
you know when i get good at something i
often don't get better at it while i'm
doing it i get better at it when i'm not
doing it especially if there's time to
sleep and think on it
so there's some sort of you know new
program swapping in for old program
phenomenon
which um you know will be a lot easier
to see
in machines it's going to be hard with
the the the wet wear
i like i mean it is true because
somebody that played i played tennis for
many years
i do still think the highest form of
excellence in tennis
is when the conscious mind is a
spectator
so it's the compiled code is the
highest form of being human and then
consciousness is just some
like specific compiler he has to have
like borland c
plus plus compile you could just have
different kind of compilers
ultimately the the thing that by which
we measure
the the power of life the intelligence
of life is the compiled code and you can
probably do that compilation all kinds
of ways
yep yeah i'm not saying that tennis is
played consciously and table tennis
isn't i'm saying that because
tennis is slowed down by the just the
space on the court
you could you could imagine that it was
your conscious mind playing
but when you shrink the court down it
was obvious it becomes
obvious that your conscious mind is just
present rather than
knowing where to put the paddle and
weirdly for me
um i would say this probably isn't true
in a podcast situation
but if i have to give a presentation uh
especially if i have not overly prepared
i often find the same phenomenon when
i'm giving the presentation my conscious
mind is there watching some other part
of me present
which is a little jarring i have to say
well that means you've you've gotten
good at it
not let the conscious mind get in the
way of the flow of words
yeah that's that's the sensation to be
sure and that's the highest form of
podcasting too i mean that's why i have
that that's what it looks like when a
podcast is really in the pocket like
like joe rogan just having fun
and just losing themselves and that's
that's something i aspire to as well
just
losing yourself in the conversation
somebody that has a lot of anxiety with
people like i'm
such an introvert i'm scared i was
scared before you showed up i'm scared
right now
um there's just anxiety there's just
it's a giant mess
uh it's hard to lose yourself it's hard
to just
get out of the way of your own mind yeah
actually uh
trust is a big component of that your
your conscious mind
retains control if you are very
uncertain
um but when you do when you do get into
that zone when you're speaking
i realize it's different for you with
english as a second language although
maybe you present in russian
and you know and it happens but do you
ever hear yourself say something and you
think
oh that's really good right like like
you didn't come up with it some other
part of you that you don't exactly know
came up with it i i don't think i've
ever
heard myself in that way because i have
a much louder voice
that's constantly yelling in my head at
why the hell did you say that there's a
very self-critical voice
that's much louder so i'm very
maybe i need to deal with that voice but
it's been like without what is it called
like a megaphone just screaming so i
can't hear you oh no
good job you said that thing really
nicely so i'm kind of focused right now
on on the megaphone person
in the audience versus the deposit but
that's definitely something to think
about it's been productive
but you know the the place where i find
gratitude
and beauty and appreciation of life is
in the quiet moments
when i don't talk when i listen to the
world around me when i listen to others
i'm when i talk i'm extremely
self-critical
in my mind uh when i when i produce
anything out into the world
that's that originated with me like any
kind of creation
extremely self-critical it's good for
productivity for like always striving to
improve and so on
it might be bad for for like
just appreciating the things you've
created i'm a little bit with marvin
minsky on this where he says the the key
to um to a productive life is to hate
everything you've ever done
in the past i didn't know he said that i
must say i resonate with it a bit
and you know i i unfortunately my life
currently has me putting a lot of stuff
into the world and i effectively
watch almost none of it i can't stand it
yeah what what do you make of that i
don't know i just recently i just
yesterday
read um metamorphosis by cough we read
metamorphosis by kafka where he turns
into jan bug
because of the stress that the world
puts on him
his parents put on him to succeed and
you know
i think that's you have to find the
balance because
if you if you allow the self-critical
voice to become too heavy the burden of
the world the pressure
that the world puts on you to be the
best version of yourself and so on to
strive
then you become a bug and that's a big
problem
and then uh and then every and then the
world turns against you
because you're a bug you become some
kind of caricature of yourself
uh i don't know become the worst version
of yourself
and then thereby end up destroying
yourself and then the world moves on
that's the story that's a lovely story
i do think this is one of these places
and frankly you could
map this on to all of modern human
experience but this is one of these
places where our
ancestral programming does not serve our
modern selves
yeah so i used to talk to students about
the question of
dwelling on things you know dwelling on
things is famously
understood to be bad and it can't
possibly be bad
it wouldn't exist a tendency toward it
wouldn't exist if it was bad
so what is bad is dwelling on things
past the point
of utility and you know that's obviously
easier to say than to operationalize but
if you realize
that your dwelling is the key in fact to
upgrading your program for
future well-being and that there's a
point you know
presumably from diminishing returns if
not counter productivity
there is a point at which you should
stop because that is what is in your
best interest
then knowing that you're looking for
that point is useful
right this is the point at which it is
no longer useful for me to dwell on this
error i have made
right that is that's what you're looking
for and um it also gives you license
right if some part of you feels like it
you know is punishing you rather than
searching then that also has a
point at which it's no longer valuable
and there's some liberty in realizing
yep even the part of me that was
punishing me knows it's time to stop
so if we uh map that onto compiled code
discussion as a computer science person
i find that very compelling
you know there's a when you compile code
you get warnings
sometimes and usually
if you're a good software engineer
you're going to make sure there's no
you know you treat warnings as errors so
you make sure that the compilation
produces no warnings
but a certain point when you have a
large enough system you just let the
warnings go
it's fine like i don't know where that
warning came from
but you know it's just uh
ultimately you need to compile the code
and and run with it and uh hope nothing
terrible happens well i think what you
will find and believe me i think
what you're what you're talking about
with respect to
robots on learning is going to end up
having to go to a
deep developmental state and a
helplessness that evolves into hyper
competence and all of that
but um i live
i noticed that i live by something that
i for lack of a better
descriptor call the theory of close
calls
and the theory of close calls says that
people
typically miscategorize the
events in their life where something
almost went wrong
and you know for example if you i have a
friend who um
i was walking down the street with my
college friends and one of my friends
stepped into the street thinking it was
clear and was
nearly hit by a car going 45 miles an
hour would have been an
absolute disaster might have killed her
certainly would have
permanently injured her but she didn't
you know car didn't touch her right now
you could
walk away from that and think nothing of
it because well what is there to think
nothing happened or you could think well
what is the difference between what did
happen
and my death the difference is luck
i never want that to be true right i
never want the difference between what
did happen
and my death to be luck therefore i
should count this as very close to death
and i should prioritize coding so it
doesn't happen again at a very high
level
so anyway my my basic point is
the accidents and disasters and
misfortune
describe a distribution that tells you
what's really likely to get you in the
end and so
personally you can use them to figure
out where the dangers are so that you
can afford to take great risks because
you have a really good sense of how
they're going to go wrong
but i would also point out civilization
has this problem
civilization is now producing these
events
that are major disasters but they're not
existential scale
yet right they're very serious errors
that we can see
and i would argue that the pattern is
you discover that we are involved in
some industrial process
at the point it has gone wrong right so
i'm now always asking the question okay
in light of the fukushima triple
meltdown
the financial collapse of 2008 the
deepwater horizon
blowout covet 19 and its probable
origins
in the wuhan lab what processes do i not
know the name of yet
that i will discover at the point that
some gigantic accident has happened and
can we talk about the wisdom
or lack thereof of engaging in that
process before the accident right that's
what a wise civilization would be doing
and yet we don't i just want to mention
something that happened
a couple of days ago i don't know if you
know who jb
strawball is he's the co-founder of
tesla cto of tesla for many many years
his wife just died she was riding a
bicycle
and in the same in that same thin
line between death and life that many of
us have been
in where you walk into the intersection
and there's this close call
every once in a while
it you get um
short straw i wonder how much
of our own individual lives and the
entirety of the human civilization
rests on this little roll of the dice
well this is sort of my point about the
close calls is that there's a there's a
level at which we can't control it right
the
gigantic asteroid that comes from deep
space that you don't have time to do
anything about
there's not a lot we can do to hedge
that out or at least not short term
but there are lots of other things you
know obviously
the financial collapse of 2008 didn't
break down the entire world economy it
threatened to but a herculean effort
managed to pull us back
from the brink the triple meltdown at
fukushima
was awful but every one of the seven
fuel pools
held there wasn't a major fire that made
it impossible to manage the disaster
going forward
we got lucky you know we could say the
same thing about the
the blowout at the deepwater horizon
where
a hole in the ocean floor large enough
that we couldn't have plugged it could
have opened up all of these things
could have been much much worse right
and i think we can say the same thing
about covet as terrible as it is
and i you know we cannot say for sure
that it came from the wuhan lab but
there's a strong likelihood that it did
and it also could be much much worse
so in each of these cases something is
telling us
we have a process that is unfolding that
keeps creating risks where it is luck
that is the difference between
us and some scale of disaster that is
unimaginable
and that wisdom you know you can be
highly intelligent and cause these
disasters
to be wise is to stop causing them right
and that would require
a process of restraint
a process that i don't see a lot of
evidence of yet so
i think we have to generate it and
somehow
we you know at the moment we don't have
a political structure
that would be capable of
taking a protective algorithm and
actually deploying it
right because it would have important
economic consequences and so it would
almost certainly be shot down
but we can obviously also say you know
we paid a huge price
for all of the disasters that i i've
mentioned
and we have to factor that into the
equation something can be very
productive short term and very
destructive long term
also the question is how many disasters
we avoided
because of the ingenuity of humans
or just the integrity and character of
humans
that's sort of an open question we may
be more
intelligent than lucky that's the hope
because the optimistic message here that
you're getting at is
maybe the process that we should be
that maybe we can overcome luck with
ingenuity
meaning i guess you're suggesting the
process is we should be
listing all the ways that human
civilization can destroy itself
uh assigning likelihood to it and
thinking through how can we avoid that
and being very honest
with the data out there about the close
calls
and using those close calls to uh
to then create sort of mechanism by
which we
minimize the probability of those close
calls and just being
honest and transparent with the data
that's out there
well i think we need to do a couple
things for it to work
so i've been an advocate for the idea
that sustainability
is actually it's difficult to
operationalize but it is an objective
that we have to
meet if we're to be around long term and
i realize that we also need to have
reversibility of all of our processes
because processes very frequently when
they start do not appear
dangerous and then they when they scale
they become very dangerous so for
example
if you imagine the
first internal combustion engine in a
vehicle driving down the street
and you imagine somebody running after
them saying hey if you do enough of that
you're going to alter the atmosphere and
it's going to change the temperature of
the planet it's preposterous
right why would you stop the person
who's invented this marvelous new
contraption but of course eventually you
do get to the place where you're doing
enough of this
that you do start changing the
temperature of the planet so
if we built the capacity if we basically
said look you can't
involve yourself in any process that you
couldn't reverse if you had to
then progress would be slowed but our
safety would go up
dramatically and i think
i think in some sense if we are to be
around long term we have to begin
thinking that way we're just involved in
too many very dangerous processes
so let's talk about one of the things
that
if not threatened human civilization
certainly
heard it at a deep level which is
covid19
what percent probability would you
currently place
on the hypothesis that covet 19 league
from the
wuhan institute of virology so i
maintain
a flow chart of all the possible
explanations
and it doesn't break down exactly that
way
the likelihood that it emerged from a
lab is very very high
if it emerged from a lab the likelihood
that the lab was the wuhan institute is
very very high
the there are multiple different kinds
of evidence that point
the lab and there is literally no
evidence that points to nature
either the evidence points nowhere or it
points to the lab
and the lab could mean any lab but
geographically obviously
the labs in wuhan are the most likely
and the lab that was most directly
involved with research
on viruses that look like covid that
look like sarsko v2
is obviously the place uh that one would
start
but i would say the likelihood that this
virus
came from a lab is well above 95
we can talk about the question of could
a virus have been brought into the lab
and escape from there without being
modified that's also
possible but it doesn't explain any of
the anomalies in the genome
of sarsko v2
could it have been delivered from
another lab could wuhan be a distraction
um in order that we would connect the
dots in the wrong way
that's conceivable i currently have that
below one percent on my flow chart but i
have a very dark
thought that somebody would would do
that almost as a
a political attack on china well it
depends
i don't even think that's one
possibility
sometimes when eric and i talk about
these issues we will
generate a scenario just to prove that
something could
could live in that space right it's a
placeholder for whatever
may actually have happened and so it
doesn't have to have been
an attack on china that's certainly one
possibility
but i would point out if you can predict
the future in some unusual way
better than others you can print money
right that's what markets that allow you
to bet for or against
virtually any sector allow you to do so
you can imagine a
simply amoral person or entity
generating a pandemic attempting to
cover their tracks because it would
allow them to bet against
things like you know cruise ships air
travel
whatever it is and bet in favor of i
don't know
uh sanitizing gel
and whatever else you would do so
am i saying that i think somebody did
that no i really don't think it happened
we've seen
zero evidence that this was
intentionally released
however were it to have been
intentionally released by somebody who
did not know
did not want it known where it had come
from
releasing it into wuhan would be one way
to cover their tracks so
we have to leave the possibility
formally open but
acknowledge there's no evidence so and
the probability therefore is law i tend
to believe
maybe this is the optimistic nature that
i have that
people who are competent enough to do
the kind of thing we just described
are not going to do that because it
requires a certain kind of i don't want
to use the word evil but whatever word
you want to use to describe the kind of
uh this regard for human life required
to do that
you're just that that that's just not
going to be coupled
with competence i feel like there's a
trade-off chart
where competence on one axis and evil is
on the other
and the more evil you become the the
the crappier you are at doing great
engineering scientific work required
to deliver weapons of different kinds
whether it's bioweapons or nuclear
weapons all those kinds of things
that seems to be the lessons i i take
from history but that doesn't
necessarily mean that's
what's going to be happening in the
future
but to stick on the lab leak idea
because the flow chart is probably huge
here because there's a lot of
fascinating
possibilities one question i want to ask
is what would evidence for natural
origins look like
so one piece of evidence
for natural origins is um that
it has happened in the past
that that viruses have jumped
oh they do jump they so like that's one
like that's possible to have happened
you know so that that's a sort of like a
historical evidence like okay
well it's possible that it hap it's not
it's not evidence of the kind you think
it is it's a justification for a
presumption
right right so the presumption upon
discovering a new virus circulating is
certainly that it came from nature
right the problem is the presumption
evaporates in the face of evidence or at
least it logically should
and it didn't in this case it was
maintained by people who
privately in their emails acknowledged
that they had
grave doubts about the natural origin of
of this virus
is there some other piece of evidence
that we could
look for and see that would say
this increases the probability that it's
natural origins
yeah in fact there is evidence you know
i always worry that somebody is going to
make up some evidence in order to
reverse the flow
boy well let's say i am a lot of
incentive for that actually there's a
huge amount of incentive on the other
hand
why didn't the powers that be the powers
that lied to us about weapons of mass
destruction in iraq why didn't they ever
fake
weapons of mass destruction in iraq
whatever force it is
i hope that force is here too and so
whatever evidence we find is real
it's the competence thing i'm talking
about but okay go ahead sorry
well we can get back to that but i would
say yeah the the the
giant piece of evidence that will shift
the probabilities in the other direction
is the discovery of either a human
population in which the virus circulated
prior to showing up in wuhan that would
explain where the virus learned all of
the tricks that it knew
instantly upon spreading from wuhan so
that would do it or an animal population
in which an ancestor epidemic can be
found
in which the virus learned this before
jumping to humans but i point out in
that
second case you would certainly expect
to see
a great deal of evolution in the early
epidemic which we don't see
so there almost has to be a human
population somewhere else that had the
virus circulating or an ancestor of the
virus that we first saw in wuhan
circulating and it has to have gotten
very sophisticated in that prior
epidemic
before hitting wuhan in order to explain
the total lack of evolution
and extremely effective virus that
emerged
at the end of 2019. so you don't believe
in the magic of evolution to spring up
with all the tricks already there
like everybody who doesn't have the
tricks they die quickly
and then you just have this beautiful
virus that comes in with a spike protein
and the
and the through mutation uh and
selection
just do like the ones that succeed
and succeed big are the ones that are
going to just spring into life with the
tricks
well no that's that's called a hopeful
monster
and hopeful monsters don't work it's too
the job of
becoming a new pandemic virus is too
difficult it involves two very difficult
steps and they both have to work one
is the ability to infect a person and
spread in their tissues
sufficient to make an infection and the
other is to jump between individuals
at a sufficient rate that it doesn't go
extinct for one reason or another
those are both very difficult jobs they
require as you describe
selection and the point is selection
would leave
a mark we would see evidence that it was
in animals or humans
both right and you see this evolutionary
trace of uh
of the virus gathering the tricks up
yeah you would see the virus
you would see the clumsy virus get
better and better and yes i am a full
believer in the power of that process in
fact i believe it
uh what i know from studying the process
is that it is much more powerful than
most people imagine that what we teach
in the evolution 101 textbook is too
clumsy a process to do what we see it
doing and that actually people should
increase their expectation of the
rapidity with which
that process can produce just
jaw-dropping
adaptations that said we just don't see
evidence that it happened here which
doesn't mean it doesn't exist but it
means in spite of immense pressure to
find it somewhere
there's been no hint which probably
means it took place
inside of a laboratory so inside the
laboratory
gain of functional research on viruses
and i believe
most of that kind of research is doing
this exact thing that you're
referring to which is accelerated
evolution and just watching evolution do
its thing and a bunch of viruses
and seeing what kind of uh tricks get
developed
the other method is
engineering viruses so manually adding
on the tricks
what which do you think we should be
thinking about
here so mind you i learned what i know
in the aftermath of this pandemic
emerging i started studying the question
and i would say based on the content of
the genome and other evidence in
publications from the various labs that
were
involved in in generating this
technology
a couple of things seem likely this
sarsko v2 does not appear to be entirely
the result
of either a splicing process
or serial passaging it appears to have
both
things in its past or it's at least
highly likely that it does
so for example the fern cleavage site
looks very much like it
was added in to the virus and it was
known that that would increase its
infectivity
in humans and increase its tropism
the virus appears
to be excellent at spreading in
humans and minks and ferrets
now minks and ferrets are very closely
related to each other and ferrets are
very likely to have been used in a
serial passage experiment
the reason being that they have an ace2
receptor that looks very much like the
human as2 receptor and so
were you going to passage the virus or
its ancestor
through an animal in order to increase
its infectivity in humans which would
have been necessary
ferrets would have been very likely it
is also quite likely that humanized mice
were utilized and it is possible that
human airway tissue
was utilized i think it is vital that we
find out what the protocols were if this
came from the wuhan
institute we need to know it and we need
to know what the protocols were
exactly because they will actually give
us some tools that would be useful
in fighting sars kovi 2 and hopefully
driving it to extinction which ought to
be our priority
it is a it's a priority that does not it
is not apparent from our behavior
but it really is uh it should be our
objective if we understood where our
interests lie
we would be much more focused on it but
those protocols would tell us a great
deal if it wasn't the wuhan institute we
need to know that
if it was nature we need to know that
and if it was some other laboratory we
need to figure out
who what and where so that we can
determine what is
what we can determine about about what
was done you're opening
up my mind about why we should
investigate why we should know the truth
of the origins of this virus so for me
personally let me just tell the story of
my own kind of journey
when i first started looking into the
lab leak hypothesis
what became terrifying to me and
important to under
understand and obvious is the
sort of like sam harris way of thinking
which is
it's obvious that a lab leak of a deadly
virus will eventually happen
my mind was it doesn't even matter
if it happened in this case it's obvious
that it's going to
happen in the future so why the hell are
we not freaking out about this
and kova 19 is not even that deadly
relative to the possible future viruses
it's this the way i disagree with sam on
this but he thinks about this way about
agi as well
about artificial intelligence it's a
different discussion i think but with
viruses it seems like something that
could happen
on the scale of years maybe a few
decades
agi is a little bit farther out for me
but it seemed
the terrifying thing it seemed obvious
that
this will happen very soon for a much
deadlier virus
as we get better and better at both
engineering viruses
and doing this kind of evolutionary
driven research gain and functional
research
okay but then you started
speaking out about this as well but also
started to say no no we should hurry up
and figure out the origins
now because it will help us figure out
how to actually
respond uh to this particular virus how
to treat this particular virus
what is in terms of vaccines in terms of
antiviral drugs in terms of
just and although the the
the number of responses we should have
okay
i still am much more freaking out about
the future
maybe you can break that apart a little
bit
which are you most
focused on now which
are you most freaking out about now in
terms of the importance of figuring out
the origins of this virus
i am most freaking out about both of
them
because they're both really important
and you know we can put bounds on this
let me say first this is a perfect test
case for the theory of close calls
because as much as
covet is a disaster it is also a close
call from which we can learn much
you are absolutely right if we keep
playing this game in the lab
if we are not if we are especially if we
do it under pressure and when we are
told that a virus is going to leap from
nature
any day and that the more we know the
better we'll be able to fight it we're
going to create the disaster
all the sooner so yes that should be
an absolute focus the fact that there
were people saying that this was
dangerous back in
2015 ought to tell us something the fact
that the system
bypassed a ban and offshored the work to
china
ought to tell us this is not a chinese
failure this is a failure of something
larger and harder to see
but i also think that there's a there's
a
clock ticking with respect to sars kovi
ii
and covid the disease that it creates
and that has to do with whether or not
we are stuck with it permanently
so if you think about the cost to
humanity of being stuck with influenza
it's an immense cost year after year and
we just stopped thinking about it
because
it's there some years you get the flu
most years you don't maybe you get the
vaccine to prevent
it maybe the vaccine isn't particularly
well targeted
but imagine just simply doubling that
cost
imagine we get stuck with sars kovi 2
and its descendants
going forward and that it just settles
in and becomes a fact of
modern human life that would be a
disaster right the number of people we
will ultimately lose is incalculable
the amount of suffering that will be
caused is incalculable the loss of
well-being and wealth incalculable so
that ought to be a very high priority
driving this extinct before it becomes
permanent
and the ability to drive extinct goes
down
the longer we delay effective responses
to the extent that we let it have this
very large canvas
large numbers of people who have the
disease in which
mutation and selection can result in
adaptation that we will not be able to
counter
the greater its ability to figure out
features of our immune system and use
them
to its advantage so i'm feeling the
pressure
of driving it extinct i believe we could
have driven it extinct
six months ago and we didn't do it
because of very mundane concerns among a
small
number of people and i'm not alleging
that
they were brazen about
um or that they were callous about
deaths that would be caused
i have the sense that they were working
from a kind of autopilot
in which you you know let's say you're
in some kind of a corporation a
pharmaceutical corporation
you have a portfolio of
therapies that in the context of a
pandemic might be very lucrative
those therapies have competitors you of
course want to position your product so
that it
succeeds and the competitors don't and
lo and behold at some point
through means that i think those of us
on the outside can't really
intuit you end up saying things about
competing therapies that work
better and much more safely than the
ones you're selling
that aren't true and do cause people to
die in large numbers
but it you know it's some kind of
autopilot at least part of it is
so the there's a complicated coupling of
the autopilot
of uh institutions
companies governments and then there's
also the geopolitical game
theory thing going on where you want to
keep secrets
it's the chernobyl thing where if you
messed up
there's a big incentive i think to hide
the fact that you messed up so how do we
fix
this and what's more important to fix
the autopilot
which is the response that we often
criticize
about our institutions especially the
leaders in those institutions anthony
fauci and so on
uh some of the members of the scientific
community
and the second part is the
the game with china of hiding the
information
in terms of on the fight between nations
well in our live streams on dark horse
heather and i have been talking from the
beginning
about the fact that although yes what
happens
began in china it very much looks like a
failure of the international
scientific community and that's
frightening
but it's also hopeful in the sense that
actually if we did the right thing now
we're not navigating a puzzle about
chinese responsibility we're navigating
a question of collective responsibility
for something that has been
terribly costly to all of us so
that's not a very happy process but as
you point out
what's at stake is in large measure at
the very least
the strong possibility this will happen
again and that at some point it will be
far
worse so you know just as a person that
does not learn
the lessons of their own errors doesn't
get smarter and they remain
in danger we collectively humanity has
to say well
there sure is a lot of evidence that
suggests that this is a self-inflicted
wound
when you have done something that has
caused a massive self-inflicted
wound self-inflicted wound it makes
sense
to dwell on it exactly to the point that
you have learned the lesson that makes
it
very very unlikely that something
similar will happen again
i think this is a good place to kind of
ask you to do almost like a thought
experiment
or to steal man
the argument against the lab leak
hypothesis
so if you were to
argue you know you said 95 percent
chance
that it the virus leaked from a lab
there's a bunch of ways i think you can
argue
that even talking about it
is uh bad for the world
so i if i just put something on the
table
it's to say that um
for one it would be racism versus
chinese people
that talking about that a leak from a
lab there's a kind of
immediate kind of blame and it can
spiral down into this idea that's
somehow the people are responsible for
the virus and
this kind of thing is it possible for
you to come up with other
steel man arguments against
talking or against the possibility of
the lab leak hypothesis
well so i think steel manning is a tool
that is extremely valuable but it's also
possible to abuse it i think that you
can only steal man a good faith
argument and the problem is we now know
that we have not been engaged
in opponents who are wielding good faith
arguments because privately
their emails reflect their own doubts
and what they were doing publicly was
actually
a punishment a public punishment for
those of us who spoke up
with i think the purpose of either
backing us down or more likely
warning others not to engage in the same
kind of behavior and obviously for
people like you and me who
regard science as our likely best hope
for navigating difficult waters shutting
down people who are using those tools
honorably is itself dishonorable
so i i don't really i don't feel that it
is
i don't feel that there's anything to
steal man and
i also think that you know immediately
at the point that the world
suddenly with no new evidence on the
table switched
years with respect to the lab leak you
know at the point that nicholas wade had
published his article and suddenly the
world was going to admit
that this was at least a possibility if
not a likelihood
we got to see something of the
rationalization process that had taken
place
inside the institutional world and it
very definitely involved the claim
that what was being avoided was the
targeting
of chinese scientists
and my point would be i don't want to
see the targeting of
anyone i don't want to see racism of any
kind on the other hand
once you create license to lie
in order to protect individuals
when the world has a stake in knowing
what happened
then it is inevitable that that process
that license to lie
will be used by the thing that captures
institutions for its own purposes so
my sense is it may be very unfortunate
if the story of what happened here can
be
used against uh chinese people
that would be very unfortunate and as i
think i mentioned
heather and i have taken great pains to
point out that this doesn't look like a
chinese failure it looks like a failure
of the international scientific
community so
i think it is important to broadcast
that message along with the analysis
of the evidence but no matter what
happened we have a right to know
and um i frankly do not take the
institutional layer at its word
that its motivations are honorable and
that it was protecting
you know good-hearted scientists at the
expense of the world that that
explanation does not add up well this is
a
very interesting question about whether
it's ever okay to lie
at the institutional layer to
protect the populace
i think both you and i are probably on
the same
have the same sense that it's a slippery
slope
even if it's an effective mechanism in
the short term in the long term
it's going to be destructive this
happened with masks
this happened with with other things if
you look at just history pandemics
there is um there's an idea that panic
is destructive amongst the populace so
you you
want to construct a narrative whether
it's a lie or not
to minimize panic
but you're suggesting that almost in all
cases and i think that was
the lesson from the the pandemic
in the early 20th century that
lying creates distrust and distrust
in the institutions is ultimately
destructive
that's your sense that lying is not okay
well
okay you know there are obviously places
where
complete transparency is not a good idea
right to the extent that you
broadcast a technology that allows one
individual
to hold the world hostage right
obviously
you've got a something to be navigated
but
in general i don't believe that the
scientific system
should be lying to us
in the case of this particular lie
the idea that the well-being of chinese
scientists outweighs the well-being of
the world
is preposterous yeah right as you as you
point out
one thing that rests on this question is
whether we continue to do this kind of
research
going forward and the scientists in
question all of them american
chinese all of them were pushing the
idea
that the risk of a zoonotic spillover
event causing a major and highly
destructive pandemic was so great
that we had to risk this now if they
themselves have caused it
and if they are wrong as i believe they
are about the likelihood of a major
world pandemic spilling out of nature
in the way that they uh wrote into their
grant applications
then the danger is you know the call is
coming from inside the house
and we have to look at that
and yes whatever we have to do to
protect
scientists from retribution we should do
but we cannot protecting them by lying
to the world and even
worse by
demonizing people like
me like uh josh rogan
like yuri dagan the entire drastic group
on
twitter by demonizing us for simply
following the
evidence is to set a terrible precedent
right you're demonizing people for using
the scientific method to evaluate
evidence
that is available to us in the world
what a terrible crime it is to
teach that lesson right thou shalt not
use scientific tools
no i'm sorry whatever your license to
lie is it doesn't extend to that
yeah i've seen the the attacks on you
the pressure on you
has a very important effect on
thousands of world-class biologists
actually at mit colleagues of mine
people i know there's a there's a slight
pressure
to not be allowed to uh
one speak publicly and to
actually think like
to even think about these ideas it
sounds kind of ridiculous but just the
in the in the privacy of your own home
to to read things to
to think it's many people many
world-class
biologists that i know will just avoid
looking at the data there's not even
that many people that are publicly
opposing gain of function research
they they're they're also like it's not
worth it
it's not worth the battle and there's
many people that kind of argue that
those battles should be fought in
private
in uh um you know with colleagues in the
um
in the privacy of the scientific
community that the public is somehow not
maybe intelligent enough to be able to
deal with the the complexities of this
kind of discussion
i don't know but the final result is
combined with the bullying of you
and uh all the different pressures in
the academic institutions is that
it's just people are self-censoring and
silencing themselves
and silencing the most important thing
which is the power of their brains
like these people are brilliant
and the fact that they're not utilizing
their brain to come up with solutions
uh outside of the conformist line of
thinking
is tragic well it is i also think
that it we have to look at it and
understand it for what it is
for one thing it's kind of a cryptic
totalitarianism
somehow people's sense of what they're
allowed to think about talk about
discuss
is causing them to self-censor and i can
tell you it's causing many of them to
rationalize which is even worse they are
blinding themselves to what they can
see but it is also the case i believe
that what you're describing about what
people said and a great many
people understood that the lab leak
hypothesis could not be taken off the
table
but they didn't say so publicly and i
think
that their discussions with each other
about why they did not say what they
understood
that's what capture sounds like on the
inside
i don't know exactly what force captured
the institutions
i don't think anybody knows for sure out
here in public
i don't even know that it wasn't just
simply a process but
you have these institutions they are
behaving
towards a kind of somatic obligation
they have
lost sight of what they were built to
accomplish
and on the inside the way they avoid
going back to their original mission is
to say things to themselves
like the public can't have this
discussion it can't be trusted with it
yes we need to be able to talk about
this but it has to be private whatever
it is they say to themselves that is
what capture sounds like on the inside
it's
a institutional rationalization
mechanism
and it's very very deadly and at the
point you go from
lab leak to repurposed drugs you can see
that it's very deadly
in a very direct way yeah i see this on
in my
field of with uh things like autonomous
weapon systems
people in ai do not talk about the use
of ai in weapon systems
they they kind of avoid the idea that ai
is used in the military
it's kind of funny there there's this
like kind of discomfort and they're like
they all hurry like uh you know like
something scary happens and a bunch of
sheep kind of like run a run away that's
what it looks like
and it i don't even know what to do
about it because and then i feel this
natural pull every time i bring up
autonomous weapon systems
to go along with the sheep there's a
natural kind of pull towards that
direction
because it's like what can i do as one
person
now there's currently nothing
destructive happening with autonomous
weapons systems
so we're in like in the early days of
this race that
in 10 20 years might become a real
problem now where
the discussion we're having now we're
not facing the result of that in the
space of viruses
uh like for many years avoiding the
conversations here
i don't know what to do that in the
early days um
but i think we have to i guess create
institutions where people can stand out
people can stand out and like basically
be
individual thinkers and break out into
all kinds of
spaces of ideas that allow us to think
freely
freedom of thought and maybe that
requires the decentralization of
institutions
well years ago i came up with a concept
called cultivated insecurity and the
idea is
let's just take the example of the
average joe
right the average joe has a job
somewhere
and their mortgage their
medical insurance their retirement
their connection with the economy is
to one degree or another dependent on
their relationship
with the employer that means
that there is a strong incentive
especially in
any industry where it's not easy to move
from one employer to the next there's a
strong incentive
to stay in your employer's good graces
right so it creates a very top-down
dynamic not only
in terms of who gets to tell
other people what to do but it really
comes down to who gets to tell other
people how to think
so that's extremely dangerous the way
out of it is to cultivate security
to the extent that somebody is in a
position to
go against the grain and have it not be
a catastrophe for their family
and their ability to earn you will see
that behavior a lot more so
i would argue that some of what you're
talking about is just a simple
uh predictable consequence of the
concentration
of the uh the sources of well-being
and that this is a solvable problem
you got a chance to talk with joe rogan
yesterday
yes i did and i just saw the episode was
released
and uh ivermectin is trending on twitter
joe told me it was an incredible
conversation i look forward to listening
today many people
have probably by the time this is
released i've already listened to it
i think it would be interesting to
discuss
uh a postmortem how do you feel how that
conversation went
maybe broadly how do you see the story
as its unfolding of ivermectin from
the origins from before covert 19
through 2020 to today i very much
enjoyed talking to joe and i'm
indescribably grateful that he would
take
the risk of such a discussion that he
would as he described it do an emergency
podcast on the subject
which i i think that was not an
exaggeration this needed to happen
for various reasons that he uh
he took us down the road of talking
about the censorship campaign against
ivermectin which i find
utterly shocking and talking about
the drug itself and i should say we
talked we had pierre corey
available he came on the podcast as well
he is of course the face of the
fl triple c the frontline covet 19
critical care
alliance these are doctors who have
innovated
ways of treating covet patients and they
happened on ivermectin
and have been using it and
i hesitate to use the word advocating
for it because that's not really the
role
of doctors or scientists but they are
advocating for it in the sense that
there is this
uh pressure not to talk about its
effectiveness for reasons that we can
go into so maybe step back and say what
is
ivermectin and how much
studies have been done to show its
effectiveness
so ivermectin is an interesting drug it
was discovered
in the 70s by a japanese scientist
named satoshi omura and he found it
in soil near a japanese golf course
so i would just point out in passing
that if we were to stop
self-silencing over the possibility that
asians will be demonized over the
possible lab leak in wuhan and to
recognize
that actually the natural course of the
story
has a likely lab leak in china
it has a unlikely hero
in japan the story is naturally
not a simple one but in any case uh
amura
discovered this molecule he uh
sent it to a friend who was at merck a
scientist named campbell
they won a nobel prize for the discovery
of
the ivermectin molecule in 2015.
its initial use was in treating
parasitic infections
it's very effective in treating the
the worm that causes river blindness uh
the
pathogen that causes elephantitis
scabies
it's a very effective anti-parasite drug
it's extremely safe it's on the who's
list
of essential medications it's safe for
children it has been administered
something like four billion times in the
last
four decades it has been given away in
the millions of doses
by merck in africa people have
been on it for long periods of time and
in fact one of the
reasons that africa may have had less
severe impacts from covid19 is that
ivermectin
is widely used there to prevent
parasites and the drug appears to have a
long lasting impact so it's an
interesting molecule
it was discovered some time ago
apparently
that it has antiviral properties and so
it was tested
in early in the covet 19 pandemic to see
if it might work
to treat humans with covid it turned out
to have
very promising uh evidence that it did
treat
humans it was tested in tissues it was
tested at a very high dosage which
confuses people they think that those of
us
who believe that ivermectin might be
useful
in confronting this disease are
advocating those high doses which is not
the case
but in any case there have been quite a
number of studies
a wonderful meta-analysis was finally
released we had seen it in pre-print
version but it was finally
peer-reviewed and published this last
week
um it reveals that the drug as
clinicians have been telling us those
who've been using it it's highly
effective at treating people with the
disease especially if you get to them
early
and it showed an 86 percent
effectiveness as a prophylactic to
prevent people from contracting
covid and that number 86 percent
is high enough to drive sars cov2
to extinction if we wished to deploy it
first of all the the the meta analysis
is this the uh ivermectin foucault 19
real-time meta-analysis of 60 studies
or there's a bunch of meta-analysis
there because i i was really impressed
by the real-time meta-analysis that
keeps getting
updated i don't know it's the same kind
of the one at uh
ivmmeta.com
well i saw it it's uh c19
no this is not that meta-analysis stuff
so that is as you say a living meta
analysis where you can watch as
evidence which is super cool by the way
it's really cool and they've got some
really nice graphics that allow you to
understand well what is the evidence you
know
it's concentrated around this level of
effectiveness etc so anyway it's great
site well worth paying attention to
no this is a meta-analysis um i don't
know any of the authors but
one second author is tess laurie of the
bird group
bird being a a group of
analysts and doctors in britain that is
playing a role similar to the fl triple
c
here in the u.s so anyway this is a
meta-analysis that that
that uh test laurie and others did of
all of the available
evidence and um it's quite compelling
people if people can look for it on my
twitter i will i will put it up and
people can find it there
so what about those here that
in terms of safety uh what do we
understand about the the kind of dust
required to
to have that level of effectiveness and
what do we understand about is
the safety of that kind of dose so let
me just say i'm not a medical doctor
i'm a biologist i'm on ivermectin
uh in lieu of vaccination in terms of
dosage there is one reason for concern
which is that the most effective dose
for prophylaxis
involves something like weekly
administration
and that that is because that is not a
historical
pattern of use for the drug um it is
possible that there is some long-term
implication of being on it
for being on it weekly for a long period
of time
there's not a strong indication of that
the safety signal that we have
uh over people using the drug over many
years and using it in high doses in fact
dr corey told me yesterday that there
are cases in which people have made
uh calculation errors and taken a
massive overdose of the drug and had no
ill effect
so anyway there's lots of reasons to
think the drug is comparatively safe but
no drug is perfectly safe
and i do worry about the long-term
implications of taking it
i also think it's very likely
because the drug is administered
in a dose something like let's say
15 milligrams for somebody my size once
a week after you've gone through the
initial
the initial double dose that you take 48
hours apart
it is apparent that if the amount of
drug
in your system is sufficient to be
protective at the end of the week then
it was probably far
too high at the beginning of the week so
there's a question about whether or not
you could flatten out the intake so that
the amount of ivermectin goes down but
the protection remains i have
little doubt that that would be
discovered if we looked for it
but that said it does seem to be quite
safe
highly effective at preventing covid the
number is plenty high enough for us to
drive
uh sarsko v2 to extinction in light of
its r naught number
of slightly more than two um
and so why we are not using it as a bit
of a a mystery
so even if everything you said now turns
out to be not correct
it is nevertheless obvious that it's
sufficiently promising it always has
been
in order to merit rigorous scientific
exploration investigation doing a lot of
studies
and certainly not censoring the science
or the discussion of it
so before we talk about the various
vaccines for code 19 i'd like to talk to
you about censorship
given everything you're saying why did
youtube
and other places censor
discussion of um have a mechtin
well there's a question about why they
say they did it and there's a question
about why they actually did it
now it is worth mentioning that youtube
is part of a consortium
it is partnered with twitter facebook
reuters ap financial times
washington post some other notable
organizations
and that this group has appointed itself
the arbiter of truth in effect they have
decided
to control discussion ostensibly
to prevent the distribution of
misinformation
now how have they chosen to do that in
this case they have chosen
to simply utilize the recommendations of
the who
and the cdc and apply them as if they
are synonymous with scientific truth
problem even at their best
the who and cdc are not scientific
entities they are entities that are
about public health and public health
has
this whether it's right or not and i
believe i disagree with it but it has
this
uh self-assigned right
to lie that comes from the fact that
there is
game theory that works against for
example a successful vaccination
campaign
that if everybody else takes a vaccine
and therefore the herd becomes immune
through vaccination
and you decide not to take a vaccine
then you benefit from
the immunity of the herd without having
taken the risk
so people who do best are the people who
opt out
that's a hazard and the who and cdc as
public health entities effectively
oversimplify stories in order that that
game theory does not
cause a predictable tragedy of the
commons
with that said once that right to lie
exists
then it finds out it turns out to serve
the interests of for example
pharmaceutical companies
which have emergency use authorizations
that require that there not be a safe
and effective treatment
and have immunity from liability for
harms caused by
their product so that's a recipe for
disaster
right you don't need to be a
sophisticated
thinker about complex systems to see the
hazard of immunizing
a company from the harm of its own
product
at the same time that that product can
only exist in the market
if some other product that works better
somehow fails to be noticed
so somehow youtube is doing the bidding
of merck and others
whether it knows that that's what it's
doing i have no idea i think this may
be another case of an autopilot that
thinks it's doing the right thing
because it's
parroting the corrupt wisdom of the who
and the cdc
but the who and the cdc have been wrong
again and again in this pandemic
and the irony here is that with youtube
coming after me
well my channel has been right where the
who and cdc have been wrong
consistently over the whole pandemic so
how is it that youtube is censoring us
because the who and cdc disagree with us
when in fact
in past disagreements we've been right
and they've been wrong there's
so much to talk about here so
i've heard this many times actually on
the inside of youtube
and with colleagues that i've talked
about talked with
is they kind of in a very casual way say
their
job is simply to slow or prevent the
spread of misinformation
and they say like that's an easy thing
to do
like to know what is true or not is an
easy thing to do
and so from the youtube perspective i
think
they basically outsource of
of the the task of knowing what is true
or not
to public institutions that on a basic
google search claim to be the arbiters
of truth
so if you were youtube who are
exceptionally profitable and
exceptionally powerful
in terms of controlling what people get
to see or not
what would you do would you take a stand
a public stand against the w.h.o who
cdc or would you
instead say you know what let's open the
damn
and let any video on anything fly
what do you what do you do here if you
say you were put if brett weinstein was
put in charge
of youtube for a month in this
most critical of times where youtube
actually has incredible amounts of power
to educate the populace to give
power of knowledge to the populace such
that they can reform institutions what
would you do how would you run youtube
well unfortunately or fortunately this
is actually
quite simple the founders the american
founders
settled on a counter-intuitive
formulation
that people should be free to say
anything
they should be free from the government
blocking them from doing so
they did not imagine that in formulating
that right
that most of what was said would be of
high quality nor did they imagine it
would be free of harmful things
what they correctly reasoned was that
the benefit
of leaving everything so it can be said
exceeds the cost which everyone
understands to be substantial
what i would say is they could not have
anticipated
the impact the centrality of platforms
like youtube facebook twitter etc
if they had they would not have limited
the first amendment as they did
they clearly understood that the power
of the federal government
was so great that it needed to be
limited
by granting explicitly the right of
citizens to say anything
in fact youtube twitter facebook may be
more powerful
in this moment than the federal
government of their worst nightmares
could have been
the power that these entities have to
control
thought and to shift civilization is so
great
that we need to have those same
protections it doesn't mean that harmful
things won't be said
but it means that nothing has changed
about the cost benefit analysis
of building the right to censor so if i
were running youtube
the limit of what should be allowed is
the limit of the law
right if what you are doing is legal
then it should not be youtube's place
to limit what gets said or who gets to
hear it
that is between speakers and audience
will harm come from that
of course it will but will net harm come
from it
no i don't believe it will i believe
that allowing everything to be said does
allow a process in which
better ideas do come to the fore and win
out so
you believe that in the end when there's
complete freedom
to share ideas that truth will win out
so what i've noticed just as a brief
side comment
that certain things become viral
irregardless of their truth i i've
noticed that
things that are dramatic and or funny
like things that become memes are not
don't have to be grounded
in truth and so that what worries me
there
is that we basically maximize
for drama versus maximize for truth in a
system where everything is
free and that's worrying in the time of
emergency
well yes it's all worrying in time of
emergency to be sure
but i want you to notice that what
you've happened on is actually an
analog for a much deeper and older
problem
human beings are the
we are not a blank slate but we are the
blankest slate that nature has ever
devised
and there's a reason for that right it's
where our flexibility comes from
we have effectively we are robots
in which the a large fraction
of the cognitive capacity has been or of
the
behavioral capacity has been offloaded
to the software layer which gets written
and rewritten over evolutionary time
that means effectively that much of what
we are
in fact the important part of what we
are is housed in the in the cultural
layer and the conscious layer and not in
the hardware
hard coding layer
that layer is prone to make errors right
and anybody who's watched a child grow
up
knows that children make absurd errors
all the time right that's
part of the process as we were
discussing earlier
it is also true that as you look across
a
field of people discussing things a lot
of what is said is pure nonsense it's
garbage
but the tendency of garbage to
emerge and even to spread in the short
term
does not say that over the long term
what sticks
is not the valuable ideas
so there is a high tendency for
novelty to be created in the cultural
space but there's also a high tendency
for it to go extinct and you have to
keep that in mind it's not like the
genome
right everything is happening at a much
higher rate things are being created
they're being destroyed
and i can't say that you know i mean
obviously we've seen totalitarianism
arise
many times and it's very destructive
each time it does so it's not like
hey freedom to come up with any idea you
want hasn't produced
a whole lot of carnage but the question
is over time
does it produce more open fairer more
decent
societies and i believe that it does i
can't prove it
but that does seem to be the pattern i i
believe so as well
the thing is in the short term
freedom of speech absolute freedom of
speech can be quite destructive
but you nevertheless have to hold on to
that
because in the long term i think you and
i i guess
are optimistic in the sense that good
ideas will win out
i don't know how strongly i believe that
it will work but i will say i haven't
heard a better idea
yeah i would also point out that there's
something very
significant in this question of the
hubris involved in imagining that you're
going to improve the discussion by
censoring
which is the majority of
concepts at the fringe are nonsense
that's automatic but the
heterodoxy at the fringe which is
indistinguishable
at the beginning from the nonsense ideas
is the key to progress so if you decide
hey the fringe is 99
garbage let's just get rid of it right
hey that's a strong win we're getting
rid of 99
garbage for one percent something or
other and the point is yeah but that one
percent something rather is the key
you're throwing out the key and so
that's what youtube is doing
frankly i think at the point that it
started censoring my channel
you know in the immediate aftermath of
this major reversal of
lab for lab leak it should have looked
at itself and said well what the hell
are we doing
who are we sensory we're sensory
somebody who was just right
right in a conflict with the very same
people on whose behalf we are now
censoring right that should have caused
them to wake up
so you said one approach if you were on
youtube was just basically
let all videos go that do not violate
the law well i should fix that
okay i believe that that is the basic
principle eric makes an excellent point
about the distinction between
ideas and personal attacks doxing
these other things so i agree there's no
value in allowing
people to destroy each other's lives
even if there's a technical
legal defense for it now how you draw
that line i don't know
but you know what i'm talking about is
yes people should be free to traffic and
bad ideas and they should be free to
expose that the ideas are bad
and hopefully that process results in
better ideas winning out
yeah there's an interesting line between
you know
like uh ideas like the earth is flat
which
i believe you should not censor and then
like
you start to encroach on like personal
attacks
so not not you know doxxing yes but like
not even getting to that like there's a
certain point where it's like
that's no longer ideas that's more
that's somehow not productive even if
it's
it feels like uh believing the earth is
flat it's somehow productive
because maybe this tiny percent chance
it is
you know like it just feels like
personal attacks
it doesn't um well you know it's i'm
torn on this because
there's [ __ ] in this world there's
fraudulent people in this world so
sometimes personal attacks are useful to
reveal that
but there's a line you can cross like
there's a
comedy where people make fun of others i
think that's
amazing that's very powerful and that's
very useful even if it's painful
but then there's like once it gets to be
um yeah there's a certain line it's a
gray area where you cross where it's no
longer
in any possible world productive
and that's a really weird gray area for
youtube to operate in
and it feels like should be a
crowdsource thing
where people vote on it but then again
do you trust the majority to vote
on what is crossing the line and not i
mean this is where
this is really interesting on this
particular
like the scientific aspect of this
do you think youtube should take more of
a stance
not censoring but to actually have
scientists
within youtube having these kinds of
discussions
and then be able to almost speak out in
a transparent way
this is what we're going to let this
video stand but here's all these other
opinions
almost like take a more active role in
uh its recommendation system
in trying to present a full picture to
you right now they're not and they're
the recommender systems are not human
fine-tuned
they're all based on how you click and
there's this clustering algorithms
they're not taking an active role on
giving you the full spectrum of ideas in
the space of science
they just censor or not well
at the moment it's going to be pretty
hard to compel me
that these people should be trusted with
any sort of curation
or comment on matters of evidence
because they have demonstrated that they
are incapable of doing it well
um you could make such an argument and i
guess i'm open to the idea
of institutions that would look
something like youtube that would be
capable of offering something valuable i
mean and you know even just the fact of
them literally curating things and
putting some videos next to others
you know implies something so
yeah there's a question to be answered
but at the moment no
at the moment what it is doing is quite
literally putting
not only individual humans in tremendous
jeopardy by
censoring discussion of useful tools and
making tools that are
more hazardous than has been
acknowledged seems safe
right but it is also placing humanity in
danger of a permanent
relationship with this pathogen i cannot
emphasize enough
how expensive that is it's effectively
incalculable
if the relationship becomes permanent
the number of people who will ultimately
suffer and die from it is indefinitely
large
yeah there's uh currently the algorithm
is very rabbit hole driven
meaning if you uh if you click on the
flat earth videos that's all you're
going to be presented with
and you're not going to be nicely
presented with arguments against the
flat earth
and the flip side of that
if you watch like quantum mechanics
videos or no general relativity videos
it's very rare you're going to get a
recommendation have you considered the
earth as flat
and i think you should have both same
with vaccine
videos that present the power and the
incredible
like biology genetics biology about the
vaccine
you're rarely going to get videos
from well-respected
scientific minds presenting possible
dangers of the vaccine and the vice
versa is true as well
which is if you're looking at the danger
of the vaccine on youtube
you're not going to get the highest
quality of videos recommended to you
and i'm not talking about like manually
inserted cdc videos
that are like the most untrustworthy
things you can possibly watch about how
everybody should take the vaccine it's
the safest thing ever no it's about
incredible again mit colleagues of mine
incredible biologists biologists that
talk about the the details of how the
mrna vaccines work and all those kinds
of things i think
maybe this is me with the ai hat
on is i think the algorithm can fix a
lot of this
and youtube should build better
algorithms and trust that
to and a couple of complete freedom of
speech
to expand the what people are
able to think about present always
varied views not
balanced in some artificial way
hard-coded way
but balanced in a way that's
crowdsourced i think that's an algorithm
problem that could be solved
because that then you can delegate it to
the algorithm
as opposed to this hard code
censorship of basically
creating artificial boundaries on what
can and can't be discussed
instead creating a full spectrum of
exploration that can be done and
trusting the intelligence of
people to do the exploration well
there's a lot there i would say we have
to keep in mind that we're talking
about a um a publicly held company with
shareholders and obligations to them and
that that may make it impossible
and i remember many years ago back in
the early days of google
i remember a sense of terror at the loss
of general search right it used to be
that that google if you searched came up
with the same thing for everyone and
then
it got personalized and for a while it
was possible to turn off the
personalization which was still not
great because if everybody else is
looking at a personalized search
and you can tune into one that isn't
personalized what are you know
that doesn't tell you why the world is
sounding the way it is
but nonetheless it was at least an
option and then that vanished
and the problem is i think this is
literally deranging us
that in effect i mean what you're
describing is unthinkable
it is unthinkable that in the face of
a campaign to vaccine vaccinate people
in order to reach hurt immunity
that um youtube would give you
videos on hazards of vaccines
when this is you know how hazardous the
vaccines are is an
unsettled question why is it unthinkable
that doesn't make any sense for well
from a company perspective
if intelligent people in large amounts
are open-minded and are thinking through
the
the hazards and the benefits of a
vaccine
a company should should find the best
videos
to present what people are thinking
about
well let's come up with a hypothetical
okay let's come up with a
a very deadly disease for which there's
a vaccine
that is very safe though not perfectly
safe
and we are then faced with youtube
trying to figure out what to do for
somebody searching on vaccine safety
suppose it is necessary in order to
drive the pathogen to extinction
something like smallpox
that people get on board with the
vaccine
but there's a tiny fringe of people who
thinks that the vaccine
is a mind control agent
right so should youtube
direct people to the only claims
against this vaccine which is that it's
a mind control agent
when in fact uh the
vaccine is very safe whatever that means
if that were the actual configuration of
the puzzle
then youtube would be doing active harm
pointing you
to um this other video potentially
now yes i would love to live in a world
where people
are up to the challenge of sorting that
out but
my basic point would be if it's an
evidentiary question
and there is essentially no evidence
that the vaccine is a mind control
agent and there's plenty of evidence
that the vaccine is safe then
well you look for this video we're going
to give you this one puts it on a par
right so for the mind that's tracking
how much
uh thought is there behind it's safe
versus how much thought is there behind
it's a mind control agent will result in
artificially
uh elevating this now in the current
case what we've seen
is not this at all we have seen evidence
obscured in order to create a false
story about
safety and we saw the inverse with
ivermectin we saw a campaign
to portray the drug as
more dangerous and less effective than
the evidence clearly suggested it was
so we're not talking about a comparable
thing but i guess my point is the
algorithmic solution that you point to
creates a problem of its own which is
that it means that the way to get
exposure is to generate something fringy
if you're the only thing on some fringe
then suddenly youtube would be
recommending those things and that's
that's obviously a gameable system at
best
yeah but the solution to that i know
you're you're creating a thought
experiment
maybe playing a little bit of a devil's
advocate
i think the solution to that is not to
uh limit the algorithm in the case of
the super deadly virus
it's for the scientists to step up and
become better communicators more
charismatic
is fight the battle of ideas
so to create better videos you know the
like if the virus is truly deadly
you have a lot more ammunition a lot
more data a lot more material to work
with in terms of communicating with the
public
so be better at communicating and stop
being
uh you have to start trusting the
intelligence of people and also being
transparent
and playing the game of the internet
which is like what is the internet
hungry for i believe
authenticity stop looking like you're
full of [ __ ]
it's the scientific community if there's
any
flaw that i currently see especially the
people that are in public office
that like anthony fauci they look like
they're full of [ __ ]
and i know they're brilliant why don't
they look more authentic
so they're losing that game and i think
a lot of people observing this entire
system now
younger scientists are seeing this
and saying okay if i want to continue
being a
scientist in the public eye and i want
to be effective in my job
i'm going to have to be a lot more
authentic so they're learning the lesson
this evolutionary system is working
uh so there's just a younger generation
of minds coming up that i think will do
a much better job
in this battle of ideas that when the
when the
much more dangerous virus comes along
they'll be able to be better
communicators
at least that's the hope the the using
the algorithm to control that
is uh i feel like is a big problem so
you're going to have the same problem
with a deadly virus
as with the current virus if you let
youtube
draw hard lines by the pr and the
marketing people
versus the broad community of scientists
well in some sense you're you're
suggesting something that's
close akin to what i was saying about
you know
freedom of expression ultimately uh
provides an advantage to to better ideas
so i'm in agreement broadly speaking
um but i would also say there's probably
some sort of you know
let's imagine the world that you propose
where youtube shows you the
alternative point of view that has the
problem that i suggest but
one thing you could do is you could give
us the tools to understand what we're
looking at
right you could give us so first of all
there's something
i think myopic solipsistic
narcissistic about a an algorithm that
serves
shareholders by showing you what you
want to see rather than what you need to
know
right that's the distinction is
flattering you you know playing to your
blind spot
is something that algorithm will figure
out but it's not healthy for us all to
have
google playing to our blind spot it's
very very dangerous so
what i really want is analytics
that allow me or maybe options and
analytics the options should allow me to
see
what alternative perspectives are being
explored
right so here's the thing i'm searching
and it leads me down this road right
let's let's say it's ivermectin okay
i find all of this evidence that
ivermectin works i find all of these
discussions and people talk about
various protocols and this and that and
then i could say all right
what is the other side and i could see
who
is searching not as individuals but what
demographics are searching
alternatives and maybe you could even
combine it with something reddit like
where effectively let's say that there
was a position that
i don't know that that a vaccine is a
mind control device
and you could have a steel man this
argument
uh competition effectively and the
better answers that steel man and as
well as possible
would rise to the top and so you could
read the top three or four
explanations about why this really
credibly is a mind control
uh uh product and you can say well
that doesn't really add up i can check
these three things myself and they can't
possibly be right
right and you could dismiss it and then
as an argument that was credible
let's say plate tectonics before that
was an accepted concept
you'd say wait a minute there is
evidence
for plate tectonic as crazy as it sounds
that the continents are floating around
on liquid
actually that's not so implausible you
know we've got these subduction zones
we've got uh geology that is compatible
we've got puzzle piece continents that
seem to fit together
wow that's a surprising amount of
evidence for that position so i'm going
to
file some bayesian probability with it
that's updated for the fact that
actually the steel man argument's better
than i was expecting
right so i could imagine something like
that where a
i would love the search to be
indifferent to who's searching
right the the solipsistic thing is too
dangerous so
the search could be general so we would
all get a sense for what everybody else
was seeing too
and then some layer that didn't have
anything to do with what
youtube points you to or not but allowed
you to see
you know the general pattern of
uh adherence to searching for um
information and again a layer in which
those things could be defended so you
could hear what a good argument sounded
right
like rather than just hear a caricatured
argument yeah and also reward people
creators that have demonstrated like a
track record of open-mindedness
and correctness correctness as much as
it could be measured over a long term
and sort of uh i mean
a lot of this maps to
incentivizing good long-term behavior
not immediate kind of dopamine rush
uh kind of signals
i think ultimately the algorithm
on the individual level should optimize
for personal growth
long-term happiness just
growth intellectually growth in terms of
lifestyle personally and so on as
opposed to
immediate uh i think that's going to
build a better society not even just
like truth because i think
truth is a complicated thing it's more
just you growing as a person
exploring the space of ideas changing
your mind often
increasing the level to which you're
open-minded the knowledge base you're
operating from
the willingness to empathize with others
all those kinds of things the algorithm
should optimize for
like creating a better human at the
individual level that you're all
i think that's a great business model
because the person
that's using this tool will then be
happier with themselves for having used
it and will be
a lifelong quote-unquote customer i
think it's a great business model
to make a happy open-minded
knowledgeable
better human being it's a terrible
business model
under the current system what you want
is to build the system in which it is a
great business model why is it a
terrible model
because it will be decimated by those
who play to the short term
i don't think so why well i mean i think
we're living it
we're living it well no because if if
you have the alternative that presents
itself
it it it points out the emperor has no
clothes i mean
it points out that youtube is operating
in this way twitter's operating in this
way
so facebook is operating in this way how
long term would you like
the wisdom to to prove that
well even though a week is better what's
currently happening
right but the problem is you know if a
week loses out to an hour
right and i don't think it loses out
it loses out in the short term that's my
point at least you're a great
communicator
and you basically say look here's the
metrics
and a lot of it is like how people
actually feel
like this this is what people experience
with social media
they look back at the previous month and
say
i felt shitty and a lot of days because
of social media right
like if you look back at the previous
few weeks and say
wow i'm a better person because that
month happened
that's they immediately choose the
product that's going to lead to that
that's what love for products looks like
if you if you love
like a lot of people love their tesla
car like that's
or iphone or like beautiful design
that's what love looks like you look
back
i'm a better person for having used this
thing well you got to ask yourself the
question though if this is such a great
business model
why isn't it devolving why don't we see
it
honestly it's competence it's like
people are just it's not
it's not easy to build new it's not
easy to build products tools
systems on new ideas it's kind of a new
idea we've gone through this
everything we're seeing now comes from
the
ideas of the initial birth of the
internet this just needs to be new sets
of tools that are
uh incentivizing long term personal
growth and happiness
that's it right but but what we have is
a market that doesn't favor this right i
mean for one thing
you know we had an alternative to
facebook
right that looked you know you owned
your own data it wasn't exploitative
and facebook bought a huge interest in
it
and it died i mean who do you know who's
on diaspora
the execution there was not good right
but it could have gotten better
right i don't think that the argument
that
why hasn't somebody done it a good
argument for it's
not going to completely destroy all of
twitter and facebook when somebody does
it
or twitter will catch up and pivot to to
the algorithm
this is not what this is not what i'm
saying there's obviously great ideas
that remain
unexplored because nobody has gotten to
the foothill that would allow you to
explore them
that's true but you know an internet
that was non-predatory
is an obvious idea and many of us know
that we want it
and many of us have seen prototypes of
it and we don't move because there's no
audience there so the network effects
cause you to stay with the predatory
internet
um but let me just i wasn't kidding
about build the system in which
your idea is a great business plan
um so in our upcoming book heather and i
in our last chapter explore something
called the fourth frontier and fourth
frontier has to do with
sort of a 2.0 version of civilization
which we freely admit
we can't tell you very much about it's
something that would have to be
we would have to prototype our way there
we would have to effectively navigate
our way there
but the result would be very much like
what you're describing it would be
something
that effectively liberates humans
meaningfully
and most importantly it has to feel
like growth without depending on growth
in other words
human beings are creatures that like
every other creature
is effectively looking for growth right
we are looking for
underexploited or unexploited
opportunities and when we find them
our ancestors for example if they
happened into a new valley that was
unexplored by
people their population would grow until
it had carrying capacity so there would
be this great
feeling of there's abundance until you
hit carrying capacity which is
inevitable and then zero-sum dynamics
would set in
so in order for human beings to flourish
long-term
the way to get there is to satisfy the
desire for growth without hooking it to
actual growth which
only moves in fits and starts and this
is actually i believe the key
to avoiding these you know spasms of
human tragedy when in the absence of
growth
people do something that causes their
population to experience growth which is
they go and
make war on or commit genocide against
some other population which is something
we obviously have to
stop by the way this is uh
a hunter hunter-gatherer's guide to the
21st century co-authored
that's right with your wife heather
being released to september i
believe you said you're going to do a
little bit of a preview videos on each
chapter leading up to the release
so i'm looking forward to the last
chapter
as well as well as all the the previous
one i have a few questions on that
so you you have um you generally have
faith
to clarify that technology could be the
thing
that empowers this kind of future
well if you just let technology evolve
it's going to be our undoing right
one of the things that i um fault my
libertarian friends
for is this faith that the market is
going to find
solutions without destroying us and my
sense is
i'm a very strong believer in markets
right i believe in their power
even above some market fundamentalists
but what i don't believe
is that they should be allowed to plot
our course
right markets are very good at figuring
out how to do things
they are not good at all about figuring
out what we should do
right what we should want we have to
tell markets what we want and then they
can tell us
how to do it best and if we adopted that
kind of
pro market but in a context where it's
not steering where human well-being is
actually the driver
we can do remarkable things and the
technology that emerges would naturally
be
enhancing of human well-being perfectly
so
no but overwhelmingly so but at the
moment
markets are finding our every defect of
character and exploiting them and making
huge profits and making us
worse to each other in the process
before we leave covet 19 let me
ask you about a very difficult topic
which is the vaccines so i took the fisa
vaccine
the two shots you did not
you have been taking ivermectin
yep so one of the arguments
against the discussion of ivermectin is
that
it prevents people from being
fully willing to get the vaccine how
would you compare
ivermectin and the vaccine
for coven 19. all right that's a good
question
i would say first of all there are some
hazards with the vaccine that people
need to be aware of there are some
things that we cannot
rule out and for which there is some
evidence
the two that i think people should be
tracking is the
possibility some would say a likelihood
that a vaccine of this nature
that is to say very narrowly focused on
a single antigen is
a an evolutionary pressure that will
drive
the emergence of variants that will
escape the protection that comes from
the vaccine
so this is a hazard it is a particular
hazard in light of the fact that these
vaccines
have a substantial number of
breakthrough cases
so one danger is that a person who has
been vaccinated
will shed viruses that are specifically
less visible or invisible to the
immunity created by the vaccines
so we may be creating the next pandemic
by
applying the pressure of vaccines at a
point that it doesn't make sense to
the other danger has to do with
something called antibody dependent
enhancement
which is something that we see in
certain diseases like dengue fever
you may know that dengue one gets a case
and then their second case is much more
devastating so break bone fever
is when you get your second case of
dengue and dengue effectively
utilizes the immune response that is
produced by prior exposure
to attack the body in ways that it is
incapable of doing before exposure
so this is apparently this pattern has
apparently blocked
past efforts to make vaccines
against coronaviruses whether it will
happen here or not
it is still too early to say but before
we even get to the question
of harm done to individuals by
these vaccines we have to ask about what
the overall impact is going to be and
it's not
clear in the way people think it is that
if we vaccinate enough people the
pandemic will end
it could be that we vaccinate people and
make the pandemic worse
and while nobody can say for sure that
that's where we're headed
it is at least something to be aware of
so don't vaccines usually create that
kind of
evolutionary pressure to create more
deadlier
different strains of the virus so isn't
so is there something particular with
these mrna vaccines that's uniquely
dangerous in this regard
well it's not even just the mrna
vaccines the mrna vaccines and the
adenovector
dna vaccine all share the same
vulnerability which is they are very
narrowly focused on one subunit of the
spike protein
so that is a very concentrated
evolutionary signal
we are also deploying it in mid pandemic
and it takes time for immunity to
develop
so part of the problem here if you if
you inoculated a population
before encounter with a pathogen then
there might be
substantially enough immunity to prevent
this phenomenon from happening but in
this case
we are inoculating people as they are
encountering those who are sick with the
disease
and what that means is the disease is
now faced with a lot of opportunities to
effectively evolutionarily practice
escape strategies
so one thing is the timing the other
thing is the narrow focus
now in a traditional vaccine you would
typically not have one
antigen right you would have basically a
virus full of antigens
and the immune system would therefore
produce a broader response
so that is the case for people who have
had covet
right they have an immunity that is
broader because it wasn't so focused on
one part of the spike protein
so anyway there is something unique here
so these platforms
create that special hazard they also
have components that we haven't
used before in people so for example the
lipid nanoparticles
that coat the rnas are
distributing themselves around the body
in a way that will have
unknown consequences so anyway there's
there's reason
reason for concern is it possible for
you to steal man
the argument that everybody should get
vaccinated
of course the argument that everybody
should get vaccinated
is that nothing is perfectly safe
phase 3 trials showed good safety
for the vaccines now that may or may not
be actually true
but what we saw suggested high degree of
efficacy and
a high degree of safety for the vaccines
that inoculating people quickly and
therefore
dropping the landscape of available
victims for the pathogen
to a very low number so that herd
immunity drives it to extinction
requires us all to take our share of the
risk
and that that
because driving it to extinction should
be our highest priority that really
people shouldn't think uh too much about
the various nuances because
overwhelmingly
fewer people will die if the population
is vaccinated
from the vaccine then will die from
covet if they're not vaccinated
and with the vaccine as the current as
being deployed that is a
quite a likely scenario that
the everything you know
the virus will fade away in in the
following sense
that the the probability that a more
dangerous strain will be created
is non-zero but it's not 50
it's something smaller and so the most
likely well i don't know maybe you
disagree with that but the
the scenario we're most likely to see
not that the vaccine is here
is that the via the effects of the virus
will fade away
first of all i don't believe that the
probability of creating a worse pandemic
is low enough to discount i think the
probability is fairly high
and frankly we are seeing a wave of
variance
that um we will have to do a careful
analysis to figure out what exactly that
has to do with campaigns of vaccination
where they have been where they haven't
been where the variance emerged from but
i believe that what we are seeing is a
disturbing pattern
that reflects that those who were
advising caution may well have been
right the data here by the way
a small tangent is terrible terrible
right and
why is it terrible is another question
right this is where i started getting
angry
yeah it's like there's a obvious
opportunity for exceptionally good data
for exceptionally rigorous like even the
self like the website for self reporting
side effects for not side effects but
negative effects adverse events
at first event sorry for the vaccine
like there's many things i could say
from both the study perspective but
mostly let me just put on my hat of like
html and like web design
like it's like the worst website it
makes it so unpleasant to report
it makes it so unclear what you're
reporting if somebody actually has
serious effect like if you have very
mild effects what are the
incentives for you to even use that
crappy website with
many pages and forms that don't make any
sense if you have adverse effects
what are the incentives for you to use
that website
what is the trust that you have that
this information will be used well
all those kinds of things and the data
about who's getting vaccinated
anonymized data about who's getting
vaccinated where
when what that with what vaccine coupled
with the adverse effects
all of that we should be collecting
instead we're completely not
we're doing it in a crappy way and using
that crappy data to make conclusions
that you then twist you're basically
collecting in a way that can
arrive at whatever conclusions you want
and the data is being collected by
uh the institutions by governments and
so therefore
it's obviously they're going to try to
construct any kind of narratives they
want based on this crappy data reminds
me of much of psychology the field that
i love
but is flawed in many fundamental ways
so rant
over but uh coupled with the dangers
that you're speaking to we don't have
even the data
to um to understand the dangers yeah
uh i'm going to pick up on your rant and
say
we estimates of the degree of under
reporting in
vares are uh that it is
ten percent of the real to a hundred
percent and that's the one
for reporting yeah the fair system is
the is the system for reporting adverse
events so
um in the u.s we have above
5 000 unexpected deaths that seem
in time to be associated with
vaccination that is an undercount
almost certainly and by uh a large
factor
we don't know how large i've seen
estimates 25
000 dead in the u.s alone um
now you can make the argument that okay
that's a large number
but the necessity of immunizing the
population to drive
sars kovi 2 to extinction is such that
it's an acceptable number but i would
point out that that actually does not
make any sense and the reason it doesn't
make any sense
is actually there's several reasons one
if that was really your point
that yes many many people are going to
die but many more will die if we don't
do this
were that your approach you would not be
inoculating people who had had
covet 19 which is a large population
there is no reason to expose those
people to danger their risk of adverse
events in the case that they
have them is greater so there's no
reason that we would be allowing those
people to face a risk of death if this
was really about an acceptable number
of deaths arising out of this uh the set
of vaccines
i would also point out there's something
incredibly bizarre and i would
i struggle to find language that is
strong enough
for the horror of vaccinating
children in this case because children
suffer a greater risk of long-term
effects
because they are going to live longer
and because this is earlier in their
development therefore it impacts systems
that are still
forming they tolerate covid well
and so the benefit to them is very small
and so the only argument for doing this
is that they may cryptically be carrying
more covert than we think
and therefore they may be integral to
the way the virus spreads to the
population
but if that's the reason that we are
inoculating children and there has been
some revision in the last day or two
about the recommendation on this because
of the
adverse events that have shown up in
children but to the extent that we were
vaccinating children
we were doing it to protect old infirm
people who are the most likely
to succumb to covet 19. what society
puts children in danger
robs children of life to save old infirm
people that's upside down
so there's something about the way we
are going about
vaccinating who we are vaccinating what
dangers we are pretending don't exist
that suggests that to some set of people
vaccinating people is a good in and of
itself that that is the objective of the
exercise not hurt immunity and
the last thing i'm sorry i don't want to
prevent you from jumping in here
but the second reason in addition to the
fact that we're exposing people to
danger
that we should not be exposing them to
by the way as a tiny tangent
another huge part of the soup that
should have been part of it that's an
incredible solution
is large-scale testing but that
that might be another couple-hour but
conversation but there's these solutions
that are obvious that were available
from the very beginning
so you could argue that ivaractin is not
that obvious
but maybe the whole point is you have
aggressive very fast research that leads
to
meta-analysis and then large-scale
production and deployment
okay at least that possibility should be
uh seriously considered coupled with a
serious consideration
of large-scale deployment of testing at
home testing
that could have uh accelerated
the the speed at which we reach that
um hurt immunity
but i don't even want to well let me
just say i am also
completely shocked that we did not get
on high quality testing early and that
we are still suffering
from this even now because just the
simple ability to track
where the virus moves between people
would tell us a lot about its mode of
transmission
which would allow us to protect
ourselves better instead that
information
was hard won and for no good reason so i
i also find this
mysterious you've spoken with eric
weinstein your brother on his podcast
the portal
about the ideas that eventually led to
the paper you published
titled the reserved capacity hypothesis
i think first can you
explain this paper and the ideas that
led up to it
sure easier to explain the conclusion of
the paper
um there's a question about why a
creature
that can replace its cells with new
cells grows
feeble and inefficient with age we call
that process which
is otherwise called aging we call it
senescence
and senescence in this paper
it is hypothesized is the unavoidable
downside
of a cancer prevention
feature of our bodies
that each cell has a limit on the number
of times it can divide
there are a few cells in the body that
are exceptional but most of our cells
can only divide a limited number of
times that's called the hayflick limit
and the hayflick limit uh reduces the
ability of the organism to replace
tissues it therefore
results in a failure over time of
maintenance and
repair and that explains why we we
become decrepit as we grow old
the question was why would that be
especially in light of the fact that the
mechanism
that seems to limit the ability of cells
to reproduce
is something called a telomere telomere
is a
it's a not a gene but it's a dna
sequence at the ends of our chromosomes
that is just simply repetitive and the
number of repeats
functions like a counter so there's a
number of repeats that you have
uh after development is finished and
then each time the cell divides a little
bit of telomere is lost
and at the point that the telomere
becomes critically short the cell
stops dividing even though it still has
the capacity to do so
stops dividing and it starts
transcribing different genes than it did
when it had
more telomere so what my work did
was it looked at the fact that the
telomeric shortening was being studied
by two different groups
it was being studied by people who were
interested
in counteracting the aging process and
it was being
studied in exactly the opposite fashion
by people who were interested
in tumerogenesis and cancer the thought
being
because it was true that when one looked
into tumors they always had
telomerase active that's the enzyme that
lengthens our telomeres
so those folks were interested in
uh bringing about a halt to the
lengthening of telomeres in order to
counteract cancer
and the folks who were studying the
senescence process
were interested in lengthening telomeres
in order to generate greater
repair capacity and my point was
evolutionarily speaking
this looks like a plyotropic
effect that the
genes which create the tendency of
the cells to be limited in their
capacity to replace themselves
are providing a benefit in youth which
is that we are
largely free of tumors and cancer at the
inevitable
late life cost that we grow feeble and
inefficient and
eventually die and that matches
a very old hypothesis in evolutionary
theory
by somebody i was fortunate enough to
know george williams one of the great
20th century evolutionists who argued
that senescence would have to be caused
by plyotropic genes
that cause early life benefits at
unavoidable late life
costs and although this isn't the exact
nature of the system he predicted it
matches
what he was expecting in many regards uh
to a shocking degree
that said the the the focus of the paper
is about the
well let me just read the abstract we
observed that captive rodent
breeding protocol is designed this is
the end of the abstract
we observe that captive rodent breeding
protocol is designed to increase
reproductive output
simultaneously exert strong selection
against reproductive senescence
and virtually eliminates selection that
would otherwise favor
tumor suppression this appears to have
greatly elongated the telomeres of
laboratory mice
with their telomeric fail-safe
effectively disabled these animals are
unreliable models of normal senescence
and tumor formation
so basically using these mice is not
going to lead to the right kinds of
conclusions
safety tests employing these animals
likely overestimate cancer risks
and underestimate tissue damage and
consequent
accelerated senescence so
i think especially with your discussion
with eric
the conclusion of this paper has to do
with the fact that
like we shouldn't be using these mice to
test the safety or to make conclusions
about
uh cancer or senescence is that the
basic
takeaway like basically saying that the
length of these telomeres is an
important variable to consider
well let's put it this way i think there
was a reason
that the world of scientists who was
working on telomeres did not spla
did not spot the plyotropic relationship
that was the
key argument in my paper
the reason they didn't spot it was that
there was a result that everybody knew
which seemed inconsistent the result was
that mice have very long telomeres but
they do not have
very long lives now we can talk about
what the actual meaning of
don't have very long lives is but in the
end
i was confronted with a hypothesis
that would explain a great many features
of the way mammals and indeed
vertebrates age but it was inconsistent
with one result and at first i thought
maybe there's something wrong with the
result maybe this is one of these cases
where the result was
achieved once through some bad protocol
and everybody else was repeating it
didn't turn out to be the case many
laboratories had established that mice
had ultra-long telomeres
and so i began to wonder whether or not
there was something
about the breeding protocols
that generated these mice and what that
would predict
is that the mice that have long
telomeres would be laboratory
mice and that wild mice would not and
carol grider who agreed to collaborate
with me
tested that hypothesis and showed that
it was indeed true
that while derived mice or at least mice
that had been in
captivity for a much shorter period of
time did not have ultra-long telomeres
now what this implied though as you read
is that our breeding protocols generate
lengthening of telomeres and the
implication of that is that the animals
that have these very long telomeres will
be
hyperprone to create tumors they will be
extremely resistant to toxins
because they have effectively an
infinite capacity to replace any damaged
tissue
and so ironically if you give one of
these ultra-long telomere
lab mice a toxin if the toxin doesn't
outright
kill it it may actually increase its
lifespan because
it functions as a kind of chemotherapy
so
the reason the chemotherapy works is
that dividing cells are more vulnerable
than cells that are not dividing
and so if this mouse has effectively had
its cancer protection turned off
and it has cells dividing too rapidly
and you give it a toxin
you will slow down its tumors faster
than you harm its other tissues
and so you'll get a paradoxical result
that actually some drug that's toxic
seems to benefit the mouse now i don't
think that that was understood
before i published my paper now i'm
pretty sure it has to be
and the problem is that this actually is
a system
that serves pharmaceutical companies
that have the difficult
job of bringing compounds to market
many of which will be toxic maybe all of
them will be toxic
and these mice predispose our system to
declare these toxic compounds
safe and in fact i believe we've seen
the errors that result from using these
mice a number of times most famously
with vioxx which
turned out to do conspicuous heart
damage
why do you think this paper on this idea
has not
gotten significant traction well
my collaborator carol grider said
something to me
that rings in my ears to this day
she initially after she showed that
laboratory mice have anomalously long
telomeres and that wild mice don't have
long telomeres
i asked her where she was going to
publish that result so that i could cite
it in my paper
and she said that she was going to keep
the result in-house
rather than publish it and at the time
i was a young graduate student i didn't
really understand
what she was saying but in some sense
the knowledge that a model organism is
broken in a way that
creates the likelihood that certain
results will be reliably generatable
you can publish a paper and make a big
splash with such a thing
or you can exploit the fact that you
know how those models will misbehave
and other people don't so there's a
question if somebody is
motivated cynically and what they want
to do
is appear to have deeper insight into
biology because they predict things
better than others do
knowing where the flaw is so that your
predictions come out true
is advantageous at the same time
i can't help but imagine that the
pharmaceutical industry when it figured
out that the mice were predisposed
to suggest that drugs were safe
didn't leap to fix the problem because
in some sense
it was the perfect cover for the
difficult job of
bringing drugs to market and then
discovering their actual toxicity
profile
right this made things look safer than
they were and i believe a lot of profits
have likely been generated downstream
so to kind of play devil's advocate it's
also possible
that this particular the length of the
telomeres is not a strong variable for
the conclusions
for for the drug development and for the
conclusions that carol and others
have been studying is that is that is it
possible for that to be the case
that this like so one reason she and
others could be ignoring this
is because it's not a strong variable
well i don't believe so and in fact at
the point that i
went to publish my paper carol published
her result
um she did so in a way that did not make
a huge splash
did she like whoa i apologize if i don't
know
how what was the emphasis
of her publication of that paper
was it purely just kind of showing data
or is there more
because in your paper there's a kind of
more of a philosophical statement as
well
well my paper was motivated by interest
in the evolutionary dynamics around
senescence i wasn't
um you know pursuing grants or anything
like that i was just working on a puzzle
i thought was interesting
carol has of course gone on to win a
nobel prize for
her co-discovery with elizabeth grider
of
telomerase the enzyme that lengthens
telomeres
but anyway she's a heavy hitter in the
academic world
i don't know exactly what her purpose
was i do know that she told me she
wasn't planning to publish and i do know
that i discovered that she was in the
process of publishing
very late and when i asked her to send
me the paper
to see whether or not she had put
evidence in it that the hypothesis had
come from me
she grudgingly sent it to me and my name
was nowhere mentioned and she has
she broke contact at that point
what it is that motivated her i don't
know but i don't think it can possibly
be that this result is unimportant
the fact is the reason i called her in
the first place and established contact
that generated our collaboration was
that she was a leading
light in the field of telomeric studies
and
um because of that this question about
whether the model organisms
are distorting the uh the understanding
of the functioning of telomeres is
it's central do you feel like you you've
been
as a young graduate student do you think
carol or do you think the scientific
community broadly screwed you over
in some way you know i don't think of it
in those terms probably partly because
it's not productive but you know i have
a
a complex relationship with this story
right on the one hand i'm livid with
carol grider for what she did
right she absolutely pretended that i
didn't exist in this story
and i don't think i was a threat to her
my interest was as an evolutionary
biologist
i had made an evolutionary contribution
she had tested a hypothesis and frankly
i think it would have been better for
her
if she had acknowledged what i had done
i think it would have enhanced
her work and you know i was
let's put it this way when i watched her
nobel lecture and i should say there's
been a lot of confusion about this nobel
stuff i've never said that i should have
gotten
a nobel prize people have misportrayed
that
um my in listening to her lecture
i had one of the most bizarre emotional
experiences
of my life because she presented the
work
that resulted from my hypothesis she
presented it
as she had in her paper with no
acknowledgment of where it had come
from and she had in fact portrayed
the distortion of the telomeres as if it
were a lucky
fact because it allowed testing
hypotheses that would otherwise not be
testable you have to understand as
a young scientist to watch
work that you have done presented
in what's surely the most important
lecture of her
career right it's thrilling
it was thrilling to see you know her
uh her figures projected on the screen
there right to have been
part of work that was important enough
for that felt great and of course to be
erased from the story felt absolutely
terrible
so anyway that's sort of where i am with
it my sense is
i what i'm really troubled by in this
story
is the fact that
as far as i know the flaw with the mice
has not been addressed
and actually eric did some looking into
this he tried to establish
by calling the jacks lab and trying to
ascertain
what had happened with the colonies
whether any change in protocol had
occurred
and he couldn't get anywhere there was
seemingly no awareness that it was even
an issue
so i'm very troubled by the fact that as
a father for example
i'm in no position to protect my family
from the hazard that i believe
lurks in our medicine cabinets right i'm
even though i'm aware of where the
hazard comes from
it doesn't tell me anything useful about
which of these drugs will turn out to do
damage if that is ultimately tested
and that's a very frustrating position
to be in
on the other hand you know there's a
part of me that's even still grateful to
carol
for taking my call she didn't have to
take my call and talk to some young
graduate student who had some
evolutionary idea that wasn't
you know in her wheelhouse specifically
and yet she did and you know for a while
she was a good collaborator so
well can i i have to proceed carefully
here because it's a complicated topic
so she took the call
and you kind of you're kind of saying
that she basically
erased credit you know pretending you
didn't exist in some kind of
in a certain sense
let me phrase it this way i've um as a
as a research scientist at mit i've had
especially just part of
a large set of collaborations i've had a
lot of students come to me
and talk to me about ideas perhaps less
interesting than what we're discussing
here
in the space of ai that i've been
thinking about anyway
it's in in general with everything i'm
doing with robotics
people will have told me
a bunch of ideas that i'm already
thinking about the point is
taking that idea see this is different
because
the idea has more power in the space
that we're talking about here and
robotics is like your idea means [ __ ]
until you build it like so the
engineering world is a little different
but it there's a kind of sense that i
probably forgot
a lot of brilliant ideas have been told
to me
do you think she pretended you don't
exist
do you think she was so busy that she
kind of
forgot you know that she has like the
stream of brilliant people around her
that
there's a bunch of ideas that are
swimming in the air
and you just kind of forget people that
are a little bit on the periphery
on the idea generation like or is it
some mix of both
uh it's not a mix of both um i know that
because
we corresponded she put a graduate
student on this work he emailed me
excitedly
when the results came in
so there was no ambiguity about what had
happened
what's more when i went to publish my
work i actually sent it to carol
in order to get her feedback because i
wanted to be a good collaborator to her
and she absolutely panned it made
many critiques that were not valid but
it was clear at that point that she
became an antagonist
and none of this adds up she couldn't
possibly have forgotten the conversation
um i believe i even sent her tissues at
some point
in in part not related to this project
but as a favor she was doing another
project that involved telomeres and she
needed
samples that i could get a hold of
because of the museum of zoology that i
was in
so this was not a one-off conversation i
certainly know that those sorts of
things can happen but that's not what
happened here
this was a relationship that existed
and then was suddenly cut short at the
point that she
published her paper by surprise without
saying where the hypothesis had come
from
and uh began to be a
opposing force to my work is there
there's a bunch of trajectories you
could have taken through life
do you think about the trajectory of
being
a researcher of then going to to war in
the space of ideas
of publishing further papers along this
line
i mean that's often the dynamic of
that fascinating space is you have a
junior researcher with brilliant ideas
and a senior researcher that
that starts out as a mentor that becomes
a competitor i mean that that happens
but then the way to uh
it's an almost an opportunity to shine
is to publish a bunch more papers in
this
place like to tear it apart to dig into
like really uh make it a war of ideas
did you consider that
possible trajectory i did a couple
things to say about it
one this work was not central for me
i took a year on the telomere project
because
something fascinating occurred to me and
i pursued it and the more i pursued it
the clearer it was there was something
there
but it wasn't the focus of my graduate
work and
i didn't want to become a telomere
researcher what i want to do
is to be an evolutionary biologist who
upgrades the toolkit
of evolutionary concepts so that we can
see
more clearly how organisms function and
why
and telomeres was a proof of concept
right that paper was a proof of concept
that the toolkit in question works um
as for the need
to pursue it further i think it's kind
of absurd and you're not the first
person to say maybe that was the way to
go about it but the basic point is look
the work was good
the it turned out to be highly
predictive
frankly the model of senescence that i
presented is now widely accepted
and i don't feel any misgivings
at all about having spent a year on it
said my
piece and moved on to other things which
frankly i think are bigger
i think there's a lot of good to be done
and it would be it would be a waste to
get overly
narrowly focused there's so many ways
through the space of science and
the the most common ways to just publish
a lot let's publish a lot of papers do
these incremental work and
uh exploring the space kind of like ants
looking for food is you're tossing out a
bunch of different ideas some of them
could be brilliant breakthrough ideas
nature some of the more confidence kind
of publications all those kinds of
things
did you consider that kind of
path and science of course i considered
it but i must say
the experience of having my first
encounter with the process of peer
review
be this story which was frankly a
debacle from one end to the other
with respect to the process of
publishing
it did not it was not a very good sales
pitch
for um trying to make a difference to
publication and i would point out part
of what i ran into and i think frankly
part of what explains
carol's behavior is that in
some parts of science there is this
dynamic
where pis parasitize their underlings
and if you're very very good you rise to
the level where one day
instead of being parasitized you get to
parasitize others
now i find that scientifically
despicable and it wasn't the culture of
the lab i grew up in
at all my lab in fact the pi
dick alexander who's now gone but who
was an incredible
mind and a great human being he didn't
want his graduate students working on
the same topics he was on not because it
wouldn't have been
useful and exciting but because
in effect he did not want any confusion
about
who had done what because he was a great
mentor and the idea was actually
a great mentor is not stealing ideas and
you and
you don't want you don't want people
thinking that they are so
anyway my point would be um
i wasn't up for being parasitized
i don't like the idea that if you are
very good
you get parasitized until it's your turn
to parasitize others
that doesn't make sense to me a
you know crossing over from evolution
into cellular biology may have exposed
me to that
that may have been par for the course
but it doesn't make it
acceptable and i would also point out
that my work
falls in the realm of synthesis
my work generally takes evidence
accumulated by others and places it
together
in order to generate hypotheses that
explain
sets of phenomena that are otherwise
intractable
and i am not sure that that is best done
with narrow publications that are read
by
few and in fact i would point to the
very conspicuous example of richard
dawkins
who i must say i've learned a tremendous
amount from and i greatly admire
dawkins has almost no publication record
in the sense of peer-reviewed papers in
journals what he's done instead
is done synthetic work and he's
published it in books which are not
peer-reviewed in the same sense and
frankly i think there's no doubting his
contribution
to the field so my sense is if richard
dawkins
can illustrate that one can make
contributions to the field without
uh using journals as the primary
mechanism for distributing what you've
come to understand
then it's obviously a valid mechanism
and it's a far better one from the point
of view of accomplishing what i want to
accomplish yeah it's really interesting
there is of course several levels you
can do the kind of synthesis and that
does require
a lot of both broad and deep thinking is
exceptionally valuable
you could also public i'm working on
something with andrew huberman now you
can also publish synthesis
sure that's like review papers they're
exceptionally valuable
for the communities it brings the
community together tells a history
tells a story where the community has
been it paints a picture of where the
path
lays for the future i think it's really
valuable and richard dawkins is a good
example of somebody that does that in
book form
that he kind of walks the line really
interestingly
like somebody who like neil degrasse
tyson who's more like a science
communicator
richard dawkins sometimes is a science
communicator but he gets
he gets like close to the technical to
where it's a little bit
it's not shying away from being
really a contribution to science no he's
made he's made real contributions
um in book form yes he really is
fascinating
i mean uh roger penrose i mean some
similar kind of
idea that's interesting that's
interesting synthesis does not
especially synthesis work
work that synthesizes ideas does not
necessarily need to be peer reviewed
it it it's peer reviewed
by peers reading it
well and reviewing it that's it it is
reviewed by peers which is not
synonymous with peer review and that's
the thing is people don't understand
that the two things aren't the same
right peer review is an anonymous
process that happens
before publication in a place where
there is a power dynamic right i mean
the joke of course is that peer review
is actually peer preview
right your biggest competitors get to
see your work before it sees the light
of day and decide whether or not
it gets published and you know again
when your formative experience with the
publication apparatus is the one i had
with the telomere paper
there's no way that that seems like the
right way to advance important ideas
yeah and you know what's the harm
in publishing them so that your peers
have to review them in public where they
actually
if they're gonna disagree with you they
actually have to take the risk of saying
i don't think this is right and here's
why right with their name on it
i'd much rather that it's not that i
don't want my work reviewed by peers but
i want it done
in the open you know for the same reason
you don't meet with dangerous people
in private you meet at the cafe i want
the work reviewed
out in public can i ask you a difficult
question
sure there is popularity
in martyrdom there's popularity
in pointing out that the emperor has no
clothes
that that can become a drug in itself
i've confronted this in scientific work
i've done at
mit where there are certain things
they're not done well
people are not being the best version of
themselves
and particular aspects
of a particular field
are in need of a revolution and part of
me
wanted to point that out versus
doing the hard work of
publishing papers and doing the
revolution basically just pointing out
look
you guys are doing it wrong and then
just walking away
are you aware of the drug of martyrdom
of uh the
the ego involved in it that it can cloud
your thinking
probably one of the best questions i've
ever been asked um
so let me let me try to sort it out
first of all we are all mysteries to
ourself
at some level so it's possible there's
stuff going on
in me that i'm not aware of that's
driving but in general i would say one
of my better
strengths is that i'm not especially ego
driven
i have an ego i clearly think highly of
myself
but it is not driving me i do not crave
that kind of validation
i do crave certain things i do love a
good
eureka moment there is something great
about it and there's something even
better about the phone calls you make
next when you share it
right it's pretty it's pretty fun right
i really like it
i also really like my subject
right there's something about a walk in
the forest
when you have a tool kit in which you
can actually look at creatures and see
something deep right i like it
that drives me and i could entertain
myself for the rest of my life
right if i if i was somehow isolated
from the rest of the world but i was in
a place that was biologically
interesting
you know hopefully i would be with
people that i love
and pets that i love believe it or not
but
you know if i were in that situation and
i could just go out every day
and look at cool stuff and figure out
what it means i could be all right with
that
so i'm not heavily driven by the
um the ego thing as you put it so i
i'm completely the same except instead
of the pets i would put robots
but so it's not it's the eureka it's the
exploration of
of the subject that brings you joy and
fulfillment it's not the ego
well there's there's more to say no i
really don't think it's the ego thing
um i will say i also have kind of a
secondary passion for robot stuff i've
never made anything
useful but i do believe i believe i
found my calling
but if this wasn't my calling my calling
would have been
inventing stuff i really i really enjoy
that too so i get what you're saying
about the analogy
quite quite well um as far as the
martyrdom thing
i i understand the drug you're talking
about and i've seen it
more than i felt it i do if i'm just to
be completely candid
and that this question is so good it
deserves a candid answer
i do like the fight
right i like fighting against people i
don't respect and i like winning
but i have no interest in martyrdom
one of the reasons i have no interest in
martyrdom is that i'm having too good a
time
right i very much enjoy my life and
that's such a good answer
i have a wonderful wife i have
amazing children i live in a lovely
place
i don't want to exit any quicker than i
have to
that said i also believe in things and a
willingness to exit if that's the only
way
is not exactly inviting martyrdom but it
is an acceptance that
fighting is dangerous and going up
against powerful forces
means who knows what will come of it
right i don't have the sense that
the thing is out there that used to kill
inconvenient people i don't think that's
how it's done anymore it's primarily
done through
destroying them reputationally which is
not something i
relish the possibility of but
there's a difference between a
willingness to face the hazard rather
than a desire
to face it because of the thrill right
for me the thrill is in um
fighting when i'm in the right i've i
think i
feel that that is a worthwhile way to
take what i see as the
the kind of brutality that is built into
men
and to channel it to something useful
right if it is not channeled into
something useful it will be channeled
into something else so it damn we'll
better be channeled into something
useful
it's not motivated by fame and
popularity those kinds of things
it's there you know you're just making
me realize that
enjoying the fight
fighting the powerful an idea that you
believe is right
is a kind of um
it's a kind of optimism for the human
spirit it's like
we can win this it's almost like you're
uh
turning into action into personal action
this hope for
for humanity by saying like we can win
this
uh and that makes you feel
good about like the rest of humanity
that if there's people like me then
we're going to be okay even if you're
like your ideas
might be wrong or not but if you believe
they're right and you're fighting the
powerful
against all odds then we're going to be
okay
that that to me if i were to project i
mean that because i enjoy the fight as
well
i think that's the way i that's what
brings me joy
is it's almost like uh it's optimism
um in action well it's a little
different for me
and again i think you know i uh i
recognize you you're familiar
your construction is familiar even if it
isn't mine right
um for me i actually expect
us not to be okay and i'm not okay with
that
but what's really important if i feel
like what i've said is i don't know of
any reason that it's too late
as far as i know we could still save
humanity and we could get to the fourth
frontier or something akin to it
but i expect us not to i expect us to
[ __ ] it up right
i don't like that thought but i've
looked into the abyss and i've
done my calculations and the number of
ways we could not
succeed are many and the number of ways
that we could manage to get out of this
very dangerous phase of history is small
but the thing i don't have to worry
about
is that i didn't do enough right
that i was a coward that i
you know prioritized other things
at the end of the day i think i will be
able to say to myself and in fact the
thing that allows me to sleep
is that when i saw clearly what needed
to be done
i tried to do it to the extent that it
was in my power and
you know if we fail as i expect us to
i can't say well jeez that's on me
you know and you know frankly i regard
what i just said to you as something
like
a personality defect right i'm trying to
free myself
from the sense that this is my fault on
the other hand my guess is that
personality defect is probably
good for humanity right it's a good one
for me to have
it you know the externalities of it are
positive
so i don't feel too bad about it yeah
it's funny so yeah
our perspective on the world are
different but they rhyme
like you said because i i've also looked
into the abyss
and it kind of smiled nervously back
so uh i have a more optimistic sense
that we're going to win
more than likely we're going to be okay
right there with you brother i'm hoping
you're right i'm expecting me to be
right
but back to eric because you had a
wonderful conversation in that
conversation
he played the big brother role and he
was very happy about it
he was self-congratulatory about it i
mean
can you talk to the ways in which eric
made you a better man
throughout your life yeah hell yeah
i mean for one thing you know eric and i
are interestingly similar in some ways
and radically different in some other
ways and it you know
it's often a matter of fascination to
people who know us both because almost
always people meet one of us first and
they sort of
get used to that thing and then they
meet the other and it throws the model
into chaos
but you know i had a great advantage
which is i came second
right so although it was kind of a pain
in the ass to be born into a world that
had eric in it because he's a force of
nature
right it was also terrifically useful
because
a he was a very awesome older brother
who you know made interesting mistakes
learned from them and conveyed the
wisdom of what he had discovered
and that was uh you know i i don't know
who else
ends up so lucky is to have that kind of
person blazing the trail it also
probably you know my my hypothesis for
what
birth order effects are is that they're
actually adaptive
right that the reason that a second born
is different than a firstborn
is that they're not born into a world
with the same niches in it right
and so the thing about eric is he's been
completely dominant
in the realm of fundamental
thinking right like what he's fascinated
by is the fundamental of fundamentals
and he's excellent at it which meant
that i was born into a world where
somebody was becoming excellent in that
and for me
to be anywhere near the fundamental of
fundamentals was going to be pointless
right i was gonna be playing second
fiddle forever and i think that that
actually drove me to the other end
of the continuum between fundamental and
emergent and so i became fascinated with
biology and have been since i was
three years old right i think eric drove
that
and i have to thank him for it because
you know
i mean i never thought of you so eric
drives towards the fundamental and you
drive towards the emergent
the physics and the biology right
opposite ends of the continuum and
as eric would be quick to point out if
he was sitting here
i treat the emergent layer i seek the
fundamentals in it which is sort of an
echo of
eric's style of thinking but applied to
the very far
complexity he's uh overpoweringly
argues for the importance of physics the
fundamental of the fundamental
he's not here to defend himself is there
an argument to be made
against that or biology the emergent
the study of the thing that emerged when
the fundamental acts
at the universal at the cosmic scale and
builds
the beautiful thing that is us is much
more important
like uh uh psychology biology
the systems that we're actually
interacting with in this
human world are much more important to
understand than
low-level uh theories
of uh quantum mechanics and general
relativity
now i can't say that one is more
important i think there's probably a
different
time scale i think understanding the
emergent layer
is more often useful but the bang for
the buck
at the far fundamental layer may be much
greater
so for example the fourth frontier
i'm pretty sure it's going to have to be
fusion powered
i don't think anything else will do it
but once you had fusion power
assuming we didn't just dump fusion
power on the market the way we would be
likely to if it was invented
usefully tomorrow but if we had fusion
power
and we had a little bit more wisdom than
we have you could do an
awful lot and that's not going to come
from people like me
who you know look at dynamics can i
argue against that please
i think the way to uh
unlock fusion power is through
artificial intelligence
is so i think most of the breakthrough
ideas
in the futures of science will be
developed by ai systems
and i think in order to build
intelligent ai systems
you have to be a scholar of the
fundamental of the
emergent of biology
of the neuroscience of the way the brain
works
of intelligence of consciousness and
those things
at least directly don't have anything to
do with physics
well you're making me a little bit sad
because my
addiction to the aha moment thing is
incompatible with
you know uh outsourcing that job like
outsourcing i don't want to outsource
that thing to you yeah moment
you know and actually i've seen this
happen before because some of the people
who
uh trained heather and me were
phylogenetic systematists
arnold kluge in particular and
the problem with systematics is that to
do it right
when your technology is primitive you
have to be
deeply embedded in the philosophical and
the logical
right your method has to be based in
the highest level of rigor once you can
sequence genes
genes can spit so much data at you that
you can overwhelm
high quality work with just lots and
lots and lots of automated work
and so in any in some sense there's like
a generation of phylogenetic
systematists
who are the last of the greats because
what's replacing them is sequencers
um so anyway i maybe you're right about
the ai
and i guess you said
i like figuring stuff out is there
something that you disagree with
ericon they've been trying to convince
them you've failed so far
but uh you will eventually succeed
you know that is a very long list eric
and i have
have uh tensions over certain things
that recur
all the time and i'm trying to think
what would be
you know the idea in the space of
science in the space of philosophy
politics family
love robots
well all right let me i'm just going to
use your
podcast to uh make a bit of cryptic war
and just say that there are
many places in which i believe that i
have
butted heads with eric over the course
of decades and i have seen him move in
my
direction substantially over you've been
winning
he might he wouldn't battle here there
but you've been winning the war
i would not say that it's quite possible
he could say the same thing about me and
in fact i know that it's true there are
places where he's absolutely convinced
me but in any case i do believe it's at
least
you know it may not be a totally even
fight but it's it's more even than some
will imagine
um but yeah we have um you know there
are things i say that drive him
nuts right like when something
you know like you heard me talk about
the um
what was it it was the autopilot
that seems to be putting a great many
humans in
needless medical jeopardy over the covet
19 pandemic
and my feeling is we can say this
almost for sure anytime you have the
appearance of some
captured gigantic entity that is
censoring you on youtube and you know
handing down dictates from the who and
all of that it is sure that there will
be
a certain amount of collusion right
there's going to be some embarrassing
emails in some places that are going to
reveal some shocking connections
and then there's going to be an awful
lot of emergence
that didn't involve collusion right in
which people were doing their little
part of a job and something was emerging
and you never know what the admixture is
how much are we looking at actual
collusion and how much are we looking at
an emergent process but you should
always walk in
with the sense that it's going to be a
ratio and the question is what is the
ratio in this case
i think this drives eric knots because
he is very focused on the people i think
he's focused on the people who have a
choice
and make the wrong one and anyway
he makes a question of the ratio is a
distraction to that
i think i think he takes it almost as an
offense
because it grants cover
to people who are harming others
and i think i think it offen offends him
uh
morally and if i had to say i would say
it alters his judgment on the matter
but anyway certainly useful just to
leave open
the two possibilities and say it's a
ratio but we don't know which one
brother to brother do you love the guy
um
hell yeah hell yeah and you know i'd
love him if he's just my brother
but he's also awesome so i love him and
i love him for who he is
so let me ask you about uh back to your
book hunter gatherers guide to
the 21st century i can't wait
both for the book and the videos you do
on the book that's really exciting that
there's like a structured organized way
to present this
um i kind of uh
from an evolutionary biology perspective
a guide for the future
using our past at its the fundamental
the emergent
way uh to uh present a picture of the
future
let me ask you about uh something that
you know i think about a little bit in
this modern world which is monogamy
so i personally value monogamy one girl
ride or die there you go ryder no that's
exactly it
but that said
i i don't know what's the right way to
approach this
but from an evolutionary biology
perspective or from just looking at
modern society that seems to be an idea
that's not
what's the right way to put it
flourishing
it is waning it's waning um
so i suppose based on your reaction
you're also a supporter of monogamy or
the
you value monogamy are you and i just
um delusional
um what can you say about monogamy
from the context of your book from the
context of evolutionary biology
from the context of being human yeah i
can say
that i fully believe that we are
actually enlightened and that although
monogamy is waning that it is not waning
because there is a superior system
it is waning for predictable other
reasons
so let us just say it is
there is a lot of pre-trans fallacy here
where people go through a phase where
they recognize that actually we know a
lot about
the evolution of monogamy
and we can tell from the fact that
humans are somewhat sexually dimorphic
that there has been a lot of pollution
in human history
and in fact most of human history was
largely polignous
but it is also the case that most of the
people on earth today belong to
civilizations that are at least
nominally monogamous and have practiced
monogamy and that's
not anti-evolutionary what that is
is part of what i mentioned before where
human beings
can swap out their software program and
different
mating patterns are favored
in different periods of history so i
would argue
that the benefit of monogamy the primary
one that drives the evolution of
monogamous patterns in humans
is that it brings all adults into child
rearing
now the reason that that matters is
because human babies are very
labor in order to raise them properly
having two parents
is a huge asset and having more than two
parents having an extended family
also very important but
what that means is that for a population
that is expanding
a monogamous mating system makes sense
it makes sense because it means that the
number of offspring that can be raised
is elevated it's elevated because all
potential parents are involved in
parenting whereas if you sideline a
bunch of males by having a polygenous
system in which one male has many
females which is typically the way that
works
what you do is you sideline all those
males which means the total amount of
parental effort is lower
and the population can't grow so what
what i'm arguing is that
you should expect to see populations
that face
the possibility of expansion endorsed
monogamy
and at the point that they have reached
carrying capacity you should expect to
see polygeny break back out
and what we are seeing is a kind of
false sophistication
around polyamory which will end up
breaking down
into polygony which will not be in the
interests of most people
really the only people whose interests
could be argued to be
in would be the very small number of
males at the top
who have many partners and everybody
else suffers
is it possible to make the argument if
we focus in on those males
at the quote unquote top with uh many
female partners
is it possible to say that that's a
sub-optimal life
that a single partner is the optimal
life well it depends what you mean i
have a feeling that you and i wouldn't
have to go very far
to figure out that um
what might be evolutionarily optimal
doesn't match my
values as a person then i'm sure it
doesn't match yours either you know try
to
can we try to dig into the that gap
between those two sure
um i mean we can do it very simply uh
selection might favor your engaging in
war against a defenseless enemy
or genocide right
it's not hard to figure out how that
might put your genes at advantage
i don't know about you lex i'm not
getting involved in no genocide
it's not going to happen i won't do it i
will do anything to avoid it so
some part of me has decided that my
conscious self and the values that i
hold
trump my evolutionary self and
once you figure out that in some extreme
case that's true
and then you realize that that means it
must be possible in many other cases and
you start going through all of the
things that selection would favor and
you realize that a fair fraction of the
time
actually you're not up for this you
don't want to be
some robot on a mission that involves
genocide when necessary
you want to be your own person and
accomplish things that you think are
valuable and so among those
are not advocating you know let's
suppose you're in a position
to be one of those males at the top of a
politicianist system we both know why
that would be rewarding
right but we also both recognize we yeah
sure lots of sex yeah okay what else
lots of sex and lots of variety
right so look every red-blooded american
russian male can understand why that's
appealing
right on the other hand it is up against
an alternative
which is having a partner with whom
one is bonded especially closely
right right and so a love
right well you know i don't wanna i
don't wanna
uh strawman the polygamy position
obviously polygamy is complex and
there's nothing that stops
a man presumably from loving multiple
partners and from them loving him back
but in terms of you know if love is your
thing there's a question about okay what
is the
quality of love if it is divided over
multiple partners
right and what is the net consequence
for love
in a society when multiple people will
be frozen out for every individual
male in this case who has it and
what i would argue is and you know
this is weird to even talk about but
this is partially me just talking from
personal experience
i think there actually is a monogamy
program in us and it's not automatic
but if you take it seriously
you can find it and frankly
marriage and it doesn't have to be
marriage but whatever it is that results
in a lifelong
bond with a partner has gotten a very
bad rap
you know it's the butt of too many jokes
but the truth is
it's hugely rewarding it's not easy
but if you know that you're looking for
something right if you know that the
objective actually exists
and it's not some utopian fantasy that
can't be found if you know that there's
some
real world you know warts and all
version of it
then you might actually think hey that
is something i want and you might pursue
it and my guess is you'd be very happy
when you find it
yeah i think there is uh getting to the
fundamentals of the emergence i feel
like there is some kind of physics of
love so one
when there's a conservation thing going
on so if you have like many partners
yeah in theory you should be able to
love all of them deeply
but it seems like in reality that love
gets split
yep now there's another law that's
interesting in terms of monogamy
i don't know if it's the physics level
but if you are
in a monogamous relationship by choice
and almost as in slight rebellion
to social norms that's much more
powerful like if you choose
that one partnership that's also more
powerful
if if like everybody's in the monogamy
there's this pressure to be married in
this pressure of society
that's different because that's almost
like a constraint on your freedom
that is enforced by something other than
your own ideals it's
by by somebody else when you yourself
choose to i guess create these
constraints
that enriches that love so there's some
kind of love function
like e equals mc squared but for love
that i feel like
if you have less partners and it's done
by choice
that can maximize that and that love can
transcend
the biology transcend the evolutionary
biology forces
that have to do much more with survival
and all those kinds of things
it can transcend to take us to to a
richer experience
which we have the luxury of having
exploring of happiness
of of joy of fulfillment all those kinds
of things
totally agree with us and there's no
question
that by choice when there are other
choices
imbues it with meaning that it might not
otherwise have
i would also say you know i'm
i'm really struck by and i have a hard
time not feeling
terrible sadness over what
younger people are coming to think about
this topic
i think they're missing something so
important and so hard to phrase
that and they don't even know that
they're missing it they might know that
they're unhappy
but they don't understand what it is
they're even looking for because
nobody's really been honest with them
about what their choices are and i have
to say
if i was a young person or if i was
advising a young person which i used to
do
again a million years ago when i was a
college professor four years ago
but i used to you know talk to students
i knew my students really well and they
would ask questions about this and they
were always curious because heather and
i seemed to have a good relationship and
many of them knew both of us
so they would talk to us about this if i
was
advising somebody i would say do not
bypass the possibility that what you are
supposed to do
is find somebody worthy
somebody who can handle it somebody who
you are compatible with and that you
don't have to be perfectly compatible
it's not about dating until you find the
one it's about finding somebody
whose underlying values and viewpoint
are complementary to yours sufficient
that you fall in love
if you find that person opt out together
get out of this damn system that's
telling you what's sophisticated to
think about love and romance and sex
ignore it together right that's the key
and
i believe you'll end up laughing in the
end if you do it you'll discover
wow that's a hellscape that i opted out
of
and this thing i opted into complicated
difficult worth it nothing that's worth
it
is ever not difficult so we should we
should even just skip the whole
statement about difficult yeah all right
i just i want to be honest it's not like
oh it's
you know it's non-stop joy no it's
freaking complex
but um but worth it no question in my
mind
is there advice outside of love that you
can give to young people
you were a million years ago a professor
is there advice you can give to young
people high schoolers college students
uh about career about life
yeah but it's not they're not gonna like
it because it's not easy to
operationalize
so and this was a problem when i was a
college professor too people would ask
me
what they should do should they go to
graduate school i had almost nothing
useful to say
because the job market and the market of
you know pre-job training and all of
that these things are all
so distorted
and corrupt that i didn't want to point
anybody to anything
right because it's all broken and i
would tell them that
but i would say that results in a kind
of uh
meta-level advice that i do think is
useful
you don't know what's coming you don't
know where the opportunities will be
you should invest in tools rather than
knowledge
right to the extent that you can do
things you can repurpose that no matter
what the future brings to the extent
that you know if you
as a robot guy right you've got the
skills of a robot guy
now if civilization failed and the stuff
of robot building
disappeared with it you'd still have the
mind of a robot guy and the mind of a
robot guy can re-tool around all kinds
of things whether you're
you know forced to work with uh you know
you know fibers that are made into ropes
right
your mechanical mind would be useful in
all kinds of places so invest in tools
like that
that can be easily repurposed and invest
in
combinations of tools right if
civilization keeps limping along
you're going to be up against all sorts
of people who have studied the things
that you studied
right if you think hey computer
programming is really really cool
and you pick up computer programming
guess what you just entered a
large group of people who have that
skill and many of them will be better
than you
almost certainly on the other hand if
you combine
that with something else that's very
rarely combined with it
if you have i don't know if it's
carpentry
and computer programming if you take
combinations of things
that are even if they're both common but
they're not commonly found together
then those combinations create a
rarefied space
where you inhabit it and even if the
things don't even really touch
but nonetheless they create a mind in
which the two things are live and you
can move back and forth between them
and you know step out of your own
perspective by moving from one to the
other
that will increase what you can see and
the quality of your tools
and so anyway that isn't useful advice
it doesn't tell you whether you should
go to graduate school or not
but it does tell you the one thing we
can say for certain about the future is
that it's uncertain and so prepare for
it
and like you said there's cool things to
be discovered in the intersection of
uh fields and ideas and i would
look at grad school that way actually if
you do go
or i see
i mean this is such a like every course
in grad school
undergrad too was like this little
journey
that you're on that explores a
particular field
and it's not immediately obvious how
useful it is
but it allows you to to discover
intersections between that thing
and some other thing so you you're
bringing to the table this
these pieces of knowledge some of which
when intersected might
create a niche that's completely novel
unique and will bring you joy
i have that i mean i took a huge number
of courses in uh theoretical computer
science
most of them seem useless but they
totally changed the way i see the world
in ways that are i'm not prepared or is
a little bit difficult to kind of make
explicit but
taken together they've allowed me to see
for example the world of robotics
totally different
and different from many of my colleagues
and friends and so on and i think
that it's a good way to see if you go to
grad school was
as a opportunity to explore
intersections of fields even if the
individual fields seem useless
yeah and useless doesn't mean useless
right useless means
not directly applicable but directly a
good useless course can be the best one
you ever took
um yeah i took uh james joyce a course
on james joyce
and that was truly useless
well i took uh i took immunobiology
in the medical school when i was at penn
as
uh i guess i would have been a freshman
or a sophomore i wasn't supposed to be
in this class
it blew my goddamn mind and it still
does
right i mean we had this i don't even
know who it was but
we had this great professor who was like
highly placed in the world of
immunobiology
you know the course is called
immunobiology not immunology
immunobiology it had the right focus and
as i recall it
the professor stood sideways to the
chalkboard
staring off into space literally
stroking his beard with this
bemused look on his face through the
entire lecture
and you know you had all these medical
students who were so furiously writing
notes that i don't even think they were
noticing the person delivering this
thing but
you know i got what this guy was smiling
about it was like
so what he was describing you know
adaptive immunity is so
marvelous right that it was like almost
a privilege to even be saying it to a
room full of people who were listening
you know
but anyway yeah i took that course and
you know lo and behold
that's gonna be useful well yeah
suddenly it's
front and center and wow am i glad i
took it but um
anyway yeah useless courses are great
and actually eric
gave me one of the greater pieces of
advice at least for college than
anyone's ever given
which was don't worry about the prereqs
take it anyway
right but now i don't even know if kids
can do this now because the prereqs are
now enforced by a computer
but back in the day if you didn't
mention that you didn't have the prereqs
nobody stopped you from taking the
course and what he told me which i
didn't know was
that often the advanced courses are
easier in some way
the materials complex but you know
you know it's not like intro bio where
you're learning a thousand things at
once
right it's like focused on something so
if you dedicate yourself you can you can
pull it off
yeah stay with an idea for many weeks at
a time and it's ultimately rewarding and
not as difficult as it looks
can ask you a ridiculous question please
what do you think is the meaning of life
well i i feel terrible having to give
you the answer i realize you asked the
question but if i tell you you're gonna
again
feel bad i don't want to do that but
look there's two
there can be a disappointment it's no
it's gonna be a horror
right because we actually know the
answer the question
oh no it's completely meaningless
there is nothing that we can do that
escapes
the heat death of the universe or
whatever it is that happens at the end
and we're not going to make it there
anyway but even if you
were optimistic about our ability to
escape every
existential hazard indefinitely
ultimately it's off or not and we know
it right
that said once you stare into that abyss
and then it stares back and laughs or
whatever happens
right then the question is okay given
that
can i relax a little bit right and
figure out well what would make sense if
that were true
right and i think there's something very
clear to me
i think if you do all of the you know if
i just take the values that i'm
sure we share and extrapolate from them
i think the following thing is actually
a moral imperative
being a human and having opportunity
is absolutely [ __ ] awesome right a
lot of people don't make use of the
opportunity and a lot of people don't
have opportunity
right they get to be human but they're
too constrained by
keeping a roof over their heads to
really be free
but being a free human is fantastic and
being a free human
on this beautiful planet crippled as it
may be
is unparalleled i mean what could be
better how lucky are we that we get that
right so if that's true that it is
awesome to be human and to be free
then surely it is our obligation to
deliver that opportunity to as
many people as we can and how do you do
that
well i think i know what job one is job
one is
we have to get sustainable the way to
get the maximum number of humans
to have that opportunity to be both here
and free
is to make sure that there isn't a limit
on how long we can keep doing this
that effectively requires us to reach
sustainability
and then at sustainability you could
have a
horror show of sustainability right you
could have a totalitarian sustainability
that's not the objective the objective
is to liberate people
and so the question the whole fourth
frontier question frankly
is how do you get to a sustainable and
indefinitely sustainable state
in which people feel liberated in which
they are
liberated to pursue the things that
actually matter to pursue
beauty truth compassion
connection all of those things that we
could list as
unalloyed goods those are the things
that people should be most liberated to
do in a system that really functions
and anyway my point is
i don't know how precise that
calculation is but i'm pretty sure it's
not wrong
it's accurate enough and if it is
accurate enough then
the point is okay well there's no
ultimate meaning but the proximate
meaning is that one how many people can
we get to have this wonderful experience
that we've gotten to have
right and there's no way that's so wrong
that if i invest my life
in it that i'm making some big error
yeah sure that life is awesome and we
want to
spread the awesome as much as possible
yeah you sum it up that way spread the
awesome spread the loss
so that's the fourth frontier and if
that fails if the fourth frontier fails
the fifth frontier will be defined by
robots and hopefully they'll learn the
lessons
that the of the mistakes that the humans
made and build a better world
hopefully very happy here and that they
do a better job with the place than we
did
but i can't believe it took us this long
uh
to talk as i as i mentioned to you
before
that we haven't actually spoken i think
at all
and i i've always felt that we're
already friends
i don't know how that works because i've
listened to your podcast a lot
i've also sort of uh loved your brother
and so like it it was like we've known
each other for the longest time
and i hope we can be friends and talk
often
again i hope to that you get a chance to
meet some of my robot friends as well
and fall in love
and i'm so glad that you love robots
as well so we get to share in that love
so i can't wait for us
uh to interact together so we went from
talking about some of the worst failures
of humanity
to so some of the most beautiful aspects
what else can you uh ask for from a
conversation thank you so much for
talking today
you know lex i feel uh the same way
towards you and i really appreciate it
this has been a lot of fun and i'm
looking forward to our next one
thanks for listening to this
conversation with brett weinstein and
thank you to
jordan harbinger's show expressvpn magic
spoon
and for sigmatic check them out in the
description to support this podcast
and now let me leave you with some words
from charles darwin
ignorance more frequently begets
confidence than does knowledge
it is those who know little not those
who know much
who so positively assert that this or
that problem
will never be solved by science thank
you for listening
and hope to see you next time