the following is a conversation with
george st pierre
considered by many to be the greatest
fighter in the history of ufc
and mma but even more than that one of
the greatest
martial artists ever quick mention of
our sponsors
all form expressvpn blinkist
theragun and the information check them
out in the description to support this
podcast
as a side note let me say that getting
the chance to hang out with george
talk to him on the podcast record a
quick self-defense video that
i'll release soon all while both of us
wearing suits
was one of the most memorable days of my
life
in setting all this up i talked to joe
rogan and originally we couldn't
schedule a chat with him and george on
the jre
which allowed me to pretend for a brief
time
that george came down to austin just to
see me
who the hell am i in truth him and joe
probably conspired to make me feel
special
but that's the point it's inspiring to
see george
and joe who are at the top of their
field
treat others as equals as human beings
no matter who they are
even silly russians in a suit meeting
george
was an honor for me beyond words
this is a lex friedman podcast and
here's my conversation
with my long time martial arts hero and
now
my friend mr george sampire
in your fighting career where you're
more motivated by
the love of winning or the fear
and hatred of losing i like to win
better than i hate to lose because if it
would not have been the case
i would never have fought in the first
place because i don't like
to fight at all but you talked about the
anxiety
the fear that you experience leading up
to a fight so
to you ultimately the reason to go
through that
difficult process is because it feels
damn good to have your hand raised
there is that there is also the fact
that
martial art i've been introduced when i
was very young
and it's probably the best thing i can
do in my life
fighting it's that's what i do best
also it provides me of
freedom of access of things that
most of people do not have
but all that as a price and a lot of
money i made a lot of money of course
with it
i was maybe predisposed with certain
abilities
i met incredible mentors
throughout my life i worked really hard
and of course i had a lot of chances the
the stars were all aligned
and in order to to
kept keep that those advantages
of freedom money and glory and excess of
things that most people don't have and
have the these
dream life that i have i had
to sacrifice myself and fight in order
to keep it
it's very hard to understand because i
also believe most fighters are not like
me
they a lot of guys because i corner a
lot of guys
and it seems to me that they love their
job they enjoyed
to to go fight in a cage i love to train
i love the science
of fighting the sport the to to be in
good shape the confidence that
training in mixed martial art give me
however i do not like the feeling
of uncertainty the stress that i have
not knowing if i will be badly injured
or humiliated or
winning the fight it's to me unbearable
and it
that's what takes the most out of me
more than
brain damage more than anything that's
what takes the most out of me
but the thing you get from it is the
freedom that you
get because uh because of the money but
because of the celebrity because of
everything that comes with it
so you can be the best version of
yourself because of fighting but
at the same time you've said that quote
i don't believe there's pleasure in life
i believe there's only a relief from
pain
we have to suffer to be on top so isn't
there something to just the
suffering in itself just doing really
difficult
just to get to the top to explain that
and
so people can relate to it because not
everybody is a fighter
i think the best example i can
[Music]
gives is let's say you're you haven't
eat for a long time
and you're craving right so you're
suffering and then when it's time to eat
finally
you're about to eat your favorite dish
it's gonna taste so much better so
that's why i believe
there's always a some sort of sacrifice
before the pleasure and the more
sacrifice you do
like they say in fighting the bigger the
risk
bigger is the reward and i feel that's
that's how it is
for me yeah i feel that with uh i've
started fasting a little bit
in the past couple of years and uh
there's nothing as
amazing as a delicious meal or anything
actually anything any food when you
haven't eaten for several days
it's it's kind of incredible uh it's not
incred
it's not incredible in this simple way
of finally i get to eat
it's you get to truly experience the the
beauty of
of what it is to be alive like that
little piece of food
you see all the flavors you you you
feel just the experience of it is uh
ultimately
of gratitude of how awesome it is to be
alive
but when you eat many times a day and
you're pigging out and
you don't get to experience that and
it's fascinating it's re it's really
like fasting
is one of the most accessible things for
people i think to experience that kind
of
uh pairing of hardship to pleasure
i agree and in my case it changed my
life
on a good good way i cannot recommend it
to people because everybody is different
but after my to to fight michael bisping
my last fight
was against uh the champion in the
heavier
weight class that i used to compete at
so
i thought that if i would gain weight
it would increase my performance yeah
and i struggled a lot to gain weight i
gained a lot
about eight to 10 10 pounds normally i
walk around
185 pounds and for that fight i was
walking around 195
however i forced myself to eat like six
times a day i was
on a very strict diet
and i didn't feel it didn't feel right
to me because
i feel like i i was carrying like a
little bit like i was carrying a bag
on my shoulder and
i think it was a bad idea for me because
when i
did the weight the weigh-in and i i
go went on a scale at 185 i couldn't go
back to my
initial weight that was 180 195 that i
worked
so hard for several months to get there
so i was 190 pounds but i couldn't get
back
and the morning of the fight i i i got i
got sick i had like uh
we didn't know what what it was and the
beginning
because in order to know to find out
what it was i needed to do what they
call a colonoscopy they put a camera
inside of you and to do that
they give you um something that makes
that empty you and i was trying to gain
weight not to lose weight
so i i told myself i'm gonna wait after
the fight
whatever it is because it was pretty bad
it was blood and
i i didn't know what i was i was very
concerned concerned i thought i had
maybe cancer i was freaking out
so i said i'm gonna do that fight and
then after right away i'm gonna make a
checkup
so i did that fight everything went well
i won the fight i went back home i did
the colonoscopy and i
i got diagnosed with ulcer colitis
then i got on very severe medication
to get better and i'm not a big fan of
medication i was
trying to look for more natural way to
to to get better and i found out about
fasting
and it really changed my life i met dr
jason
fong was one of the one i'm
one of the world authority of fasting
he treat diabetes patient with fasting
and he gave me a program of fasting and
it really changed my life and right away
what i did
is i went in in a cat scan to see the
difference
because it was right after my fight with
michael bisping and i
i did the cat scan so i had my uh
muscle mass bone density uh fat
percentage water retention it's pretty
amazing
it can show you which harm has more
muscle than
the other it's very precise and i did it
like uh
two two months after yeah so i i started
doing um
time restricted eating uh sixteen eight
but
right that right away when i started i
did
three days water fast and the doctor
jason funk says because i like to train
during those days
i cons i consume himalayan salt to make
sure
because when you sweat there's a lot of
minerals to to make sure you don't
depleted your mineral and um
when i went when i compared the two
results in the cat scan i found out
my biggest concern was to lose muscle
mass i found out that i did not lose
muscle mass
instead of losing it i it increased a
little bit
even though my weight on the scale
was lighter i i kept the same muscle
mass even
increases a little bit my bone density
increases a little bit
my water retention is the biggest thing
that decrease so the my inflammation
and my fat percentage so basically the
by looking at the data
i found out that by eating
so much trying to gain weight for to
fight michael bisping i only increases
my water retention which is not good
because it's like dead weight and
inflammation on you
so what uh was the actual process of
fasting
she said 16 8 time restricted so
intermittent fasting but you also
mentioned the three out
of the three day water fast what did
that feel like
and you also said training during the
three day yeah
how did that feel oh can you give me
some details of absolutely this is
fascinating
so i do three days water fast
uh four times a year nice and for me
i do it everybody's different but for me
i do it after
uh new year's because during the the
early days that's when i
i eat bad foods and i drink i see it
more like a like a cleansing you know
like a
like like a detox so to speak mental too
like psychologically yes
i do it after the new years right before
the summer
cut for the beach yeah yeah yeah after
the summer because of the summer i've
been
partying a little bit sometime let
myself go and right before the
the holidays and um i've tried the doc
dr fungi says to me say george everybody
is different
because i'm a very active person and
everybody has a different genetics so so
for me i i feel that three days is the
sweet spot
because i still train during those three
days the first day the first
two days i don't change nothing i i
train regularly on every
on my regular schedule however on the on
the third day
i modify a little bit i i do something
more
[Music]
more easy and that's how i do it and
i've tried before because i when i say
three days is my
sweet spot i've tried to go up to five
days
but the problems is after my third days
i i
found out that i had a big problem
sleeping i i get into a
hyperactive mode yeah they call that the
hunter-gatherer uh
uh mode you know like you you you you
your brain
i mean it's amazing your creativity is
at its peak
but you cannot sleep very well and
sleeping
for me i think it's very important so
that's why i do three days for me it's
my sweet spot
that's interesting you're right it's the
four or five days when you start
see sleep is not important for me so the
creativity is really important
so it's very interesting with the places
your mind goes after a few days
you're right but uh i mean
what does it do to your mind so you
mentioned your body likes it
in terms of training does it um do you
find that it helps you focus and think i
mean you're one of the
great strategic thinkers in terms of
martial arts does it help
with learning does it help with thinking
does it help with strategizing and all
that
well unfortunately i got into fasting
after i retired i wish i would have i
really wish people
asked me would you have done it during
the time that you competed and the
answer is yes
i think we live in a society that we're
bombarded by publicity
oh buy this eat protein this that and
fasting nobody makes money with it
because there's nothing
to sell you know i think that's why
a lot of people have not heard about it
and even my
for myself if someone would have talked
to me about fast the benefits
of fasting when i was training
before i got sick i would probably have
ignored
ignored him because it i'm not you know
it was it's hard to believe sorry it
sounds ridiculous
yes it's going to help your mind and
you're going to gain muscle potentially
exactly and and perhaps people have
talked to me about it but i
kind of it went in one of my hair and
got out
from the other side you know but uh it
really changed my
my life and dying i i was diagnosed with
ulcer colitis
and it helps me get rid of all my
symptoms what i do is
i know a lot of people have ulcer
colitis and and
for me i cannot recommend it to to other
people because everybody is it's
different but
for me i made a a lot of research
of how people from those circulations
got better and i found out that a lot of
people that got that condition get
better in the natural way
fasting eating fermented food collagen
and like bone broth and stuff all i got
and it made a huge difference in my life
i just wish i would have known that
before
so do you have a specific diet wise
stuff you like so
you know i've recently another
ridiculous sounding thing but it makes
me feel
really good it's very low carbs so
you know keto even carnivore it sounds
ridiculous
it doesn't make any sense but it makes
me feel really good even for performance
is rogan has an influence you know he's
a no carnivore diet
i was influenced actually by people yeah
like he
there's i'll tell you where cause i was
doing it before he was doing it uh
is there's it was uh popular in the
endurance athlete community
where it was fat adapted athletes it's
people who
insane people who run 50 miles 100 miles
they
figured out that they could fuel their
body by
with fat they can go to fat as the
source of energy as opposed to carbs
so and i remember
hoping that i'll be able to learn how to
run 50 miles and so on
i've never done more than 22 but
it i i just remember switching away from
carbs
and feeling really liberated
like i wasn't thinking about food as
much i'm able to eat once a day
and feel really good i mean it i think
every everybody's body is different
but i think carbs make me lazy
maybe it's because uh yeah it's the
crash but also just
psychologically something it uh it
forces me to also think about food too
much
like it starts becoming you know art
just like you said our society is so
much about food there's so many
so much advertisement and so much of our
social life is about food
and so it's very easy to live life
like live day to day thinking when is
the next meal
like what am i gonna eat for lunch what
am i gonna eat for dinner what am i
gonna eat for breakfast
and uh if you're not careful that's
going to get in the way of you doing
cool for like
liberating yourself and thinking like
what am i actually passionate about in
this life
like creating and forgetting to eat
those kinds of things
and still being able to fuel your body i
don't know
it's been fascinating to to figure out
like later in life that carbs aren't
necessary to function well
it's it makes me think like we don't
know anything about nutrition
that's right yes you know um
personally i don't think i
could have a diet without carbs i love
chocolate too much
for me eating it's a it's a pleasure of
life i love my carbs i love my sugar
however if you talk about that i don't
have a specific diet
but recently i what i'm trying to do is
the days that i do not work out i only
eat
once that's kind of my rules plus i try
to respect
sixteen eight and do my three day fast
four time years and but the rest of the
thing i
i i i let myself lose because i
i don't think i would be happy if i if i
uh
if i if i don't give myself the the the
right to
to eat for me personally i love to eat
so much next
and um you talk about diet carnivore
diet is very interesting because i
a few years ago i went to africa in
masai mara
and it's a tribe in
in east africa and i went to visit
them i did a safari and i talked to them
and these guys they their diet is 99
carnivore they that's crazy and you
should see they're very beautiful people
shredded like yeah some people would say
oh it's genetic i'm like yeah maybe it's
genetic but
i mean and think about the eskimos also
that like most of their diet is
on on fish right they so
i believe it can be done you know like i
believe it can be done
like an exclusive carnivore diet and i
i think i'm gonna try it pretty soon
just to have the experience you know to
see how it feels like
where you're gonna hang out with joe be
careful bringing it up because he'll
convince you to uh forever switch to
carnivore definitely he loves it
i mean but just like you i think he
loves
food so he's he can't ever stay on
carnivore
it was funny because we went to an
italian restaurant together and
i still only eat meat like i love um
i love the constraints of discipline
that's that's partially why i like
carnivore i like saying no to food that
is delicious
[Laughter]
but a part of the problem is that i
don't know how to moderate you said
chocolate i don't know how to have one
chocolate is that something you're able
to do
have like in moderation no it's when it
when i have an opportunity i do it i
don't
have any i'm an extremist person alex i
i
that's the thing i when i when i have a
chance i
i like i i just eat i go too much and
that's why i like about my life you know
that's what i
like about fasting because probably if
i would not have discovered fasting
eating chocolate would give me cramps
and all sorts of problems yeah because
people on
circulitis normally they cannot eat
chocolate they cannot drink alcohol
but i believe because i'm fasting
that's the reason why i'm i'm medication
medicine medication free i can eat
whatever i want whenever i want
but i have to do that that fasting you
know and now it becomes to
it became to a point that it's no longer
hard for me it's it's like normal
i don't even force myself yeah i don't
it's easy
you know what i mean some of my friend
thinks i'm think i'm i'm insane you know
but i tell them it's like with when you
get used to it it becomes like an
abbot and i'm and i know that
hunter-gatherer
like our ancestor did not eat three
times a day
it's it's it's not true they
they ate when they they could and when
they eat they they
they they feed themselves as much as
they can until that
because the next time because they
didn't know when they could eat again
right so it's uh i think that's
how we're we're built you know to to to
have this similar lifestyle
if we could take a step back to the
discussion about fear
a little bit so mike tyson talks about
this process of him walking to the ring
he sounds similar to you in many ways
of the anxiety and the fear that he
experiences
and uh he has this uh
sort of story that he tells about
walking to the ring and being
supremely afraid but as he walks and
gets closer and steps in he finds the
confidence
and becomes supremely confident i think
he calls himself like a god i feel like
a god in the ring
is is do you go through a similar
process of finding the confidence
well it yes and um
i usually i use a james lange theory
they they did so what i do is because
i'm i'm
i'm not afraid to admit that i'm afraid
and uh in the beginning of my of my
career
i really thought i asked myself because
i was very good
in mixed martial but i i really thought
i wasn't made for this because
the idea of fighting didn't
was was didn't make me happy it's
something like i
i was i was forced to do in order to
keep that lifestyle that i have
and achieve my goal perhaps one day to
make enough money to
retire and you know that that was my
dream but when i was looking around
the gym where i was training most of my
training partner they were happy they
were excited and sometimes i corner i
corner a lot of guys and they're happy
and they're in the locker room they
don't react the same way
i do some perhaps does but
if you see me in the locker room
like when i get like my last fight with
michael bisping just to give you an
example
in my last fight with michael bisping
because it's fresh it's the one that is
the most recent
and but it's always the same thing my
last fight
and my thing i get in the locker room i
had like
three guys that i trained with mickey
gall
amon zahabi and uh joseph duffy
they all lost it was like like my locker
room was
basically cursed you know the
when you're in the locker room and
people from your locker room leave for a
fight and then they come back it's kind
of a momentum you know you
you shake and yeah good job now it's my
you know it's kind of a
team brotherhood sort of thing
so the the the
the atmosphere in my locker room was
pretty bad it was like uh
going to a you know like a funeral
so i was very scared and ever before
every fight i
i asked myself i i asked myself always
what the hell i'm doing here why
did i choose to come back oh my god
and i'm freaking out however
i'm putting on a mask like i'm acting
because if i don't do that it will
reflect on my coaches
and if my coach might the confidence of
my coaches is affected
it will reflect reflect on me so i need
to feel strong
i need to make them believe that
i'm excited to be there and i'm happy to
be there so
this sort of play start when i
get when i first step in the locker room
even though i
feel completely different but that's how
i play it
normally the day the fight day i never
felt
feel 100 i always feel exhausted tired
my highs are hitching because i don't
sleep enough the few nights before
because i'm constantly
rehearse rehearsing scenarios that might
happen and i find
so mentally it's not
that i'm not on top but you keep all
that to yourself
i keep it to myself and i'm lying to
everybody around me
but everybody knows you know for us
john denahar they they know freddie
roach they've been with me for a long
time so they know what's going on but at
least
i'm lying to them i'm like i'm feeling
great so and seeing all my training
partner
like very disappointed because they lost
their fight some were
were badly hurt as well it was hard
so and i remember i get i get more i get
i start to warm up and everything and as
you start to warm up
you become a different person because
you know
cert we know that certain posture and
yoga can have
affects your men there's mental state
but it's i would say it's a little bit
the same thing in in fighting you know
like when you start hitting the pads
you your your muscle memory your
instincts comes back and and
you remember that you're good at this
you know and your confidence start to
grow
and as seeing your trainers holding the
pad and then repeating your moves
it makes you also remember all the
sacrifices you have done through your
your training camp and confidence come
from how you prepared yourself
and even you're afraid you can be
confident
confident in the same time being afraid
and being confidence is two different
thing
and before every fight just right before
i walk in
it's when i'm scared i go in in the
bathroom
and i look at myself in the mirror i
used to have a bandana and a ghee
but now i it no more i didn't have this
this for my last fight because of the
the the new reebok deal they had but i
did the same rehearsal that i always do
i look at myself in the mirror and i
start to compliment
myself like even if i don't believe it
i'm starting to trying to believe it as
i am i'm finding all the reason why i'm
going to win the fight
and and all my trainer knows that before
every fight when when the guy from the
ufc goes and
steppen maroon says saint pierre are you
up next i always take a few minutes
to do that that same rehearsal and i
tell myself i'm gonna win this fight
because
i'm better and and i'm very cocky about
myself i'm telling all the reasons that
i'm gonna
you know when i'm i got a better team i
made more sacrifice you know
i'm i'm faster i'm more powerful way
more athletic my fighting iq is better
than him i got a strategy on point
that he's never going to be able to keep
up with and and this and that
and i'm and be i was telling myself hey
i'm going to show these young kids
how things should be done you know i'm
trying to boost myself yeah
try to to boost yourself and you start
to believe in it you become a different
person
so when you walk out the bathroom now
rock and roll now i really believe it
for real you know like i'm still scared
but i believe
it for real and that's the
transformation that happened for me
right there and from that from now
from from there to the fight it's until
the fight is over it's called
i call it cruise control because i do
not have time to think in a fight if
you're trying to think you're missing
the opportunity so that's how i see it
for myself so at that point you stop
thinking and you just go cruise control
autopilot trust yourself you know trust
yourself because you you repeated
all the scenarios you know so everything
that you have done it's it's inside that
your computer your computer your brain
is programmed to react
accordingly to certain situations and
the it's not the the night of the fight
that you you'll tell yourself oh finally
i'm gonna do this if you do this now now
if you have not practiced it before
you're screwed it the preparation the
repetition that
makes it happen you know what about like
the
really difficult moments in a fight
where you
are tested to your limits essentially
usually it's cardio related exhaustion
right where you have to ask yourself
that same questions like why the hell am
i doing this
yeah do you do do you experience those
or
are you able to ride through the
autopilot and if you do like what do you
do in those moments
never in a fight when i'm in a fight
when it's the the
when the fight is is on i never change
my mind i go
until the end however
for example my first fight would be
japan i
had a terrible first round so i had to
switch gear
that happened sometime but it's part of
my plan i always have a plan b
plans plan a plan b plan c
you need to have that if fighters goes
into a fight thinking oh what i'm gonna
do this is this
and they don't have a plan b if this
doesn't work
that's mean they're not well prepared if
you talk to me before
every fight i can like in 30 seconds
give you my old strategy
you know for bj penn my first fight
would be japan was
i'm gonna keep it standing up
keep the fight from the outside you know
because i'm faster than him
then the fight would be japan's start i
found out that
i was not faster than him and i found
out that
his reaction time was better than than
than mine
so i got beat up the first round
and i got the bloody nose and everything
so my plan b
was now i'm gonna wrestle him you know
i'm gonna wrestle him and
you know make him tired and trying to
put him down and that's how i beat him
because i
switch gear you know but if you can't do
that if you cannot
find a way to become the perfect nemesis
to your opponent
you you you might win if you fight but
you you're gonna
find a uh you're gonna fight someone
sooner or later that will
that will give you a lot of uh a lot of
trouble
so that's where the anxiety pays off
you're anticipating all the ways it goes
wrong so you develop the plan b
and plan c hi you know we talked a lot
with uh like john donahue who you work
with
it's interesting i don't think i've
heard him talk about plan b and plan c
he usually has a really clear plan a
an entire system of plan a i don't think
i've heard him
we've had uh we had a a good discussion
about it
in um uh over some cheeseburgers
and he's uh he was kind of espousing the
value
of mastering escapes so
when you find yourself in bad situations
being
exceptionally good at finding ways out
of those bad situations and that's a way
of dominance
there's nothing there's no better way to
dominate your opponent
according to him than to show that they
can't possibly hurt you no matter how
bad the position is
uh it's like it's a as opposed to a
physical dominance it's a psychological
dominance it's very interesting
but i wonder if he has plan b
and plan c in his mind too you know in
uh
mixed martial arts sometimes it's like
in science something you can make a mis
like a mistake you know like every human
can make mistakes you know
there's certain sport or a certain
situation that you
if there's a mistake made you're you're
you're that's it
exactly sometimes it's the case in mma
but sometimes you
able to redeem yourself and uh
if you look the fight with bj pen
one that i had which was probably one of
the most competitive fight i
and it was probably the it was the fight
that i got the most
damage and i was messed up it took me
three days
like two three days to recuperate from
that fight i was really damaged
and my first fight versus my second
fight i made a lot of adjustment
because i i've learned from my first
fight and also i had a guy
one thing people don't know like they
talk about fighters having secret
weapons
see for me my secret weapons was not
like some is that they used like certain
like different things for me was
knowledge
i had a guy in montreal he was measuring
frames
he's not a scientist is he's a friend of
uh ferrous and i
and what he does he watch fight and he
measure frames
the way he does it is when you watch a
fight and one of the guy throw a punch
he
he cut the picture by frame the video by
frame
so he's able to see which fighter has
better reaction time than others
and bjpen he found out that bj penn
evolved the
ufc roster at the time when he was in
his prime he had probably the best
reaction time of all
according to him lyoto meshido was the
second one
but bj penn was the first one so
i knew that if i would try to go first
because i always been the fastest
guy normally when i fight someone but
when i fought big japan i tried to go
first and he was always able to like
i never was never able to to touch him
with my jab and he came back with a
counter punch
however because of what he told me
i knew that big japan has a very fast
reaction time but had a very poor
reset time to him the way he described
it to me is like your nervous system is
like a muscle
bj pen was so fast but he's like more
like a sprinter
so what i did the second fight i when i
fought with japan i made him flinch
like i fake a lot so i make him react
and flinch so all that that reaction
time
that he used to flinch was not used
properly to avoid my punches so he i
burn i i load up his his nervous system
with a lot of information and fit and
fake and to make him flinch and
pretending i was kicking and wrestling
so he got overwhelmed and he got tired
very very fast so that's how i beat him
people sometimes they don't know
really what's the strategy behind the
thing they only see the physical part
but when you fight someone if i fight
you i look at you in the eyes
there's a lot of things that going on
between you and i
i can look down here pump jab you in the
face
the audience will not see this little
detail
but you will see it and that's what it
makes the magic
during a fight the relation that you
have with the opponent you know like
like the mental game what you you make
him believe
those little things i use a lot of those
if you
talk to a lot of my opponent they'll
tell you like i use a lot of these
little thing you know like i look down a
banana i go
i go up or i'm pretending i want to
attack you so i'm i'm
making flinch but in reality i'm just
doing this
because i want to rest i want to
recuperate and i'm tired
how much is you know people talk about
that with poker for example
how much is the value of this you know
so like some people argue that poker is
more about the betting
you know it's just the money it's just
how much you bet and so on
so that would be more like uh the
analogy there with
with fighting would be just strictly the
physical movement of your body
and then a lot of people argue that
there's a lot here in the way you look
in the little movements in the face
so do you think there's do you think
you're communicating
with your opponent when you look at them
there's no way to know for sure 100
and i'm by no no mean psychic nothing
like that and i don't believe in that at
all
the only thing is i know to looking
through the eyes of my opponent
when he's afraid and when he gives up on
me yeah i've been accused very often
in my career to not take enough risk to
not
finish my opponent but the reason why i
didn't finish my opponent is because
i saw in his eyes that he gave up he
gave me the fight and i'm winning the
fight
so it's not up to me
it's not to me to make it to try to
sacrifice myself trying to finish him
perhaps if i do that i will open up from
for him to
to to capitalize on my mistake
it's up to him to make a risk so
people sometimes they they don't
understand that this is the art of
fighting my friend you know
like if i'm winning the fight like in
aki and isaac
if you're winning the game and it's the
third period
it's at the end of the third period
you're not gonna take out your
goaltender trying to score another goal
because winning
uh uh five to three or five to four
is the same thing same thing in mma we
make a living out of this
and sometimes you know as sad as bad as
it can be
you want to save yourself for another
day you know you want to minimize the
damage
but if he knows he's losing the fight
it's up to you him to take the risk it's
not up to me
so i'm having i'm a good counter fighter
i use a lot of my attack or counter
strike or uh reactive techno proactive
take down
that's my specialty so i'm not gonna i
i'd have no desire to sacrifice myself
trying to to trying to finish my
opponent if he want to
if if if perhaps i might give him the
opportunity to capitalize on me
it's it's not it's not smart to do that
and very often when i fight someone i
can read him i see the fear in his eyes
now i'm like i
got you now he's very desperate that
doesn't mean i have to
put my guard down because he's going to
be desperate but i know i'm beating you
and i know i'm beating you i'm just
going to do what i need you know if i
have a chance of course i'll knock him
out
but i'm not gonna try to sacrifice
myself to knock you out
and if you do that maybe one day you'll
make a mistake and
you'll get dropped and you're you'll
you'll tell yourself i shoot
i just got brain damage maybe i'm never
gonna come back the same maybe you know
i
i ruin my career or you know it's a it's
a very serious
game that we're playing it's very
dangerous in the face of that
risk i mean uh mike tyson talked about
you know when the opponent looks away he
knows he's got him
right that uh that he's broken
for a person like me who has trouble
making eye contact with people
there's there's truth to that i mean
there there's truth to that
that there's there's an animal nature to
us looking away
i mean you could see that the way the
body language
the way the eyes move between two
animals going at it
uh in in the wild when like two lions
fight or
to whatever fight there's a certain
beta move when you've you've been
defeated
yes or one thing when i know that that
when it happened one of the sign is when
i just like
made a faint and the guy flinched like
crazy that's mean he's really scared of
me
it's a little bit like you're you're
you're you're doing this that guy flinch
a little bit or you're doing this he's
flint like
that's mean you hurt him and he doesn't
want to get hurt again so he's really
trying to
run away and not
not winning the fight anymore but not
losing sort of surviving the the five
round and it's hard to
to finish a guy who does doesn't want to
fight
a guy who's not fighting anymore to win
and he's fighting to not lose
and the proof of that if you don't
believe me just look the reign of all
the greatest champion in ufc
i don't care who they are jon jones or
uh
like you could clearly see that in the
beginning of their rank they could
you know finish a lot of their opponents
the same as me in the beginning i was
finishing all of my opponent
but there's a time that the entire ufc
roster is studying you
and they found ways to perhaps not
beating you but they found a way to
navigate to the the fight in a way that
they minimize the damage
you know what i mean so it's a big
difference between fighting to win and
fighting to not lose
you said that there's a difference
between a fighter and a martial artist
so now we were talking about fighting
you're considered by many to be one of
the greatest fighters of all time
but you've said that there's a
difference between a fighter and a
martial artist
a fighter is training for a purpose he
has a fight
i'm i'm a martial artist i don't train
for a fight
i train for myself i'm training all the
time
my goal is perfection but i will never
reach perfection
so what do you does it mean to be a
martial artist
martial artist is because that lifestyle
that i have has been introduced to me
and the seed has been planted to my mind
a long
long time ago by my father i
am i do not train
because i have a fight i will always
train even now it kind of
amused me that to see that
a lot of people because i'm still
training because i love the science of
fighting i do not like to fight but i
love the science of it
and i will always do it as long as i can
do it
people think i'm going to make a
comeback and everything i'm i'm about to
get to have
40 years old you know like it's i have
you know like well mike
i want to fight in a cage at 40 years
old i mean some people have done it they
did it very well but i
i'm not one of them i'm i feel a little
bit to me that
and you never say never i feel like to
me like it's a little like a kid that
you play with this train when he's young
like
he's five years old brother six years
old or seven years old eight years old
and then i was like
what the hell i'm doing here and i'm too
old for this like i said
i i have done it you know and
and and i got out of it
on top and i'm i'm healthy which is the
most important thing
right now i'm touching wood and i'm i'm
wealthy
i beat the game you know what i mean in
a way like i that's not to be cocky but
i did it and i wish
more more fighters could do the same
thing i wish
but it's unfortunate because a lot of
them they stay
there and hang out for too long and and
they get badly hurt they get
beaten and and and broken you know
and they finish broke as well because
the lifestyle you have when you're a pro
athlete
it's crazy you know it's it's it's
unbelievable
however everything that goes up in life
goes down
and you need to plan your future you
know so
for for me what if some guys have the
same mentality as me and they're
watching us right now i would say
if you do it because you're just good at
it you like the money the the advantage
the freedom that it gives you but you
don't necessarily like to fight
when you're done you finish on top you
know go
go cash out and get out of here walk
away this is
hard to do however lex it's not
everybody that
does it for that reason some people
generally love to fight love to compete
so they do it because i love it you know
or they do it because of the money but
if you don't
love it if you don't like to fight
because it's very stressful and you
don't enjoy you
you enjoy the training perhaps but you
don't like to fight you do it because
it's part of what you need to do in
order to keep that lifestyle
yeah and you know like
you don't need the money get out of here
man if you're in your
you're in your prime get out of here
because if you don't you you you'll hurt
your own legacy
your damage your your health it's it's
very sad
and and it's a it's a it's a sad
business you know what i mean i i
it's like a lot of uh one one of the
place
where is the the mo the mo one of the
most happiest place
for me to go and the most the saddest
place for me to go it's on the gym
to try sorry montreal because
it's one of the happiest place for me to
go because i can go train and do what i
love to do
but it's also a very sad place for me
because after when i'm about to leave
there's always a
bunch of young kid that comes or guys
that are
around 30 33 years old and they come to
me hey george you have some advice for
me
and i look at them and
if they're my friend they're real close
friend of mine i'll tell them the truth
in their face
and i've done it many times and it was
not well received
but if they're not my friend i have to
you know you know there's always an
advice about fighting and i answer
their their question it's my pleasure
but the truth if they
they want me to tell the truth the big
majority of them
i would tell them i said listen man
you're in a
maybe a three like an a on a losing
streak
of three fight you're 30 33 years old
you know i think you should think about
doing something else
in your life you know have other goals
you know because
you're not gonna make it and you know
i've seen that movie before
and it's a very sad ending and i'm i'm
sad to tell you the truth
because you're not going to make the
money just choose some
but if i tell them that they're going to
be angry at me because they're going to
be like oh you you make it and you think
i cannot make it so it's kind of
they're going to think i'm cocky but i
was lucky to make it you know what
the star were all annoying but at one
point you need to be able to
to have a plan b you know like like some
parent they come
to see me with their kids hey this is
the future world champion and then
in ufc and what advice would you give
him i always tell the same thing
and it doesn't not make everybody happy
when i said i say i go to the case say
are you good at school say stay at
school school is very important for you
stay educated yeah do boxing martial
arts it's a great sport stay in shape
but don't put your eggs all in the same
basket and the parents sometimes are
angry when i'm
not angry but i can see their eyes
they're like they kind of
surprise and it's not because i
made it that i will tell their kid to
follow the same path that i
did i went to school too i i studied
i i dropped of school when i had my
first world championship fight against
matt hughes
but before that i was school so i had
another
you know a a a a another way to go if
things would not have gone the same the
the way i wanted
but the problem and i'm saying that it's
not only about boxing in mma i'm talking
about hockey basketball baseball same
same thing maybe it's the one on the 100
000 that make it
and i'm saying i'm saying that make it
when i'm saying make it that's mean
they can retire and have enough money
for the rest of his life
because it's a sad story the only people
only heard about the people
that makes it but a lot of fighter even
a ufc
champion in boxing champion even
football basketball i don't i don't i
don't care the big names
when they retire they have zero they're
bankrupt my friend
and it's a very sad sad story and a sad
reality that most people are not aware
of
but having other paths in life actually
can also
increase the chance of you dominating
and like reaching the highest
peak uh in your main thing i mean jimmy
pedro i don't know if you know who that
is as a judo coach in uh
in america he was uh he says that to all
of his athletes is to make sure that you
go
he has a lot of you know kayla harrison
two-time olympic gold medalist
he has a lot of uh olympic medalists but
basically there's something about going
to school like having a
forget school any other avenue in life
that
gives you the freedom to go all out in
your main
like that you know you're doing it for
the right reasons
you're not stuck it clears the mind to
where you're
free to be the best in the world yes as
opposed
to kind of you have to i mean different
people are motivated by different things
so sometimes some people like
having their back to the wall and that's
the only option they have but
most people i think excel when you have
other options i think it's a distraction
and i think it's important to have a
distraction
uh when you say that i think about one
of my coach john danaher
he put his academic background
experience
into jiu jitsu and that for me that's
why he's the best teacher i ever had
he's incredible he started
teaching me when i even couldn't speak
much english at the time and
i was able to communicate and understand
you know that's how good he is
but i i truly believe that most of
athlete especially
in sport like mixed martial art trained
way too much
if i could go back and talk to a young
george
i would tell him say you do way too much
volume
you train way too hard train smarter
it's more important
and i think sometimes we underestimate
the benefit of uh
recuperation because you i think
we assimilate the information that we
learn
during a training when we recuperate and
not during the training itself
and this whole mentality of harder
heavier you know like like it's
it's good for someone who's lazy but if
you're an elite athlete
most of the time you know like you're
not always but most of the times because
you're not
lazy and a lot of guys sometimes they're
elite athletes champions and you hear
people
say oh i can't believe he's very gifted
but he doesn't work but perhaps it's not
really
because perhaps it's because we don't
understand perhaps he's doing the right
thing and it's
us who's working too much and too hard
that's what i think
there's a guy i train with he's uh he
made me
think about about it his name is mansoor
bernawi
he's going to be a future star is he's
an incredible fighter
he trained once a day
and he asked me some time advice when he
came in montreal he's from france you'll
hear about him he's
he's very good and
i i saw him in the morning at tristar
and i said okay i'll see you perhaps
later in the other 20s oh no i only
train once a day
and he kind of wait for me to give him
like like like
not not an approval but like
to see how i react or or you know i
don't know it was kind of a strange
feeling but
i i told myself at that point i kind of
i had an
awakening and i and i told myself man
maybe he's doing the right thing because
a lot a lot of people would say for
example oh that's a lazy way of doing it
but perhaps it's the best way to do it
i'm not saying
training once a day is the the best way
to do it that's what i'm saying i'm
saying that
everybody is different but for him it
works
beautifully and i wouldn't change
anything you know like
if i would be him because he is he's
improving like
crazy yeah and ultimately the bigger
picture there is
to do something that everyone else's uh
says is stupid it's like the fasting
thing
that that a lot of people would say a
lot of nutritional experts would say
that that's
that's a dumb way you know if you want
to be an mma fighter
you should be eating like many times a
day you should be starting every day
with oatmeal
you should be carbing up constantly but
that's not necessarily true for
everybody and
it's possible i'm sure there's actually
now a few mma fighters that are
carnivore only it's possible
i i used to eat right before training
and i it didn't bother me
however now i my first training
that i do normally in average around
noon 11
a.m i'm uh i'm i haven't eat anything
when i do my first training and it feels
to me that i'm much
i'm much more clear and much more clear
in my mind i'm much more creative
i feel better yeah yeah it's a big
difference i just wish i would have
known that before
you know well it's fascinating the role
of the mind and all this how important
is it for your mind to be clear to to
really think deeply
i there's a
there's a judoka american named travis
stevens
i remember he said something that
the right kind of practice is when your
mind is exhausted
at the end of it that you were
constantly thinking through things
like your body shouldn't be exhausted
first your mind should be exhausted
first
it's really fascinating so people think
about training hard
you know a successful practice is where
you walk away
just overwhelmed how much you have to
think
it's fascinating framing of of a
successful practice
it's true travis stephen was one of my
main training partners when i got ready
for my fight with
nick diaz and carlos conditt
he drove every friday
from i believe boston it's like a six
hour drive
drive to the gym in montreal
train with us an hour and a half
drive back
he's got such an amazing discipline i
was
so happy for him when he won the medal
at the olympic game man
what a well-deserved uh
you know uh accomplishment it's
unbelievable it paid off you know i'm
i was so happy for him and every time we
we got to the the gym it was waiting for
me in a in in
in the kneeling position like a soldier
i was like my god this guy he's made of
steel you know and and after training i
always have to offer him i say hey
travis i know you you like to train with
that because in montreal they have very
good judo team
nicholas gill and all that that was guy
and i say if you want to stay i'll get
you the hotel you know like every
anything you want is like no no i gotta
go back i have another training later
i'm like not only that he trained with
with us
he had to go back because he had another
training i'm like
this is insane and he's gone through a
huge number of injuries
so he's also an innovator because i mean
it's difficult to say but for american
judo there's not
many high-level judoka so if you want to
be the
like fight with the best in the world
you're you have to be alone
it's a lonely journey actually it's kind
of sad uh
it's much easier to be in japan where
everybody's a killer
when you're alone at it it's uh it's a
difficult journey
and you know it's it's funny we talked
about
kind of there's some sports where a
mistake
is um that's it you know you can't
recover from a mistake
i think judo oftentimes is one of those
sports and
added on top of that is um
the olympics only every four years
and travis's story he's the reason why
uh when i saw him in 2008 as i
i started martial arts uh i switched
from like wrestling and
street fighting to doing jiu jitsu and
judo
and i just saw so much guts and the in
i might be messing up the years here but
in the next olympics
he fought and he lost
on just the referee call yeah and just
he went to war and he just
so much guts and just everything
on the line and to lose and then to
still persevere through all their
injuries through all that
through incredibly difficult training
sessions to go another four years and
then
compete and then win a medal i mean that
guy is just
and like he clearly could have been very
successful
he's also an incredible jiu jitsu
competitor so he could have
switched to that but he's stuck in
in a lot of sport when you're in elite
like for example in canada i saw he's
the number one sport in the country
kids when they're in elite when they're
young they get chosen
and they're kind of uh already um
known as a superstar you know the the
school
where they go and on the program they
follow like i'm sure it's the same thing
in us and basketball
baseball perhaps uh american football
because they already chosen so they grew
up with that
uh that it that itsy kid that that
uh superstar stardom so to speak and
it's already gla glass sort of glamorous
you know
however in in mma there's no
mma judo wrestling like
in america because it's not our national
sport it's it
actually it's it's not like even when i
first started was
not really well received by the media
there's no glamour into it now i don't
know it seems like it's another
era now and i feel sometimes
that some people do it for the wrong
reason
you know some people do it because of
the glamour because of the money
but even if you're an elite and very
good the glamour and the money
won't come in the beginning it's a
very long grind before
you know it start it start to come in
and you need to make those sacrifices
and it's a it's a journey that where you
will be
tested you will be hurt repetitively
and you're gonna have to to reach the
down deep and come back up and then once
you finally think you made it you're
gonna go back in the down deep again
it's a very exhausting and decorating
um adventure sometimes but if you hold
on to your dream and you believe in it
you know and you have the the the stars
are aligned you're going to make it
that's why it's only a few people that
that make it you know
and and that's why i feel i feel
sometimes
the new a lot of people in the new
generation do it for the wrong reason
in my in my generation because a sport
at first it was there were no rules
i thought it was more pure the people
that did it was really
because of the passion that they we
didn't seek money and
fame we did it because we wanted to be i
did it
because i wanted to be the man you know
i i like
to have the confidence that when i walk
somewhere i'm you know i have the
confidence that
you know it's an illusion because nobody
is faster than a bullet yes
but i wanted to achieve it for myself
and i
which today now because i don't know if
it's social media and all that that
the world has changed the glamour the
you know it's i feel it's a different
thing right now
yeah the uh if you get in it for the
glamour or the money you may not have
the right
the right amount of fuel to persevere
through all the ups and downs
yeah sure you know when you talk about
motivation
of uh money and glamour
the a guy comes to mind and i don't know
how many wrestlers you know but
in russia there's a guy named
uh bovaci assatea of the satia brothers
one of the greatest
uh freestyle wrestlers of all time but
he also has um
it's funny he doesn't have many
interviews one of my goals is to go out
and
talk to him in russian do an interview
with him because he's
exceptionally poetic and a deep thinker
he's a the kind of martial artist that
you are
in the way that it's not just about the
the different battles you've been
through or whatever
it's about the philosophy behind the way
he approaches life
and he he's spoken quite a bit about
that the
the glamour the fame the money are all
things that get
in the way of um
the purity of the experience the art
that
the way to achieve greatness is to just
lose yourself in the art
of the actual combat
in this case it's wrestling and then
kind of not to worry and actively make
sure that you block out
anybody who you know
feeds you the narrative where you're
supposed to be this famous person and
all those kinds of things that uh he
basically says let others
write your story i make sure that you
just focus on the art
and now another person from that side of
the world is
of course khabib so he represents that
side of the world and we were talking
about walking away
and most people not being able to walk
away at
the top as you have but also now
could be has it looks like incredibly so
so
i mean maybe you can comment about what
your thoughts are
about uh khabib nurmagomedov being able
to just
walk away you know we talk about the
goat very often
khabib is you know one of isn't the
argument
because he has the most dominant
carrier of all martial art guy
you know some guys can be named the goat
for different reasons but khabib
for that reason and he's undefeated he'd
i don't even know if he lost he might
have lost
round but he'd dominate
all his opponent it was ridiculous and
such an incredible career that he had um
i love to watch him fight he's
incredible um
and when you talk about the art when you
say mixed martial art
the idea of a
flawless performance for me
everybody often when we say flawless
performance
thinks about a knockout a brutal
knockout
but for me it's it's to be able
to showcase beautiful technique
like a beautiful take down beautiful
submission be
like something beautiful that
you know when you you look at for
example uh
wayne gretzky or michael jordan or
like stephen curry or even if you don't
know
nothing about basketball and you watch
michael jordan
you'll be like wow that's beautiful what
you just did
like we talked about fighting and and
trying to say
the the word beautiful and fighting for
certain people it could
sound kind of crazy you know but but i'm
talking about the technique
a beautiful technique you know for me
that's the goal
you know when i was fighting it's not
only to to have a brutal knockout
because some people are more gifted than
others and so
i'm saying gifted some people are better
than others in certain
phases of fighting but for me it was
that it was to showcase
to win of course but to showcase some
beautiful technique that that you can
watch the
watch it and be like wow that was
incredible the timing he did it that
and when i talk when i think about kabir
norma gomanov
i see all the detail that that of his
work especially when he got he's got his
opponent
against defense that's like that's his
area of expertise where he's
to me he's the best that ever did it in
in terms of
that fighting style that that particular
expertise that he has it's just the the
flawless execution of that particular
set of techniques
yes conor mcgregor had the
the accuracy the spider anderson silver
was like was i would say the most
flamboyant of all you know like he was
moving like the matrix
john jones was incredible in terms of
creativity
spinning elbows and that and he faced
incredible
adversity symmetry johnson was
so complete you could you could bring
like he was slamming a guy to an armbar
it was just unbelievable like like
he was like the complete fighter
bj penn was like so flexible he he did
stuff with his body then
like nobody could do his dick the
dexterity of his hips was just
unbelievable
um dominic cruz to me was incredible his
footwork his distance control
so when you talk about like the goat
royce gracie another one
he did things that i think for me is not
number one because yeah i gotta i gotta
and starting to interrupt the hoist is a
fascinating one i'd love to hear what
you think about them but
many people consider you
most people consider you to be the
number one
greatest mixed martial arts fighter ever
so it's fascinating to remove you from
that list
and continue this discussion and asking
like who do you think is the greatest
fighter ever you listed some amazing
ones
hois you somehow skipped fedor it's as
i'm very as a russian i'm very offended
no i was going to there's so many
fedoras one
as well fedor i think in his prime was
like
when you say when you talk about a name
for example like
we talked about him when he was in his
prime like when i talked for example
about anderson silva i'm not talking
about the andersons
who fought his last fight uh against
urayo hall i'm talking about anderson
servo who knocked out
victor belfor yes bg pen same thing
the problem is when fighters hang on for
too long in the sport that's what
happened
they kind of make make
people forget how good they were and
it's very sad we talk about fedor and
just
just think about uh stephen yochich
me which is probably the greatest
heavyweight of all time with fedor
i would really wonder who would have won
this fight
the both guys in their prime i tend to
lean towards fedor because my heart was
with fever the fedor but he could have
gone the other way but just because meow
chich
lose his last fight now everybody's like
oh yeah they forgot about him
it's crazy man it's one fight you zig
when you shoot zag
boom it's that's the reality of mixed
martial art well that's why
the thing is the mixed martial arts
isn't just the performance the strictly
who won and who lost it's also the
stories we tell ourselves
and so i mean there's beautiful stories
being weaved
and that also is part of uh who is the
greatest of all time
is what what were the battles what what
what
had to be overcome what was the
the flavor of the flawless performances
you know all of that plays into it and
you're right
being able to walk away at the top is
also part of that
a lot of people ask me about khabib and
that fight i want it to happen
khabib wanted to happen but ufc did not
want to happen
between you and khabib yes and we tried
to make it like about
three three years ago when i when i
retired two you know three no it was
after
two years ago and it didn't never came
to fruition
the ufc were clear they said they would
they have their plan for khabib
and it makes sense to for the business
standpoint because they want to keep the
ball rolling
now can be retired and like everybody
else after just justin gaitrey i was
doing the comment theater in french
for the ufc and now i have butterfly i
thought he was going to call me out
if there's one guy that i would have
said yes it would be him because for a
fighter
the most exciting thing things to do
it's
often the scariest one and khabib was
you know where is the scariest matchup
yes
but it was worth the risk because nobody
have ever been able to solve them
how would you solve the khabib
nurmagomedov puzzle
well khabib is very good against the
fans
i would have to establish a game plan
and everything but i think
what i would needed to do is take the
center of the octagon right away
use a lot of fake and fate keep the
fight
all the way all the way out or all the
wind and when i sell the win is when you
close the gap use my proactive and
reactive
take down and my perhaps my superior
explosivity to put them down
i like to use those proactive and cr and
reactive technology because for me i
feel it's more economical
khabib is a much better chain wrestler
than me chain wear stories when you got
the guys to defense it's pure resting
what makes my takedown very efficient
it's my karate
it's not my wrestling it's i'm a i'm
very good at timing
my opponent and getting in
with with my explosivity so if you watch
at my takedown
it does not demand often it does not
demand a lot of work when i use the
i call it proactive takedown when um
he's coming to punch me and i react so
i mean proactive is when when i i'm
faking it so
i i i i instigate the attack down by a
fake
then i take take him down and reactive
is when he's
i'm baiting him to throw something and
then he then have a counter
yeah yeah yes but all might take down in
the center of the octagon
yes my takedowns are more in the center
of the octagon like for example another
guy that does it well is gleeson tebow
that did it well in his best
days you know khabib has more a style of
chain wrestling i would say like kamaru
uzman
or sort of speak kind of kind of guy
it's a different style you cannot
compare both town
and that's the kind of takedown i'm good
and i would if i would have fight kevin
that's one of the strategies i would
have had i would not have been afraid
because everybody that i thought i was
able to put them down
and and and i have the pedigree to to
prove it in my
fight resume so you would have perhaps
see him on his back and i would have
perhaps be on my back as well so it
would have been a very interesting fight
and
how hard do you think he is to take down
i mean a lot of people speak about his
wrestling being just it has nothing to
do with it like
the wrestling because let's do the
correct if i get that timing
and i got my boat hand around around his
knees he's going down
everybody goes down yeah yes yes this
goes down and and
and i had a lot of uh that's what i
would have done i would not have been
afraid of his wrestling
uh i would have be the instigator i
would have forced the fight
forward and that's what that's how i
would have approached that
fight which i believe most of his
opponent
were afraid of his wrestling because
they didn't have the tools that i have
to put him down
i would not have forced the wrestling i
would have in in the clinch i would have
tried to disengage i have many ways to
disengage the clinch
i would have wanted to force the fight
in in that in a
in a fighting distance you know like in
in a shoot box distance not in that in a
wrestling distance is it possible
this fight still happens i
you're young look great in a suit
well there's a lot of problems now
and the thing is now i made peace with
it
i no longer don't wanna fight and i
don't it's not gonna happen ufc
was not interested and i'm bound by
contract with the ufc
and by exclusivity there there's some
people says to me oh how about if
russians are a crazy uh a
wealthy russian guy come with money yeah
i i
i said i have the i'm gonna be uh in
court with ufc
and and also i'm older now and when i go
home man i'm like
i don't want to do this you know like
and we're always like this i don't want
to do this but
like for example i was training with
freddie roach a few days ago and i'm
hitting pads
you know and freddie is looking at me
and he's like hey
you have the hitch back i'm like yeah if
dana white would walk in the room in the
in the
gym at that precise moment with a with a
ufc contract
i would sign it sign it in a blink of an
eye
but then after i go home i'm like hell
no
no my belly is full my you know i'm
healthy i'm wealthy why would i want to
fight for i made peace with it
but the minute i go back in the gym
because i still get it inside me when i
train with the young guys
i still get it and a lot of guys think
hey
tell me the truth you're preparing a
comeback because i still get it you know
i'm a little bit
older but i i get more knowledge i can
compensate
i i i become a different animal because
you know it changed you but then after
you go home and you
you you're like man uh no way i'm doing
this
yeah it's very hard to explain you need
to be acquired one to understand that
it's very very hard to explain
well from your perspective i think
khabib
is one of the rare one of the few
fascinating scientific puzzles yet to be
solved
so from that aspect as a martial artist
it's just a fascinating journey to try
to solve that puzzle
there is a thing too like say oh who's
the best fighter people
lex they don't like i underst i i
realize that
later in my life and i'm sure a lot of
young guys will say oh i said
it's not don't speak for me but i'm
telling you right now what i'm about to
say you will realize it later
when i was young i think you can
proclaim yourself the
more the badass man on the planet you
know like nobody can beat you at
it's an illusion man that's the sad
thing about for example dc
uh daniel cormier does probably one of
the greatest
if not the greatest of all time you said
miyotis but like
it's almost because of that little
matchup with jon jones
it's it's difficult for people to
conceive of him as the greatest of all
time
it's all about match-up it's all about
timing and
also you make a fight you may you make
both guys fight ten times
the result might be different like
like every time you know i mean maybe
he's gonna win
eight out of ten but that knight is
gonna
he's gonna lose why because we don't
know the the universe made it like that
you know maybe he got sick maybe he had
the
emotional issues he didn't sleep well
and he makes him
uh lose focus and he got caught you
don't we don't know
but it's it's that's the thing with
people ask me would you
have done it with khabib what would
happen i don't know maybe out of 10 time
i don't know maybe
as a fighter i hope i would have win
more than him
he thinks the opposite is only one way
to find out but
that night if there's a fight the guy
gonna win doesn't mean he's the best
fighter that's mean
the the he's the one that fought the
best the night of the fight same thing
in basketball or aki the team that wins
the game
it's not necessarily the best team is
the team that
play the best the the night of the game
and fighting is no different
so being the baddest man on the planet
it's an illusion
i mean that's the tragic thing about it
is uh on any one night
anything can happen and then that tells
a story for all of human history
it is it's uh it's that
it's sad to think about but that's what
makes it beautiful that
there's so much at stake like entire
lives
all the dreams you've had growing up all
the hard work all of it is decided in a
single night
even though that means nothing in terms
of who's actually better
it's uh i mean that's the beauty that's
why people love the olympics especially
because it happens so rarely
and dreams are broken or uh
like triumph is achieved by the unlikely
hero
all like right there i mean that's
that's why we love it right that's why
that's why i love it
if we would know always the result
before it would be boring that's why we
do it you know
uh you watch the odds you know like like
sometimes
i like to watch the odds uh before a
fight you know
because you know there's things you know
i believe in causality you know i
believe in
everybody believe different things but i
believe everything is
because there's a there's a cause to
everything that's
personally what i believe i don't
believe that
i i have like free will i think i have
the illusion of free will but i believe
there's a cause for everything and if
i'm doing something
because of something because of a cause
by definition there's no free will in a
way you know
if there's a cause by definition there's
not how does that make you feel by the
way like the idea that if we just look
uh outside of even just human psychology
and fighting and so on if we look at
like physics if everything is
predetermined
if all of these little molecules
interacting it's already like your story
is already written i mean it depends
it's it's written but
i would need to know all the data and
it's impossible right
like it's it's i it's kind of weird i
gotta say but i don't
to me i don't see any argument
to counter that idea i i i i can
i don't maybe i'm i'm ignorant but i
haven't seen
nobody and everything from that i've
read so far
there's nothing that countered that idea
that that
because in a mechanical world if your
car
broke or you know we don't say oh the
car decided to broke
or a three a tree is fall
there's reason why the tree is falling
we don't say the trees decide to fall
right
so what because us human being i think
it's our ego
we decide and i'm no different than
anybody when i make a decision i
decided to do this i choose to do this
but i'm aware that there is causes
that make me do certain things and by
definition
i think if there is a cause there is no
free will by definition
right yes but the thing is just like you
said
we understand so little about human
intelligence the human mind and
especially
consciousness that
the this giant
mystery this darkness that we don't
understand how
how it how it feels like to be something
to be a conscious being
that because of that we're not able to
really even
reason about free will or not because
there might be some magic that comes
from
consciousness the you know the the
consciousness might be
the thing that makes us different from a
car that breaks down
there might be something totally
fascinating totally undiscovered yet
that will
make us realize that free will is
actually real and somehow fundamental to
the human experience
so it's sometimes i think
we forget when we talk about free will
and physics and it all seeming to be
predetermined
we forget how little we actually
understand about the world
and i think in that mystery that could
be
totally new ideas that are yet to be
discovered and will make us realize that
it's not just an illusion it is
something that is like
at the core of how the universe works
some people believe that consciousness
is a fundamental property of the
universe like it's a
it's a one of the forces of physics like
consciousness permeates
everything it's in everything like this
table is conscious but it's not
as conscious as us and we're this little
peak of consciousness
and if that's true and if we get to
understand that
maybe there's something there's an extra
bonus we get in terms of free will
once you become one of those entities
that are super conscious
so i i tend to be sort of humbled by the
mystery of it
do you believe one day with
with the technology that keep improving
we will
make a robot that will be able to
be somehow conscious absolutely
i that's been my dream that's been i
hope i hope to do just that
first of all i believe that all people
are capable
and want to be good to each other and
i think love is uh is a really powerful
thing that connects us and can create
better and better worlds
sort of like uh create better and better
societies that improve both the
technology the quality of life and just
the basics of human experience and i
think
creating ai systems that are conscious
that are human-like
can enable us to be better to each other
like they can it's almost like adding
more and more
kindness to the world through the
systems we interact with will inspire us
to be better and better to each other
in terms of them being conscious i think
that is a
an absolute requirement that entities we
interact with
communicate some element of
consciousness
to us like that's how we connect to each
other the reason we
you and i connect is that we believe
that
each of us are conscious and to me what
consciousness means
is the ability to hurt ability to to
suffer
to uh to struggle in this world because
just like you said uh
with with without the struggle you don't
have the love
you don't have the pleasure and
ultimately consciousness
is an entity's ability to struggle
to suffer and from that arises the
pleasure
and us together being able to
appreciate sort of uh
appreciate the highs and
experience together at the lows that's
how we form the deep connections
i personally think we can create that in
robots and i i personally believe it's
a lot easier than uh than we think does
it
make you afraid sometimes about
the fact that one day hey hi like
intelligence
artificial intelligence could be
you know could hurt us or or you know
like because we're
you know because of hollywood of course
you know the movies we watch but but it
seems
like when i hear sometimes elon musk
talking you know like
yeah so elon talks about with ai we're
summoning the demon
he is very concerned and i talked to him
about it
quite a bit he's very concerned about
all the different ways ai could
hurt us humans i tend to believe that
there's a lot more ways in which ai can
make our lives better
and can make life awesome for humans i
think
humans are the ones that can do a lot of
evil things so i'm less worried about
i am more worried about humans if i look
at what you men have done on
on the course of history you know for
for example
in regards to the planet to the the
scale of the universe
i think what i'm afraid is that we have
more
of a destructive force than a
beneficial force so if a height take
that and cause the duration
in order to protect us against ourselves
it could hurt us in a way i don't know
if you if you understand what like
what do you think about that does it
makes you afraid sometimes
not because of a hype but because of
what humans are doing
that heihei could do to us to prevent us
of hurting ourselves you know yeah no
i mean definitely it can bring out the
the worst in human nature
and uh provide tools
for evil people to do evil things at a
larger scale
but i just think it depends
what you think human beings are i tend
to believe
that as we get more intelligent we
we start to see the value the
evolutionary value
and the value in terms of happiness of
being good to each other and i think ai
if if you look at ai as an optimization
problem of how to create a civilization
that works well
and expands throughout the universe i
think love
is much uh more effective so ai will
help us
maximize that i think there's going to
be
always spikes throughout as it has been
through human history
where charismatic leaders will do evil
onto the world in the name of good you
have the stalin and the hitlers and all
of that
but ultimately
over time i think technology will give
the good uh the good people
power and the evil people
less power now there's a lot of ways in
that
in uh that that won't be the case
there's a lot of ways for it to go wrong
and elon talks about them but
i i honestly think in terms of
intelligent ai
that's going to bring more love to the
world the thing i'm concerned about is
dumb ai so there's been a lot of
discussion
between china and the united states
recently on autonomous weapons system
this is something people don't they're
afraid to talk about
but there's now a race
uh where the united states has
officially said
that they're not against adding ai to
its weapon systems so now the us
military
is adding automation adding intelligence
to its drones to its uh
anything that can create damage and so
of course
and they did this so in response to
china doing that
so you can imagine this is this is
terminator
you think about terminators intel
intelligent systems they're not
they're pretty dumb the the point is
they're efficient at doing what they do
and
in the space of war efficient at doing
what you do means
killing so that i'm really afraid of but
those are dumb ai
those aren't your uh loving
deep fulfilling relationships that's
like
uh efficiently being able to fly to plan
the trajectory of dropping bombs
of missiles of how to do counter-attacks
of how to maximize the destruction of a
particular facility instead of
individuals
and then that can just escalate
and as opposed to the cold war with the
with the soviet union
this could be a hot war and then
the consequences once you allow
it's kind of terrifying because
currently the drones are operated by
humans
so you know you have say you have
information about uh intelligence gives
you information about a particular
terrorist located at this area
and then you use drones to
maybe uh the automation there is to help
you
figure out what is the best trajectory
to
strike at that location so
you still have a human that pulls the
trigger at the end
dropping the bomb now automation and ai
in autonomous weapons systems might be
where you say
there's a bad guy over here you figure
out
how to get rid of the bad guy okay so
then
of course the systems will be very good
at finding the right trajectory and so
on
but there's bugs that can happen
unexpected bugs that the system might
figure out that there is
this bad guy might actually be in these
other
five locations so mike's might make
sense to cover the entire area right
and you see you might just drop bombs on
the entire area
and then you know that's just okay so
that's going to lead to a lot of
destruction of the scale of a city
but then you can immediately take that
to nuclear weapons
if you add automation to uh responding
to counterattacks to nuclear weapons
somebody you might get information that
somebody's planning a nuclear attack on
the united states
and the ai system will immediately
respond and
you know it can respond at a scale of
launching nuclear weapons itself
and so there's all of these
possibilities that don't require much
intelligence
and that's exceptionally that's
exceptionally concerning
i i'm like you i do not believe there is
babies that are born bad i think people
do bad things because of their
experience
however if i look
to my experience and from what i can see
some very often
men's of power wants more power
that's what makes me afraid with yeah no
absolutely
i listen i've been uh i've come from the
soviet union
uh stalin is arguably one of the most
powerful humans in history
uh he's not talked often enough about by
the evils he's done hitler gets all the
attention
yeah but stalin has done arguably much
more evil than uh than hitler
yeah well this is this is human nature
it wants power
we see that with institutions we see
that with governments and nations
i think you see you see this with the
internet
people are really hungry for the
distribution of power
like you see that people are very much
distrustful of centralized places of
power of institutions and so
on so i think successful organizations
successful companies
successful governments will be run by
people who distribute the power
like i don't trust myself with power at
all yeah and i think
you have to build into the system
that no one person can have power and
that you distribute it
that's where you have in the financial
sector you have cryptocurrency right now
with bitcoin and all those kinds of
things
people are exploring how can we avoid
the central bank
to have the control how do you put the
power in the hands of
people uh thousands of people millions
of people and in the same way with
uh with military with um any kind of
uh with technology i think the future
looks very distributed
so what do you think about militarizing
space
[Laughter]
the uh space force i i i don't think
about it often because
right now i'm filled with excitement
about space exploration which is the
positive aspect so elon
you know i was born in an
era where it was exciting i don't know
about you but for me it's exciting to
look up to the stars and
dream about us humans ex you know uh
colonizing mars colonizing other planets
expanding onto the galaxy into the
universe
that's really exciting uh so
i'm the the possibilities there are
endless
i don't think because the also the
resources are endless
and so i think we get into trouble with
militarization with
wars when the resources are very
constrained
so i think for a while we're not going
to be fighting
the the only wars we'll be fighting in
space are the ones that kind of um
another nation to compete yeah who goes
to the moon first i guess that's those
those are kind of those kinds of things
or maybe for satellites and all those
kinds of communication and
uh maybe in assistance for like cyber
warfare which is also very dangerous but
in terms of
space wars out in space i think
i think everything out in space will be
positive and inspiring it's very hard
but
all good things are hard i think this is
where i've been
i've been talking to a bunch of people
about um extraterrestrial life
i'm really excited by
i don't know it's the other thing um
when i look out to the stars
it's exciting to me i know i think
you've spoken about it being scary
but to me it's exciting that there's
intelligent creatures out there
far beyond perhaps the intelligence of
our own
that uh are just too far away to explore
yet but we might
one day come in contact with them so uh
that that to me is the ultimate
motivator is to meet
other intelligence life forms out there
and connect with them
have you ever meet jacques valley
no but i've been in communication i want
to i hope to talk to him he's amazing
french yeah
i am i know that there are many theories
about yes
you know if there is alien we don't know
right but but
some people think it's from another star
systems
and jacques valley is a like to make a
long story short he has a different
theory thinks it's
perhaps beans that
could be living in a different dimension
than us and the reason why he says that
is
when he makes an experiment when there
is a signings very often
of a ufo let's say i'm i'm the ufo
that you have three guys and one
they they are looking at the ufo very
often
one experiment that you can do and
sometimes
that that is the case you asked your two
friend to walk on the side and there's a
at a point that it's like a corridor you
see the ufo and then
you stop seeing like a corridor and
that's one of the
reason why he's saying that it's perhaps
a dimension
and i found that fascinating you know i
this is what you know to the discussion
of consciousness and all that
it it feels like we might be just
experiencing a very particular slice of
this universe
we might not be understanding what's at
the higher dimensions or
yeah i mean higher dimensions in
whatever form that means you know
there's all these physical theories now
that describe a world with dimensions
that's much higher than the four
dimensions of
the three-dimensional space in one
dimension of time
so whatever the hell is going on in
those other dimensions
it could be something unfortunately
this is the sad part it might be
something we can't even comprehend
with our human brains that the
limitations are just
um i mean we're built we're just
descendants of apes so like it might not
be possible to even understand
is there alien is there another
dimension are they a human from the
future is there
perhaps chinese or another you know what
i mean a group of people that are
working with
a technology far behind but you know
what lex i had a chance to meet
you know because of the sport i'm doing
i met a lot of
people in military and politics
sometimes that i
i asked them every time i met i met one
this week and and
um i i i asked him i say is it true
about the the uf who is there is there
and he says to me like before even
before i ask him i say hey
sorry i have to ask you a question i
wasn't in los angeles
sorry i have to ask you questions oh you
want to ask me about ufo right away you
knew
i said yes you saw it in your eyes say
yeah there is things that flies that we
don't know
but it does it didn't tell me he doesn't
know it they don't know if it's
you know whatever but there's things
apparently that are detected and i know
you met
uh forever you know like flavors
fascinating
crazy it makes me sad that we live in a
different area now that that it's
used to be a subject that was ridiculed
and now
it's so cool that it's you know i'm very
excited to live in
to that that era you know yeah it's
really exciting but still the
governments are
kind of behind the times on that aspect
is
they're not transparent and they don't
communicate well
you know it saddens me to think the
possibility that that
you know like the us government might be
in possession of something
that they don't tell the world about
because they're just scared
it's because they don't know what the
hell it is and they don't want the
chinese to gain the technology or all
those kinds of things
do you think the president of the united
states for example because the president
comes and go every right four or eight
years do you think he would know
all the secret or it would be a guy like
for example
vladimir putin with no much of a
you know i don't think the president
even know like even can
he knows all all the the secrets the u.s
president yeah i don't think so
because he goes they go back and forth
you know every four years
you know they have the terms right so i
you know
i i wasn't sure before but i think i
could trust
the previous united states president of
donald trump
that if he knew
he would probably tweet about it so
perhaps
so i yeah i i think
from from the con you know i've worked
with darpa i work with uh dod
at clearance and i think from the
perspective
if you if you see the world as
fundamentally a dangerous world
where secrets are important to have from
a military perspective
i think it's very unsafe to tell
the president in the united states that
you have this kind of technology so if
you think of the world in that way
i i hate that that's how that world is
viewed because
ultimately i think what's more powerful
than the military secrets
and i hope that actually is what will
happen in the 21st century
because what's more powerful is inspire
people inspire the the young elon musks
of the world to to create cool new
things
if we have technology that we've
come have encountered that we don't
understand that should only be
inspiration
to uh develop that kind of stuff it
shouldn't be seen as military
as a military threat as a secret to hold
on to
i think secrets um i hope
we more and more let go of the idea that
there are secrets that give us advantage
you know like in the tech sector people
are more and more
releasing the software they're making an
open source
like secrets don't make sense they share
the knowledge right share the share the
knowledge like share
like being afraid to share the knowledge
i think i hope is an
old idea it's more yeah when you make it
things more compartmentalized you know
yes well yeah what that's the other
thing is the bureaucracy of government
is like
people only know their own little thing
and they don't spread the information
it doesn't travel well i mean there's a
lot of just inefficiencies that are
it makes me sad it makes me sad because
uh
the the science the engineering that
happens in governments like lockheed
martin
developing the different airplanes that
they use for military applications is
some of the most incredible engineering
ever
and it's secret because they're afraid
to share it
with the russians and the chinese and so
on but
on that topic i do think somebody like
vladimir putin
window probably knows some stuff my god
my god i would i would love to know what
he knows but then again
you never know because even he is you
know people think of him as an
exceptionally powerful person
but he's also just managing a bunch of
tribes
his power is very limited he's trying to
hold together
uh a bunch of greedy power-hungry
mad men that's right okay and he's
trying to establish a balance
he might not know everything so i i hope
this changes
because i think there's nothing more
exciting about
i don't even know if there is a human
that knows
you know what i mean like this idea that
there's some
civilization alien civilization that
that land on the white house and say hi
i come to meet the prison and like why
would they do that
you know what i mean it's kind of absurd
you know
well i i do think that actually i mean
that's one possibility right is
lart you know if an alien civilization
really wanted to contact us
i think everybody would know so i think
what we're
if if there's any kind of interaction
between humans
and aliens i think most likely what
we're interacting with
is the crappy like probe drone
thing that kind of just like like it's
like this
yeah yeah this dumb thing you know we're
not interacting with the aliens i think
just like
just like for us i think humans aren't
when we uh venture out into space
the first thing that's going to mean
aliens is our robots it's not us humans
because we keep sending robots out so
they're going to like
they're going to make decisions about
humans by looking at the robots
i say their famous greys the grays
maybe they're our robots maybe it's all
bs2 you know yeah yeah so
i i don't know i don't know what uh that
interaction actually
would look like if aliens really wanted
to reach out really communicate
and i don't know if we're able to
actually communicate with them that's
one of the sad things we might not be
able to
that we might the aliens might already
be here
and we might just not even know
know how to see them or know how to
communicate with them
there's so much misinformation and
sometimes there is
people that are very credible that that
that made crazy claims you know like
like
you don't know what to believe you know
like paul ellior the the
the minister of defense of canada i've
said like some that there is many alien
race that ever
that that's what he says research it and
then
that that scientists from i think israel
recently have said something about trump
he was keeping secret or
medvedev you're from russia they have
been caught in there like
during a break in between interviews to
talks about like oh it's like men in
blacks over to speak i don't know
he didn't look like he was joking but i
don't know if he didn't know about this
yeah you can check on youtube it'd say
it's it's it's it went
viral yeah there's a lot of things like
that sometime like
or or bob lazar i'm like imagine if it's
true man yeah you might imagine if we if
we're like
a fish in the water we live in our own
world and
sometimes there's a fisherman that
grabbed the fish
yeah take him out of the water and threw
it back in the water and the fish goes
back to the other fish and say
hey there's someone that that take me
out of the water then i've seen
uh things that i did not like imagine if
it's true like we like
yeah and and one other thing like i
wanted to ask you because
you were consciousness how about dreams
what is a dream
yeah well i i more and more i don't know
if you're paying attention to this
there's now
it's become more acceptable in the
scientific community to do
large-scale studies of psychedelics for
example and there's a lot of connection
between psychedelics and dreams
it's very similar states there's there's
a lot our mind does
when it detaches itself from reality
that it can just explore a lot of
different ideas
it's very possible that dreams is you're
traveling somewhere
and the same thing with psychedelics
you're traveling somewhere
in a different not traveling through
physical space it's the other dimensions
that we're talking about you're
traveling some other
through some other dimension to meet
some other creature people talk with dmt
that they meet some elves i've never
done i i'd like to
i don't know if there's a safe legal way
to do it but
uh they all talk about meeting elves
and they're like creatures like entities
and like who are
who are they what's what is this
is it because they're high or it's
because they're actually meeting
something
and maybe there's no difference i mean
that uh who knows exactly and that takes
us right back to us not being able to
really understand
how our mind works you know i work in
artificial intelligence
it's clear that we understand so little
about intelligence
some basic things about intelligence
just at the
at the very sort of basic uh first
principles
level we don't understand what it means
to to reason to think to
assimilate pieces of knowledge together
from
the from the basics to the complex we
don't understand it we don't understand
how the human mind does it
we don't understand how the human mind
is able to take incredible
waterfall of information and filter
cleanly into just like
clean you only see the things that are
important and are able to
jump together and be able to reason
about the world and
at the same time have moments of like
genius of creativity
like what what is that that also you
know people
writers talk about that that they're you
know they're almost like communicating
with the muse
like where do ideas come from yeah this
is the joe rogan philosophy but but i i
do know that
past civilization were a lot of them
were based on
shamanism and you know what i think it's
sad is
if someone drink alcohol and when he's
drunk he's
going to commit like create like
like murders or something we're going to
blame the person right
we're going to say that's his fault it's
not the fault of alcohol
however if someone does psychedelic or
any
things that is illegal and do something
crazy now we're gonna
put the fault on on psychedelic you know
what i mean
and perhaps the person itself is the
the reason why you know he's been doing
these things you know what i mean
so yeah it's fascinating how like
society
you know like in canada they just
legalized marijuana
oh yeah but before that
before they did it like if you talk for
example to my dad my dad is
against it like because the whole
mentality is like it's drug it's bad at
that but drinking a glass
you know drinking a beer it's fine i
mean what
is you know what i mean what is good
what is bad and
i guess you think chocolate could be bad
as well for your health or i mean i'm
going to the extreme now but
yeah what is good what is bad if you use
it for recreation you use it for an
experience for
to learn about yourself it's like
it said that the line is very tiny you
know there are some countries
that drugs are all legals you know what
i mean and i
i don't know the the the stats but i
would i would be interesting
to know if they have more
crimes there than other countries where
it's more strict i
would that would be interesting to know
about that it's fascinate me
you know yeah and i mean we humans kind
of just come up with the
arbitrary lines of what's good what's
bad that applies with drugs that applies
with anything
uh that applies with animals for example
we talked about carnivore diet
maybe the time we live and now will be
remembered for
the cruelty to animals for example
and i believe this the 21st century will
be remembered
for our cruelty to robots
that uh eventually there will be a
civil rights movement for robots where
the the ones who
uh choose to be conscious the ones who
have consciousness will
say we deserve rights too
we deserve to be treated with respect
too
how about the people we put in jail
people put in jail i mean if i think in
the future we'll look back
and we'll think of ourselves being
stupid to
you know to put people in jail instead
of you know like
trying to fix the problem in in in
at the base you know of course now we're
or i guess it's our endurance that
made it in a way that we cannot sort
sometimes understand what makes uh
sometimes a psychopath a psychopath or a
murder or murderer
but you know if we can pinpoint the
problem and
take care of it before you know what i
mean or
made it in the way that we can
reestablish that person in
the society you know who knows you know
what was their future is
old it's interesting we live in an
interesting time
you mentioned your father what have you
learned from your dad
you mentioned he was an important part
of your childhood my dad is
amazing i grew up we didn't have a lot
of money but it doesn't mean if
i'm born in a nice country that always
nice thing happen
you know my dad for me is a big role
model
because i see him through to my life
facing a lot of adversity you know he um
he stopped drinking when i was a
teenager he was an alcoholic
and i seen him struggle through that
you know and it was very very hard and
um
i've seen him work
like crazy hours like
come leave in the morning come home at
night burned out because of work
through almost all his life to the point
that it became
a slave of the system yes it became a
habit and a normal
way of living and it made me realize
that i've learned a lot through my
father
he taught me perseverance hard work you
know
when you face adversity you know to
never give up until you achieve it
but also he it taught me a lesson that
in a way that i don't want to be like
him even if he is happy
it's because i realize i don't think he
knows anything else
like he works through all his life
and i don't want to live to work i want
to work for it for
you know what i mean i want to decide
when i work you know i feel like like he
he lived to work instead of working for
a living
and perhaps it's because he did not have
choice
he he was the older of his family they
had they were nine kid
his dad my grandfather died when he was
young so he had to become
the father of the family and and work
to put money on the table so perhaps
that what
made him that way and he became like
like a habit for him my dad taught me uh
when i was at school i was bullied at
school he's the first one to initiate me
to a martial art
he taught me kyrati my dad my dad was a
black belt in kyokushin karate as well
very nice but because he was working too
much he didn't have time to teach me
and i needed self defense in order to
defend myself
i have a winning a great carrier and
mixed martial art but in the
in the schoolyard that's so good my
mixed record my my record is not very
good
when you're a kid and you're about
seven eight years old and you're facing
bullied
bullies that are
two to three years older than than
yourself
it's not the same thing than when you're
25 and the guy is 28 so there is a big
discrepancy in terms of maturity
so my dad taught me introduced me to
karate
danny i didn't he didn't have time to
teach me then he put me
in a school with an a teacher that said
it was
jean kutzer and i grew up with a lot of
anger
and uh there were two person that was
afraid growing up
it was my dad my dad was very severe
very strict with me
and i'm glad he was because i i could
have become very bad
i could have become chosen on a
different path
people see me as a nice guy and i'm
gonna i am a nice guy i try to be a good
role model
but i could easily have turned
towards our around there there's
darkness somewhere in there
yes they are a lot and a lot of my
friends have chosen
that pat and unfortunately you know they
they
they are they they are they are not with
me today
even if i'm from canada and canada seems
like the nicest
country in the world like i said it's
even if you live in the nice country not
always nice thing it depend
of the situation but that's what my dad
taught me
you know and he gave me that
to to because i i'm very good at
learning
by observing people and by observing him
i i see
the the struggle he had with alcoholism
and what he did the the
the pain sometimes that even flick to to
to us
to my family but how he
turned he did that 180 degree
and i really admire that and i know it
was uh
very very hard for him and he did it you
know and for me uh
that's a great role model for me so
with your dad being an engine of
basically hard work
and you finding a balance of being able
to work your ass off
but also to be able to enjoy a piece of
chocolate
what is the perfect day in the life of
georgetown pierre look like so like
if you were to go through a day that's
very productive but also want to
make you sit back and enjoy and say that
was a good day
what's that look like what are we
talking about when do you wake up what
do you eat
what do you do it changed over the years
when i was younger i have a good day it
was like a good training session or you
know achieving
good thing in my training you know and
that's why i was very good at it because
when i i was obsessed you know i think
to be
good at something you need to become
obsessed and to me
performing in my training was everything
you know like
when i had a bad training session i
didn't tell my training partner
i was acting like a like because of the
my ego i didn't
you know i didn't tell nobody i was like
hey then i go in the locker room
like man then then i'm playing the the
the the training in my mind you know i'm
saying okay i should have done this and
i've done and
it hunt me it hunt me man it's a
training and it hunt me
until the next running session on when i
can redeem myself
that's how it is when we used to
train in all together back in a day
in canada we had david luizo
we had patrick we had uh
dennis kang uh steven
jonathan there was all like the the best
guy in canada
that were training with each other
before we were
training in different gyms but once a
week
i made it in a way that i contact
everybody that we all join for us
and we exchange ideas and we train with
each other
so a friendly i would say friendly
competition it was not
malicious but it was hard training you
know like not our goal is was to improve
you know but it wasn't
very competitive and when
that day you used to get out of the
training session with a bad performance
for me
he used to hunt me until the following
week
when i could give it back and and
perform better
with the guy that i had the most trouble
with that's how it was
and that's how you get better you know
but but
it was not a training where it it it we
were trying to do malicious thing to one
another you know what i mean
you need to be playful but playful but
competitive
that when i had a good training session
because aspiring was on a friday
i had the best weekend and what i was
going out with my friend drinking and
partying and have fun
that was that was my my
my my ideal day back in the day
today is strange you know my my my life
has changed
you know like um i
i am not the same person i used to be
when i went on my knees and begged the
ufc for a title shot
you know what i mean i am uh i'm wealthy
i'm healthy most importantly that's the
most important thing
and as man i'm going to tell you the
truth as good as my career was
man my private life man is a million
times better man i i and and people ask
me sometime they
always wonder they they try to ask me
and it's normal it's a lot of people is
curious and they're the reporter
and in the sport of mixed martial art
we say we play basketball we play soccer
but you don't play fighting
so when you expose your private life
we've seen that happen in the fight week
sometime conor mcgregor and khabib
your competitor knows that he cannot get
to use what he will do he will try to
get to someone that you
love so may i never expose
my my private life i never post
instagram
of my family of my stuff that's the
reason why
because i mean i'm in a business of
fighting
and people know that they cannot get to
me
and i believe because i was bullied when
i was young
i didn't realize that when i was young
but it helps
me deal with the mental warfare that i
need
that i had to face later on in my life
in mixed martial art because it's a very
egotistic sport
and there's a lot of a lot and a lot of
intimidation and i was used to i've been
used to this thing when i was young so
it does not get to me
however the good way to get to me
go go go go try to get to someone i i
love
now man i'm gonna go crazy you know what
i mean
and i'm aware of that so in order to
protect myself
i always because i'm aware i'm a public
person
so i try to always keep my surrounding
like in a private
yeah one of the ways that like uh your
your friend of mine
joe rogan has been an inspiration that
he he's got like
an incredible family and he for the most
part is starting to change recently
actually it's kind of interesting but
for the most part throughout his life he
kept it
pretty secret doesn't talk about it and
he's common he's a comedian comedians
talk about everything he doesn't really
talk about it
and there's something to that it like
preserves the magic of this
the silence of the private life and i
think it can affect the
the development of the kid if
the kid grew up being oh he's the son of
that guy instead of being his own person
you know what i mean
so so for me it's very important like
my parents are older it's fine but it
taught me a big lesson
when i'm with my friend at the dinner or
anything i talk with
person always share a thing but when i'm
talking i'm aware of
of the audience who i'm in front yeah
and i mean but oftentimes those people
are just incredible
it kind of makes me sad that uh
you know there's a lot of people that
love you right and they're a lot of
really incredible people
and you'll never get to really know
their story that's right i mean i don't
know for me it makes me sad
you see them like at airports and stuff
people will tell me they listen to this
podcast or something like that
and they're i could tell they're
incredible people and it makes me it's
like a little goodbye
of of a possible friend i don't know it
makes me sad it's right
it makes me it's lonely it's almost like
celebrity
is a lonely thing so the higher the
celebrity the more lonely you become
in some kind of way but of course you
have that little gem of a private life
where you can personally i believe every
relationship i i
like i don't like to use this term but
it's always
a give and take relationship you know
like you can gain something and the
person like it
it could be something like not material
is materialistic like something oh he's
a good
confidant like you someone that they can
give me good advice or or
it's a word i would say like extensional
like if a pilot as a co-pilot
is the co-pilot is extend as a
extensional relationship with him you
know so he knows if he gets sick or he
faint
he's there to make sure you know he is
there to help
and i think in every relation it's about
compatibility but it's about
extensionality
right in a way that if that person is
extensional and sometimes we talk about
about
love you know like sometimes i think is
is it
is it a bs word or not because i myself
sometimes look at
i look at myself in the mirror and when
i do s
stupid thing sometimes i love myself a
lot and sometimes i don't
you know what i mean because i'm angry
at myself i've done
stupid thing so that means sometimes you
could
love could be fluctuating you know what
i mean how about in relationships
sometimes you
people they say oh they love each other
but then when they divorce they go
oh i want the house and the dog and the
kids stay with me and
you know what i mean if you love if by
definition if you really love
someone and let's say you're an old man
and you love a woman and she decided to
leave you for a younger man if you
really love her
you're gonna help her pack and leave but
in our society sometimes
we want to hone something to me
love includes the missing somebody
losing somebody the anger at somebody
it's all the passion feelings towards
somebody
that's all love okay i you know it's all
part of the thing it's the ups and downs
it's uh the sad thing is when the
feelings
towards the person the ups and downs go
away they're forgetting
yeah that's that's the opposite of love
so the opposite of love isn't
hate the to me the opposite of love is
forgetting
and and that's that's a much bigger
that's like the depth of human
connection that's
how i see love so sometimes i try to
stay positive and
i've been asked how i try to because i
have the image of
someone who's positive but i go to my
own demon as well sometime
however we talk about love
when i was young
you know like like i didn't love
who i was at first that's how i love i
learned to kind of
love myself like i didn't and then when
i was going
to to bullying i was i believe i was
bullied because i didn't love
myself i i because i project a very bad
image
of what i think of myself i was
a kid that lacked a lot of confidence i
was looking down when i was walking
i shrugged my shoulder when someone was
talking to me i was avoiding
eye contact so i was a very easy target
for the bullies and i think
bullies are like in predatory animal in
nature
they will hunt the the easier prey they
would don't they don't go the lion don't
go
for the the alpha bull they go for the
one who's
old or who's sick the weakest one and
bullies are the same in society i
believe
and i didn't like to be bullied of
course but i didn't like the
the person that i was but i found out
through martial art
the respect and
my my coach was extraordinary to me he
taught me discipline and self
strength self strength and i found out
that
i needed to in order to love myself i
needed to change myself
because i didn't when i looked at my son
in the mirror i didn't like what i
saw so i decided to become
like someone that i would love so
i tried to look people straight up
and and trying to showcase
a more confident image that i
had and it was hard in the beginning
because i didn't really believe in it
but i
i faked it until kind of i make it
so when i was walking at school
more and more i was learning how to
become more confident and i was
like taking charge when the teacher was
asking questions i was
at first i was never answering was like
this waiting always to be the last
then i was hey i i i know what the
answer this is the answer
i got out of my comfort zone so to speak
and i wish i would tell you that i got
out of bullying
because a hollywood story i use martial
art to beat up all the bullies
but it's not how it happened to me it
happened because i
changed myself from the inside out
and i learned how to
because i didn't love myself in the
beginning i learned
how to become like someone that i love
and even now like i'm by no mean
perfect i do a lot of stupid thing
but i learn as a person and even i do
have something stupid i'm like
shoot i did something stupid i at least
i can apologize to the person if i
realize and then
i know that i'm not the person i was in
the past
i'm the person that i am right now so i
can learn
and become that image of the person that
i love so
in in a way the reason i'm trying to be
positive and i and i
am able to stay positive sometime in
life is because i'm always
trying to be like that person
that i love yeah and i think if you
don't look yourself in the mirror and
don't
love yourself or don't see any positive
future for yourself
how can you change your environment if
you cannot change yourself
you know what i mean you would never be
happy if you're not happy
when you look at yourself in the mirror
so change yourself first then change
your
you know it's not the environment you're
gonna change for yourself it's you have
to go from the inside out
you know this this i learned to martial
art i have a
i had a coach who was incredible used to
drill these ideas in my head and
and give me confidence you know like
like this telling me all these
these beautiful things about myself and
how i
he's dead now unfortunately peace peace
to him but uh
he was incredible incredible he was very
very strict i was afraid of him i was
afraid of my dad and afraid of him
he couldn't teach nowadays like he used
to teach me because he would be in
probably in jail you know but i'm glad
he did it because for that time being
that's what i needed it and i would
never have had that the career
i had in mixed martial art without this
because i would i would never have got
out of my comfort zone would have been
impossible
and in order to improve in life you need
to get out of your comfort zone
it's hard it's very hard to do and and
strive to be the person that you can
love
i i does that's that's beautifully put
george if you were to give advice to a
young person today about life
what would you tell him
if he takes
life with the same mentality
that i do if he has the same
taste of things that i have
i would tell him you know for for
for sport for life in general i would
say
if you will have a dream
you know like
make everything in your power and work
very hard you know never take no for an
answer and go through hell
in order to achieve it
don't work hard only but work
smart that's i think the problems with a
lot of
people they work hard they can work hard
they burn themselves they don't work
smart
whether it is in in science and business
they make bad choices or they are badly
informed
in sport how many guys i've seen ruin
their career in the gyms
they they spar so hard they they ruined
themselves in the gyms they leave their
career in the gyms
what i would say to for example because
my field of expertise and
it's in sport of mixed martial art
i would say to you
young kid make your training
playful you know when you get ready for
for competition you need to trying to
recreate those
elements that makes you go outside of
your comfort zone
but in every days life in general
make your training playful don't makes
it like a
hardcore competition about who's who's
winning who's losing make make it
playful
so it will increase
because your know you will not be afraid
of
getting hurt or losing
you will be tent to trying more things
and be you it will make you become more
creative creative
you know that brings up another question
about learning
so you you value knowledge and you're
exceptional at basically being very good
at learning
and figuring stuff out new things or
going deeper on the things you already
know
so what advice would you have for how to
learn
effectively how you know you say work
smart
how do you figure this game out i
believe
the best way to learn is learning from
other people's mistake
[Laughter]
however i'm not perfect and i've learned
from my mistakes as well and sometimes
i've i it took it took me a few mistakes
to learn the same thing but
especially in the sport of mixed martial
art because we're talking about
the the failure could have very serious
uh outcome on someone's life
and well-being so it's crucial
to trying to learn from other people's
mistakes do you study others
do every every fight i'm studying my
opponent and i've studied myself
as well to know what
how my strength mix versus
my opponent weaknesses and how can i
make the fight go in a way that
i'm taking my opponent outside of his
comfort zone
very often people are good at studying
their opponent but they're not good at
looking at themselves in the mirror and
knowing what they should do in order to
to maximize their their odds of success
right
that's why i always thought for me
it was important to not be the best at
one thing
but be very good at everything
that's why i always seek advice
advices from the best in every
discipline
like i wrestle with the best wrestler i
i could be with i box with the best
boxers i
i practice karate with the best karate
fighters
uh same thing in jiu-jitsu i trained jiu
jitsu with the best
best jiu-jitsu guys however when i mix
everything and mix martial art
if i if i'm because i'm very confident
in every areas
so when i'm fighting someone i'm very
good at
and that the identifying where is the
less competent
and i know for a fact that because i'm
competent everywhere i can
if i can bring the fight where he's
outside of his comfort zone
it increased my odds of winning there is
no certainty
it's all about odds i believe because
there is always
x factor that you do not control yeah
it's fascinating to see you actually
because you've
been a student of movement uh
you've been exploring all kinds i mean
gymnastics all that kind of stuff there
there's something reminiscent to um
like uh conor mcgregor is one other
martial artist that's kind of explored
movement
been a scholar of movement um at least
from my perspective it's very sort of
bruce lee like
it's almost making a study of the human
body
and all the possible things you can do
is there a philosophy behind that that
you have
you talk about bruce lee man
he changes my my life too he was ahead
of his time
yeah incredible a lot of people talked
to me and asked me hey is brucy
would have been able to fight in ufc i
look i don't think so you know i don't
know
i think he was a you know he was a
martial artist he could have defended
himself but
to say that he could have compete in
amongst the elite
of the elite fighter perhaps in his time
but if for sure if you put him in ufc
right now
you know the sport hasn't improved
incredibly
since then but in terms of
philosophy yeah bruce was amazing like
one thing that
just to prove that he was ahead of his
time he was talking about using your
longest weapon against your opponent
nearest point and we see that that that
kick that
um it it got popular popularized by jon
jones you know the
the sidekick to the time it's longest
weapon against your nearest point in
boxing is the jab
but in mma when you can use it all your
weapon
that's the kick to the tie
and there is i feel there is like kind
of
three dimension in martial art there is
the philosopher like bruce lee
there is the choreography the
choreograph
people like for example you see in
movies the stunned people
they're incredible like or the one that
does like forms and karate like
jumping spin kick bad kick like
acrobatic stuff
mixed martial art they are unbelievable
and there's also the the
the one that compete in in fighting like
that's what i do that i
personally specialize in well you also
do the philosophy
i do a little bit of philosophy but
that's you know consequences
we are all i guess we are all ever like
we all practice the three dimension
because martial art is
i would say it's it whether you want it
or not you have to touch these three
dimensions
but you will specialize in one i
specialize to my life in
fighting like the real thing in terms of
fighting competition
and of course if you do martial art
you'll be able to defend yourself
because
it's a self-defense however you might
not be able to fight
as an elite and the most prestigious
organization
and you might not be able to perform the
stunt that
for example the stuntmen have done in in
the
the syriza was playing in the falcon and
winter soldier
these guys are incredible they're like
real life superhero
things they do it's to me like it's
it's fascinating it's amazing and also
bruce lee the philosophy
how many hours he he
took like thinking about this stuff you
know i'm sure he did not just came out
of
out of nowhere you know like he was
thinking like that's mean he
slept on on this he
how many hours it's just unbelievable
he's like water my friend
exactly how many times has he thought
about water going to bed
yeah before he said that uh well let me
ask a very important fundamental
question about martial arts we're both
wearing
a suit and tie uh joe rogan thinks that
wearing a tie is a huge disadvantage
is it a clip-on or is it an actual tie
are you controlled by another one
so do you agree or disagree with joe
rogan that wearing a tie
is a is a martial art
significant disadvantage in terms of
combat in a combat scenario
in a fight i think it would be a
dissonant disadvantage
yes okay but i i work as a as a security
bouncer
in nightclubs and event when i was 18
years old
yes and um
sometime i had to work in certain event
that i was in suit and tie
i never had to use
my force to take someone out when i
wasn't super untie
but if i would have had to before going
to the table to
physically take that out i would have
removed my tie
and i would have removed my vest for
sure and i would have called back
up for sure and i would have probably
used the element of surprise to
be first on the guy yes uh
when you're in a bar same thing you call
back up first
and and and you make sure you ask the
way the waitress before to clean the
table
before you go yeah and when you go
you have to use the element of surprise
yeah because fighting
fighting that makes martial and fighting
in the street it's two different things
and yes i'm a mix i'm a mixed martial
art competitor that's what i've done all
my life but i had a lot of street fight
in my life
a lot when i wasn't what's the
difference what's like the oh my god
it's
a huge difference there is guys that
if i would have a choice you know to
fight
like for example certain guys and you
have seen a street fight and fight
like other guys that are not in ufc i
would maybe sometimes
pick guys that are not in ufc not
necessarily because in in
in a street fight there's no referee
that says go it's the element of
surprise and when you're a nice guy
you're not the aggressor
you always have the element of surprise
that's what it taught me oh interesting
yes because if aggression in your second
person will not come punch you without
warning it needs
to it needs to trigger some it's
something need to be triggered
before so if someone comes because it's
looking for trouble
there's a sign that is looking for
trouble so i was
just talking with fast food on this
weekend about it and i saw that
every every martial art yeah comes from
like some martial arts are from
exclusive week for competition yes
like sport karate uh like certain
martial art
but traditional martial art are for the
street
are for self defense and i start my
background in kyokushin karate so it's
for and and i did japanese jiu jitsu so
my background before i even start
training for mixed martial art my
background is in self defense
and it's very important to understand
that in a street fight
the element of surprise is everything
and there are no rules you can go for
the eyes the next the the
surprises everything total ball game you
know what i mean you have the
the chair the beard there's so much more
thing
going on so the idea of because
you are a ufc fighter you think you're
invincible this is
bs anybody can come like if if a big guy
who punched very hard
most people don't know how to punch by
the way they don't know how to make a
fist and throw it in a forward direction
but if
someone knows how to do it i don't care
who you are if you could be
francis and genu someone come behind
your head and
whang or there's an argument and you get
surprised by a punch
you can beat you up and lose a fight
that doesn't matter
yeah the element of surprise is
everything so you were saying remove
all the sources of the elements the
surprise all the clear the bar
remove the tie i still disagree with you
about the tablet and
just for your information if someone
comes
looking for trouble and you see me do
this
and and going sideways yeah that's my
position
that i'm i'm thinking there you go maybe
something will happen and i'm
about that's
see to flip the table on you then
wearing a tie
is communicating the nice guy image so
it
actually gives you the freedom for more
elements of surprise
by wearing the tie if you take it off
that's more
you're limiting your options because
nobody's going to expect the guy in the
tie to do anything
i'm a big believer that sometimes it's
not only
materialism it's what you project
that's true like i had troubles in a bar
and i was able to deflect
the guy was looking for trouble talking
to me and i was able to deflect his
whole aggressivity by saying like
hey man that's a nice shirt where did
you get it like saying like something
was
stupid like this then it it kind of
break
break the momentum and he you know but
the guy was looking for trouble
i don't want to fight you i don't want
to fight you but i'm not going to wait
until you pull you make the first move
because the first
the minute you you touch me you push me
or you you touch me you declare war and
the war is unleashed my friend and i'm
i'm taking you out of order
with the necessary force of course you
know i mean that's
the thing with martial art if you use
the necessary force to take out a
problem
it's okay but if you you know you you
take advantage of it that's when it's
not all right because it's a weapon
so if someone comes up to me that's my
position and
now i'm i'm assessing the situation you
know
that's that's how they teach in self
defense here never put your hands down
i wasn't there because i'm brown or boom
like like what
this is this is very important and you
never
you always your center line on the side
ah yeah like this
if someone knows martial art he will
recognize that pattern
but if you go like if someone talk to
you and you go like this
that's mean you're telling the guy that
you want to fight you don't want to do
that you don't want to oh yeah
um that's that's interesting you know
that's
that's the position because your hands
are here you know whatever you can do
you're here
well also your ear tells the story
it's not everybody that knows that
however it some people
might think that it's my mom grabbed me
by the air and pulled me because i
didn't listen to her you know
a real fight in the stream and a fight
in in mixed martial
is a different ball game what do you
think is the best
martial art to prepare you for street
fighting you know people often kind of
have this discussion of jiu jitsu maybe
boxing maybe wrestling
do you think when you talk about a young
person studying martial arts to prepare
themselves
for um a street fight it's often
much different than a mixed martial art
fight and
i know there's a lot of bs in the world
of martial art like self defense stuff
that
like but i believe
self defense is is very important in a
way to understand
the the situation to understand those
those situations that might accurate how
to deal with it
because not necessarily the the
we talk about the technicality we talk
about the tacticality the tactics
you know like when i'm talking to you
about the element of surprise it's
important this is not technique a
technique is a punch or or
techniques that i physically will use to
enable
my my my opponent my my aggressor
tactic is the tactic i'm telling you
about is in a street fight
if someone is looking for trouble and i
feel the heat rising as the conversation
goes that's the position i'm gonna take
and
i have to be first i cannot let him
go first so i have to strike first or do
something this is the first thing
that generally and i have to to
to agree on um
after that of course there is the the
knowledge if you're a professional
fighter
you have a huge advantage once the fight
is started the war is declared now it's
everything goes but generally speaking
the person that will
intervene physically that will have the
first blower the first
you know the first punch will
have a huge this use advantage it's like
doing a 100 meter raise and having a
head start
you know and and that you don't you
can't prepare for with any martial arts
yeah and if i'm a smart guy
i know how to fight if a guy like an
heavyweight champion comes to me or
like like like a you know i know i know
what to do to this this ebola like boom
or
hair and or the neck you know like and
if you
if you blind them what is it going to do
you know what i mean so so
or a bottle you know what i mean so so
the element of surprise
is it's everything so that's why it's
always
always good to be the nice guy and not
looking for trouble because if you're
not looking for trouble
you have the head start you have the
option of having a head start
so what you're saying is being a nice
guy is the is the best form of
self-defense
maybe a little humor yeah you know
i have learned that i've learned that
when i was a kid yeah i was about
maybe seven six six years old we used to
to play in montreal there's a lot of
snow we used to play king of the
mountain yeah
that's the first combat lesson that i've
learned in my life
and i managed somehow it was a lot of
kid i managed to get on the top of the
mountain and uh
another guy came come in on top of the
mountain and he was angry that before
i was there before him when you played
king of the
mountain it was a mountain of snow you
don't strike each other we just
wrestle and push and i managed to be
first and when he came
he says to me say okay you wanna you
wanna fight
and i said yeah i don't know what it
means like i wanna fight you wanna
wrestle you say i i say
yes he punched me right in the face
boom and then i and then i fall on on
the bottom of the mountain but
then i when i fall down i remember that
vision in my life because it it it's
it's i will remember that for the rest
of my life
i'm about to stand up and i see the
blood coming out of my nose see the the
snow is red because my nose is bleeding
now i i remember the element of
surprises
everything my first street fight i've
lost
i got i didn't get knocked out but i i
got dropped on the bottom of the
snow mountain and i was like uh he got
me because
i was not expecting my hand i was not
expecting a punch
so from there when i felt the the the
eat
of an in during an argument or something
was not right i always stroke first
i didn't win all my fight because
sometimes there were more than
one guys on on me you know but
i think it's important to not be the
aggressor so you have the element of
surprise
and i always use that in your favor
that's so brilliant
let me uh go from the very practical to
the the most
impractically huge question about the
meaning of life
you said that uh when great depths
of unrelenting sorrow punctuated by
great peaks of joy and liberation
the result is delicious so uh
what do you think is the meaning of this
whole journey that we're on
this life what makes life delicious
to me you know
satisfaction is the end for me
like like i always if i'm satisfied
that's mean i have no nothing to live
for
i'm talking i'm not talking only about
my career about talking about my life
what
what do you want in your life you want
you want kids you want a family
you want to be champion what do you want
in your life you have like a long-term
goal
short-term goal
in mixed martial art i achieved what i
needed to achieve
i'm sad cespar i'm no longer the same
josh schneider than when i was on
begging for a title shot on my knees
i move on for it from it
now i had a chance to go into movies
now that same insane
that same insane drive that i had to be
the champion in the world now i put it
into acting like i'm having a lot of
acting class now and
luckily for me the timing was amazing i
got
i got casper the the falcon and the
winter soldier
was that is on disney plus channel
it's a huge huge project to be part of
for me because it's like
you play basketball you have a chance to
go for the nba right away i was very
lucky
the timing was just too perfect and so
you need to constantly challenging
yourself and having goals to achieve
you know like that keep your brain
activated
i keep working and the proof of that is
that
you see sometimes some old people
like when they retire very often
sometimes you see that they they got
sick and
they die or because they they
it's either because sometimes we think
we we
we certainly make benefits we do
something good for them by
making not work and giving them a break
so in our mind we're like oh it's gonna
be able to relax
but in their mind it's not good because
they're not busy they have nothing to
live for like
like my dad is used to work all the time
and he has always something to do
is retire now i myself now
call him by force to find him some job
hey dad okay
can you come in my house have this thing
to repair i don't know how to do it so
he gives him
it gives him a reason not not to live on
because he has other things to do but
but
what i mean is also in life i think you
always
don't be afraid to aim high don't
don't be afraid to fix your objective
very high
and never be able to reach it be afraid
of reaching your goals essentially i
mean you always have to keep moving it
out you think there's a it's an
interesting question because you've been
acting in some really exciting things do
you think there's a
a dramatic role where it's basically
you know you go full robert de niro and
taxi
uh driver is do you think there'll be a
full length feature film with george st
pierre i liken there's level to this
thing
i'm aware that i have to restart as a
white belt
and for some people it could be
discouraging but for me man it's great i
love it
i freaking love it i embrace it because
everybody told me like
i would never be able to do it and it's
fine but
the and also the outcome of a failure
in the sport of mixed martial art is
much more
serious than the outcome of a failure
for a movie for example
for for if you zig when you shoot zag in
a fight you get knocked out if you zig
when you shoot zagging on set
oh cut we'll do it again and
i know that i will be most likely
be choosing for action martial art
roles because that's my background there
is this new trend in hollywood now when
they want someone to play
an italian guy they're going gonna
choose a real italian person
when they want someone to play a russian
guy they're gonna choose someone who has
a real
russian background now they want a real
martial art fighter i've done fighting
all my life i just need to improve my
acting skill
but when i train in acting i get myself
out of my comfort zone i'm not playing a
role of a martial argument i'm playing
like romance
comedy drama so when i go on set and
playing the role of uh
of a badass martial art guy it's it's
easier so
like in training for a fight i always
make my
preparation harder than the actual
task i would love to see where i don't
know if you've seen the wrestler with uh
mickey work
oh yeah those types of films i would
love to uh
i would love to you do something like
that if not now
then in 10 20 years i could see that
that would be amazing
there's levels to the game right yes
it's gradual and i don't
and i'm aware that i i don't want to
take something on my shoulder that i
won't be able to deliver
it's like a fighter wants to go for a
title shot right away could it could
very well break him you know what i'm
and i don't want to do that because i
know
i've done some gigs in the past but i
was not focusing on it because i was
focusing on competing as a martial art
martial artist and competition
in mma but now i take it very seriously
so i cannot
do the same mistake again because i've
done some stuff i've done it for the
money and it was
good it was fun to to to be beat up by
jacob van damme
and everything but but my acting was not
on point you know at that time
so if i ever every time i'm gonna come
back from now on on
on screen you need to be sharp because
you cannot mess it up if you mess it up
it's like a loss on your record you're
not taken seriously
so so that's how i see it and
it's very fun because i i had a chance
to talk to a lot of guys and on top of
all the class that i'm having
like a few days ago i was with danny
trujo
and i i always seek the advice of actors
when i
when i see some of them that because i
really admire how they do you know how
they project their emotion and i asked
him danny true i said
i said to him he is an amazing guy by
the way very nice guy
and i asked him i say him how how do you
do to be
because you scared the hell out of me
how do you do
to be so scary like what is your trick
and he tells me he's like george if
you're threatening if you threat someone
and you scream at him i'm gonna kill you
wherever
it's not as scary if you're smiling and
you say
i'm gonna kill you like and he says also
to me that
another advice he gave me is like when
you say this
think about you killing him for real
that how you hate him and how you're
gonna kill him so the
camera will take the emotion out
don't try physically to do that that's
the mistake i used to do before
i used to physically show that i'm
strong and angry and and to be
mean so these are the just an example of
tricks
that i learned sometimes when i met an
actor i always try to learn from
everybody that i met in my life it's a
difficult journey because then you have
to go to some dark places
as a person because you really have to
imagine imagine some dark
things that's fascinating actually i i
think a lot of the actors they have
sometimes problems because of that beca
because now i understand why it's like
if you work on your bicep your by itself
will grow right it's a
it because it it it's that stress that
you put on it
that will make it grow right emotions
are i believe are the same way if you're
used to dig inside of you down deep to
to to to make your negative emotion
depressive emotion comes out if
something
bad in your life happen you will fall
into those emotions much more rapidly
that's
someone who does not that every day you
know what i mean because it will
it's like a muscle memory like if you
program yourself to react a certain way
you will
reach that point very often so that's
why sometimes you see some
some guys they we often blame it on
drugs but i think it's
also because of the acting they are used
to be so
on the hopped up and sometimes they go
to the down deep
so they they they they're they they're
both extreme you know you got to be
psychologically tough and that's life
this is so exciting to see you challenge
yourself in that direction
that's one thing that i'm a little bit
afraid
that happened to me i i i really hope
i'll i'll always
be uh you know like a problem
having a problem to control my emotion
be oh yeah much extreme
i hope it does not happen to me and and
if
i feel that i'm going towards that
i'm going to you know give up on on
my new objective and find something else
to to achieve
but in your personal life you want to be
real with your emotions you don't want
to
it doesn't you know you're just just
like with biceps you don't want biceps
that are too big
you you you are real but you are extreme
really and and that's that that's the
that's what i think something that could
happen to actors sometimes when they go
too much into their emotion like we talk
about like sometimes guys that
that that commit commit suicide perhaps
you know
i don't know it's because i don't know
their real life but it could be
something that they get so much into
their character
i didn't understand it at first because
i never had acting class but after a
while
that you have acting class now you start
to realize that yeah okay you understand
why
some actors get caught up in their
emotion because
that can have an influence on their life
right you're on a fascinating journey
uh george i can't tell you how much it
means to me that you'll be so nice to me
that you'll give me so much respect
just that that tells everything i need
to know about you as a human being with
everything you've accomplished
you waste all your time and you're so
nice
to me just as a fellow human being man i
have
so much respect i'm so honored and the
energy you give me by just
even showing up here i'll carry that
forward for a long time to come george i
love it thank you so much for talking
today now
thank you lex for having me on the show
you know i've been looking to talk to
you for a long time
for me talking to a guy like you it's a
it's a great learning experience because
i always learn
and uh it's life is fascinating to me
and
all the experience that we have and
lives you know it's something that can
make us grow and
this experience for me just you know
make me grow as a
as well you know plus we look pretty
damn sharp today so man
and black my friend thanks george
nice thanks for listening to this
conversation with george st
pierre and thank you to all form
expressvpn
blinkist theragun and the information
check them out in the description to
support this podcast
and now let me leave you with some words
from miyamoto musashi
think lightly of yourself and deeply of
the world
thank you for listening and hope to see
you next time
you