the following is a conversation between
me
and michael malus michael is an author
anarchist and simpleton and i'm proud
to call him my friend he makes me smile
he makes me think and he makes me wonder
why i sound so sleepy all the time
and now enjoy this conversation with
michael malus
in the dupagolova language that i'm
increasingly certain
i'll never quite able to get the hang of
hello comrade let's miss it
so animal farm by george orwell is
one of my favorite books it's an
allegory about
at least i think about the soviet union
and the russian revolution
of 1917 so for people who haven't read
it
it's uh animals overthrow the humans and
then slowly become as bad
or worse than the humans so
comrade if we lived on this farm in the
book animal farm
which animal would you most rather be
would it be the pigs the horses
the donkey benjamin the raven moses the
humans
mr mrs jones the dogs or the sheep
um i'm gonna go with the milton answer
which is better to rule in hell than
serve in heaven right
it's better to rule in health and serve
in heaven yeah so i would have to go
with
the pigs so i guess i'd be a cop um
at the very top so the leader the main
pig napoleon versus like the wallet or
the other
yeah i i would say it's not it's sure
it's an allegory of the russian
revolution but i think
um orwell's point was this is broader
towards most totalitarian dictatorships
i mean
it could very easily be read as an
indictment of mussolini or hitler
or many of these others uh i'm a huge um
george orwell fan one of the things that
i think people on the right
need to appreciate is the courage
of many of these in undisputably
left-wing voices who were the strongest
ones to take on
uh totalitarianism totalitarian
communism and the three i think off top
my head who are all
in my top ten heroes of all time are
emma goldman
albert camus and orwell being the third
you know something that uh
leftists like to throw in the face of
people on the right who constantly
invoke orwell
is that orwell said and i don't have the
exact quote on top of my head but some
of the effect of
every word i have written is in
should be taken as a defense of
democratic socialism against
totalitarianism
so uh people like truman you know was
obviously very hardcore
in many ways anti-communist we like
to parse things out you're going to
laugh
into binary fashions that you know left
good right bad or right good left bad
but historically speaking it does not
fall away into these camps
as easily as people would like and i
think it is important for those of us
it takes a lot more courage to fight
the right from the right or to fight the
left from the left because
in a sense a lot of your countrymen or
your fellow travelers are going to
regard you as a traitor to the cause
so i every chance i get i will sing the
praises of these three
figures among others who not only even
if they hadn't
done what they had done just lived just
amazing lives that all of us can
uh learn from and admire and
regard as somewhat a role model so what
was the nature of their opposition to
totalitarianism is that basically
freedom well the value of freedom let's
go to the three of them
so emma goldman she was an early
anarchist figure you know we'll talk
about her later i'm sure
she got deported from the united states
with her partner in crime alexander
berkman literal crime he tried to
assassinate
uh frick who was andrew carnegie's
main man in the pittsburgh steel mill
strike um she got deported
to the soviet union and they're like
they're like oh you want socialism
because at the time the anarchists were
regarded as socialist
you know go choke on it and she's there
and she was watching in great horror
uh what was going on and she actually
went to lenin's office and she goes this
isn't what we're about the revolution is
about
the individual and free speech and
everyone working together to further
society
and he told her that you know you know
free speech is a bourgeois contrivance
and regardless you can't have these
circumstances in the midst of a
revolution
and when she left the soviet union and
you know she went to britain and at the
time
before the 1917 there was a lot of
discussion among
socialist circles about what would the
revolution look like right
would there be the bakunin anarchist
model would there be the marxist model
obviously the bolsheviks ended up
winning but even then it wasn't obvious
because there was the bolsheviks and the
mensheviks and
what people you know you and i know what
those words mean but
bolsheviks were kind of funny because
boisha means bigger and manchester means
smaller
the mensheviks had the numbers it was
sarcastic that they were called
mensheviks and the bolsheviks were
called bolshah and lenin
you know destroyed all his foes in a
very merciless way obviously
beforehand you know there was the idea
like okay with all these cockamamie
ideas
we have to work together you know we
don't know what's going to look like for
the cause then as soon as he sees power
he's like yeah yeah we're not doing that
kind of pluralism anymore
this is going to be the right approach
so she left the soviet union as did
berkman
she wrote a book that they titled my
disillusionment with russia and i
remember this is one anecdote which i'm
going to
discuss in the forthcoming book where
she goes to britain and the british
were very red at the time they really uh
had something called the fabian society
which was the predecessor to the british
labour party
which were like all right we're going to
get rid of liberalism and have a
socialist
uh kind of nation and she gave talks and
there was this one's time where she gave
a talk and
she started and there was a standing
ovation by the time she was done you
could hear a pin drop
because she dared to look at these
people in the face something they'd be
fighting for all their lives and saying
you know we've been to the future and it
works
and she's like guys this is worse than
the czar uh you know people are under
house arrest you're not allowed to have
you know newspapers are being shut down
if they have heretical views so on and
so forth
and you know she was just even more of a
pariah than she had been previously so
she is you know deserves huge accolades
in that regard
i brought her up and we were talking
about with our conversation with iran
or well i think you don't need me to
explain what he has done and continues
to do
to use fiction to demonstrate uh the
horrors
of a totalitarian state and camus who
might be my all-time
you know great lighthouse so to speak in
terms of being a man of conscience
you know he joined the communist party
and for a lot of people in the states
you hear
oh you joined the communist party so i
need to hear so all you need he was a
communist all you need to know
he joined the communist party because
they were the main ones fighting the
fascists in france and other locations
and he took nazism as did many others of
course very very very seriously he
wasn't some committed communist but this
was just his
mechanism to take on uh you know be part
of the underground in vichy france and
so on and so forth
so he had the quote which is ascribed to
him
which is kind of a misquote howard zinn
is the one who actually said it that
it is a job of thinking people not to be
on the side of the executioners
and he very much felt if you read his uh
speech when he won the nobel prize i
forget
in the 50s where he goes it's basically
the job of writers
to keep civilization from destroying
himself
i don't think i'm ever going to be a man
on the level of camus and what he's
accomplished
but i think that vision of
it is the job of writers to be the
conscience
and to point out uh you know this is the
leftism at its best when
you're giving voice to the voiceless
when you have the machine of the state
crushing and marginalizing people and
they might not be educated literate or
have any power at all
some he's the guy who's like you are
ruining
humans these humans matter and i'm not
going to let you look the other way
and act like you don't know what you're
doing so in this time
whether we look at the time of fascism
or we look at the fictional animal farm
what's the heroic action then so uh
camus joined the communist party there's
a bunch of different heroic actions
some more heroic than others not just
for the
you know heroes the wrong word in terms
of like effectiveness
what's the effective action i guess is
what i want to ask as a writer as a
thinker
somebody with a mind what's the heroic
action
that's a tricky question because a lot
of times in the west heroism
is regardless intertwined with martyrdom
right so it's kind of this idea of like
you have to speak to
you know kemu always talked about just
let justice be done though the heavens
fall
this is a common um kind of motto among
people with conscience
and that you have to do the right thing
even the consequences might not be what
you like
and i think that is a good loose
definition of heroism
so if you me i'll give you one example
of heroism this was on twitter and i
really feel bad that i don't remember
the guy's name
uh this was the line to auschwitz i
believe it was
and you know there's the nazi guards
keeping everyone along
and uh if you were a certain i think if
you were under 12 they killed you or
some there was some age limit where
some kids were killed or some were not
there were some circumstances
and he asked the mom how old this kid
was and she's like he's 14 and she's
like no he's 12. and she's like no he's
nice 14 she goes
he's 12. and she realized what this nazi
was telling her even in that
circumstance and it ended up saving the
kids life so i think heroism
in this context is defiance
and standing true to values of
liberalism
humanism and venerating the sanctity
of human life i think that uh and
i think it's also important to pick your
battles
uh i don't think if you know he got that
nazi over there gotten a bullhorn
and said hey this is the rules blah blah
blah blah that's not going to help
anyone do anything so i do think
you know people a lot of times attack me
from my anarchist views it's like oh
you know would you call the police would
you use the roads would you pay your
income taxes
uh you know i i got an argument with tim
poole because there was that couple i
think it was at missouri or illinois
when they were
had their guns and they were being
arrested and they basically took a plea
deal
and he said you should have fought i go
it's a lot easier to say you should
fight but we don't know what
circumstance someone is under
and what these totalitarian regimes did
very very well as as you know
is if you were a target and they can't
get through to you
that's fine you have a family so you can
sit there
lex and gird your jaw and you can stand
up to all the torture
cool what are we gonna do about your
wife what about your mom one thing
stalin did
he made it a law that kids up to
uh 14 and up could get the death penalty
for certain crimes
so after that the rule was from the nkvd
if you were interrogating someone they
would have death warrants
for the kid's child on the desk visible
so i'm interrogating you asking you
to commit to i'm sorry to admit to some
crime
that you're not committed and those
piece of paper it's you know svetlana
she's got a death warrant you're gonna
admit to any crime you want
so this is something americans this is
even the case right now in north korea
um which i know you had yami park on
it's something i talk about a lot
let's talk about instead of the
hypothetical but this is happening right
now
on earth you can look at the map on
google uh the great leader kim il-sung
the founder of north korea said class
enemies must be exterminated three
generations so north
when people talk about individualism
versus collectivism uh rick santorum
former center says the family is the
basic unit of society
unit north korea takes that seriously
the family
is punished as a unit so if someone does
something wrong three generations have
to
pay the price and you often don't know
who it is
that got you all in trouble there's not
a trial this to western
minds is something almost
incomprehensible it's a lot easier to be
brave
when it's just your skin there's
something when it's when it's
yeah when it's your child your your
loved ones
your every man becomes a coward but also
what bravery is there for me to write an
essay for the guardian to say i don't
vote there's no consequences to me
there's no
possibility of consequences to me this
is the wonderful thing about living
excuse me in a free country
uh it would take a lot of courage to be
in the soviet union and say i'm not
going to vote
and what would that courage accomplish
very little so i think heroism in the
sense of kind of the suicidal stuff and
taking a stance with no consequences is
a bit overrated
there is some aspect like the way i
think about heroism
is something like you said about the
soldier
which is quietly privately in your own
life
live the virtues that you want the rest
of the world to live by
yes so like without like writing about
it
is um it's not as heroic as living it
quietly
i'll give you a great example of this i
sometimes give talks on networking and i
tell the kids
if you know someone's in town and it's
their birthday with nothing to do take
them out
and i say i do this for selfish reasons
and everyone laughs
and i go think about it this way the guy
who takes people out for their birthday
is awesome that could be you like you
have that capacity
to be that person and you're making that
day feel special they're going to
remember for a long time
what's the cost dinner 30 bucks 25 bucks
so they're it's it's very disturbing to
me
how often people have opportunities
to slightly move the needle and make
things a bit better
at almost no cost and they just
literally don't think in those terms
and one of the things camus talked about
you know he's
often described as a existentialist
which he did not like that term he
regard himself as an absurdist
is the idea that we're basically blank
canvases and this isn't something that
is dangerous this is enormous
opportunity
and you have the ability to become the
kind of man or woman
that you admire and want to be you don't
have to be you know
i don't know george washington or one of
these great heroes of all time
but everyone out there has the capacity
capacity excuse me
to be a hero to their kids or to be a
hero to maybe some
there's there's nursing homes and
there's old people who are lonely
i think that you take in a dog that's on
its last legs
uh these are little things terry shepard
does that a lot out of garden was a hero
um these are not terry sheppard on
blanken's name
these are things that people do um that
aren't heroic in the sense of superman
but that i find admirable extremely and
i think are very underrated because
these people aren't championed
is this some kind of weird
passive-aggressive and direct way
for you to tell me that i should take
you off for your birthday on monday
is that why you gave that whole speech
that's that wasn't it at all
that was a joke michael no it was a
failed joke
nevertheless there was no punch line
without failure we would not have
triumph
can we stick on the camus absurdism
versus existentialism
sure what do you think is the difference
in your ideas about uh anarchism
too it seems like those are
somehow intricately connected because uh
existentialism is connected to freedom
and freedom is connected to anarchism
sure but i mean
sartre was a defender of the soviet
union
uh he said explicitly about things like
gulags like even if it's true we
shouldn't talk about it
um so he it's what people don't
appreciate is how
uh human beings can have contradictory
ideas in their minds at the same time
so one would think okay someone's a
democrat they think abc therefore they
think def
people that have all sorts of
contradictions and it's not at all clear
and they'll
have a clean conscience because the
human mind is very sophisticated um
and is capable of doing this so sartre
you know was
you would think he's this radical
individualist you know this sense of
ultimate freedom
but he's defending the soviet union
camus on the other hand
would probably be was very much like a
social democrat
he didn't really talk about what
politics should be
so much as it shouldn't be his essay
reflections on the guillotine
is one of the great masterpieces of all
time an attack on the death penalty
not in terms of no one's evil or it's
wrong to kill murderers but in terms of
what does it do for a society if you
have someone who set
takes a person and locks them in a room
and says
you know in two years i'm going to
murder you and you lock them for that
this is not someone we regard as moral
regardless as someone who's
a complete monster but that's what the
state does you know
on with the death penalty and he
challenges us to think
is this the kind of people we want to be
do
and again he's saying i'm not saying
killing a murderer is wrong i'm not
saying evil is wrong his entire career
was dedicated to fighting the concept of
evil
but are we the kind of people who want
to be doing these things that in any
other context we regard as torture
or depraved so i i'm much more of a
camus person
than a star person he was probably
against war in that same way so i don't
i have to
uh admit i don't know much about the
political side of kamu
well i don't think his political side is
that interesting or relevant what i find
so interrupted what i find fascinating
about camus and what i think about on a
daily basis from him
is his insistence that you have to live
a life based on conscience
that you have to be accountable to
yourself when you put your pill your
head on the pill
at the end of the day and ask yourself
did i live
a righteous life with integrity true to
my values
did i uh not needlessly cause harm to
innocent people
um you know that kind of mindset did i
if someone is weak
am i using that as an opportunity to
exploit them or to harm them
or do i feel a bit of sympathy or
empathy for this person
because maybe they didn't have
circumstances that were you know as
beneficial as other people had well how
does that fit absurdism
where everything is absurd nothing has
meaning
uh you know it really borders on
nihilism so he
his he regards not his his philosophy
explicitly said is a response to
nihilism and
a attack on nihilism he you know he
regards cynicism as like
the worst value people can have and i
agree with him
one hundred percent a lot of times
people call me cynical online
and i push back very very hard because
to be a si
you know i had this quote and then you
write where i said i'd rather be naive
than a cynic
because a cynic is a hopeless man who
projects his hopelessness to the world
at large
uh camus this is the metaphor i use and
i find it very inspirational
i thought it was in his work but i guess
i thought if it described it to him
there's two types of people you imagine
you go to a mountainside
and you see a blank canvas
on an easel standing in front this
mountainside
one people be like why is this blank
canvas here
you know what what was this what's going
on here uh and just be confused
whereas the other type of person will be
like there's a blank canvas here in this
beautiful countryside
what a great opportunity i can paint
this river
i could paint that bird i could paint my
friends or myself
in the background infinite choices and
this is a gift that i have been given
and i think that also ties very heavily
into what i was i went to yeshiva as a
kid which is jewish school
what we were taught in incessantly uh
how to look at life
is this beautiful gift that god has
given you
and that god wants you to be happy he
wants you to live
to the fullest in a moral way i remember
the first time i went into a church
and they were asking questions about the
jewish concept the afterlife they
weren't familiar with jewish thought
and it took me a second because i didn't
really have answers and then i
remembered what we were taught which is
let's suppose you're at this banquet
with the best chef on earth
and the table's so heavy because you've
got steaks and you've got chicken and
you've got sushi
and the wine's flowing and you've got
your dr pepper and
mr and mr pibb and the store brand
everything you want
and you're looking around at this
amazing bounty right
and then you turn to this best chef on
earth and you're like oh so what's for
dessert
i mean the offensiveness of that is just
so
you know insane like you have this eat
the meal like i promise you
if i could deliver this meal the
dessert's gonna be okay
so this focus on the afterlife when
we've been given this amazing gift
uh you know on this earth is is a very
kind of different mindset from both
the jewish tradition as i've been taught
and the kamu mindset
obviously kamu is an atheist didn't
believe in an afterlife but this concept
that life
is is meaningless but that means
you have that opportunity to find value
to seek for truth to seek for happiness
and kamu has this quote
it's ascribed to him it's like a meme
i've never found the source so maybe he
doesn't really say it
but he says maybe it's not about happy
endings maybe it's about the journey
and i think when you have that mindset
and as you and i i think you and i both
found this
because neither of us when we were kids
thought we'd be doing this
right but now that we are really
fortunate
definitely this yeah and definitely that
yeah but now that we're fortunate enough
to do this and that we're blessed enough
that there's people who find this of
value and interest
and we could pay the rent doing this
there's not a day that goes by
where i don't think you and i or think
this is pretty absurd
yeah but it's also pretty wonderful and
as a consequence of us
thriving it also shows other people that
happiness is possible
on this earth and i think cynicism is
the lie
it's not just the worldview it's a lie
that happiness is not
possible in this earth or it's only
happy possible
if you sell your soul and you're like a
bad person you screw
other people over i reject that in every
aspect
you know as you said my birthday's
coming up i've been feeling
um just a lot of really great things
have been happening very very recently
so it affects me very heavily
emotionally especially when i see
the response it gives to uh
like the kids right so it's one thing to
say this is what i'm for
but when you can provide proof of
concept that what you've been advocating
does result in positive responses i got
a message from this kid
who had tried to kill himself a year ago
okay and then he
was like look i found your work i found
some other stuff and
now i realize i'm going to make
something of myself i was born in a meth
house
you know whatever 19 20 years old i
should be in the garbage
but i'm gonna try to be a stand-up
because i have opportunity on this earth
even if he fails as a stand-up you know
he's still
such whatever he does washing dishes
there's no shame in that
he is it so bad to have a crappy job
and a girlfriend who you don't really
like but as compared to the alternative
of like i'm going to kill myself this is
heaven
well i think there's beauty to be
discovered in
all of it and all of those experiences
yes so
but at the same time so
i often think about i just recently
reread the idiot by destiusky
i often feel like the idiot that's why
when i say i'm an idiot
i often think about prince mishkin that
kind of idiot which the world sees you
as naive
i don't think he's naive i don't think
i'm naive but i tend to
see the good in people and the good in
every moment
and the world often
is cynical and in fact especially in
what we do
often the intellectual is supposed to be
cynical
it's i this is very much an urban uh
elite educated mindset where if you
write a book about someone who's let's
suppose a drug addict or a prostitute
that has heft and that's valid but if
you're writing a book about
like a love story you know two people
love and it's they're in roller coasters
or
carousels that's less legitimate i hate
that i hate that i hate that so much
because the message it gives to people
is you have to choose between
thriving and happiness and silliness and
seriousness
and depravity and i'm not saying a drug
addict approaches to pray but they're
basically their world views if it's
unless it's dark and twisted
it doesn't really count as art and i i
despise that mindset that subtext
so the internet and people around me
often will call me naive
because i don't think the word they want
is innocent don't you think it's about
it's not that innocent
no but it innocent in that you you
genuinely in your heart i know you
fairly well at this point
believe that goodness is possible and
that
people can if not be good at least be
better than they were yesterday see
even the word naive or the word innocent
presumes that
there's not wisdom in that presumes that
somehow
that's uh oh isn't that beautiful to
live that life
of a child who sees the world with these
bright eyes and is hopeful about the
future
but just wait until they grow up and
realize that reality is much harsher
than they think
right but that child might be wiser than
all of the adults in the room and don't
you don't you want to be if the world is
like that
don't you want to be the guy who takes
it on and changes it for the better
right so it's like saying well you know
cancer is everywhere it's inevitable
well don't you want to be the one who
says not anymore i'm here and i'm going
to make that change
and i can see it being better than it is
now
so i i i think you and i have the same
analysis of your world view and i don't
think that there is a good
word for it so i guess it's this idea of
you know inherent benevolence might be
you know maybe wordy
but i think that's more accurate because
you know you and i did not have such
easy lives
growing up to put it mildly you
constantly talk about
um just horrific aspects of life so to
claim that you kind of don't know that
they exist or you sleep on the rug
is completely not accurate to your work
and your mindset
can we talk about world war ii in the
soviet union
sure
so on sunday june 22nd
1941 hitler launched
operation barbarossa which was the
surprise invasion of the soviet union
that's right if i could read to you a
few lyrics
from a song that for some reason has
stuck throughout my childhood
it was a famous song during that time
the song talks about um kiev
like that moment as part of that
operation that kiev was first bombed and
it was announced on
june 22nd the song says at exactly four
o'clock
that the war has begun for some reason
this song
haunts me because
the exactness of that time and this
realization
that at any moment you could have this
thing happen to you in your own personal
life maybe you had something like 9 11
happen where everything changes
and it's just like haunting because it
makes me think
that at any moment something like that
could happen that changes everything
and i just think about like normal life
going on in kiev at the time
and then all of a sudden the bombs are
dropping
and they announced that the war has
begun and you thought you were
going to stay out of the war um
um this is something that is very
intensely emotional for me
because you and i are both russian
jewish
so to know that my grandparents
and my great-grandma were told
that the nazis were coming and this
wasn't a dress rehearsal
and that if they get here which they do
they did lev is very western ukraine
that 100
you and all your relatives are going to
be uh murdered
yeah and uh
there's a monument now in in level where
i'm from about this
but i i don't think either of us can
imagine
what it's like to know
to think that we're about
you know minutes or whatever hours or
there's just there's just the russian
army
standing between us and everyone
everyone
we are related to are going to be
murdered for no reason
and um
you know like what's the closure here
right like they evacuated a lot of
people
and but they didn't evacuate enough and
to know
that there is this force
coming to 100 murder you this isn't some
kind of you know uh the tv news being
hyperbolic they are coming to kill you
and they if they get you they will kill
you and you have to
you know we all think about war let go
you know we hope america wins in iraq
right but if america got their ass
kicked kind of in vietnam
it's not really going to affect america
in the sense that you're going to have
the body bags and all the kids being
killed and that's something that's i'm
not sweeping on the rug but
no one in america thought the vietnamese
are going to come here and kill them
right they were secure in their person
so to have that sense of
we really need to win because if we
don't win
we are 100 if we they the russian army
doesn't win
we are 100 percent all going to be
slaughtered
and often in not just a bullet to the
head in sadistic ways
is something that um to know that people
who share my blood
uh saw and went through is very hard for
me to kind of um
uh wrap my head around and there's no
possibility
to delude yourself yeah yeah yeah
because i mean they
they would uh as the song also talks
about but
they would burn the factories so it's
basically saying
we're in the war now this is like this
is your life yeah like this is our life
you know how you yesterday you're
worried about like oh i misplaced my pen
where is it like it's like yeah
this was paradise most of us are gonna
this our life now is that most
of us are going to die and
if we want to prevent all of us from
dying
we uh we have to fight and we also can't
sit down
in some kind of weird like um desert
island or
you know plane crash situation and be
like let's decide
between us who's going to be the first
to die maybe the like titan the titanic
right
they sat down and they were like women
and children in the lifeboats
you know they had this rational
agreement you don't have those choices
in in a war so um
it's it's something that i uh uh
it's it's just very chilling and it's
something i don't really have
um the emotional space to understand or
grapple with
uh even you know obviously i've been to
north korea you can see it and so on and
so forth
you and i can't or anyone listening to
this except for maybe on me and people
like that
you can't imagine what that's like to
live it
we can't i we can't imagine what it's
like to live in those situations where
it's not like before hitler came
everyone's you know dancing around
and having a great time i mean imagine
how what that life is like
where your preference to hitler
is starving and waiting online for hours
for bread
and to have the secret police and your
friends are turning you in and your
phones are all tapped and you're a
prisoner
but to you this is infinitely better
than the alternative like these are the
choices that you know our family had to
deal with it's something that no matter
how much
you it's like a let me put in terms
people understand
you know what i mean it's like your
first bad breakup right like that's a
much
simpler thing to wrap your head around
because it's like if you've never had it
you can't really
but when you feel it it's just so
intense but you can't tell someone
what's like
we could sit down for days and hours and
have people tell us
but until it's the totality totality of
your environment and your life and your
mindset
i remember my grandma
um
she would talk about that's like
when you're when you're that hungry
all you're thinking about is bread yeah
because your brain won't let you know
human beings you're revolved we have
instincts whatever and
the mind is telling you food food food
food food food
and that there's kids thinking this and
that there's there they're not going to
get the food yeah and
imagine being a parent and you're
watching your kids without food
and knowing they're not gonna get the
food
and uh the fact that this happened in
north korea in the 90s
yeah i i met a refugee
and uh he had to watch his dad starve to
death
and uh thank you um
and we have no
concept of uh
what it's like i mean we kind of you
know it's just like
last night here in austin all the places
were closed and i couldn't get my
protein powder
yeah and this is the extent of my
suffering
when it comes to food you know or if i
couldn't there was a restaurant that i
went to in brooklyn
where for some vacation reason they
weren't serving
sashimi they only had sushi so i had to
have the rice and the carbs
to live a life where that is the extent
of your food problems
as opposed to the choice is either
hitler
killing you or being hungry 24 7. you
know my grandma told this story of how
they had a close call it was her and her
brother and her mom my great-grandma who
passed
and i think there was like either
helicopter overhead or something and my
great-grandma jumped on top of my uh
grandma's brother and not my grandma so
she basically
did a sophie's choice my grandma's name
is sophia
and chose the brother and this is
something that she felt
you know all her life that her mom had
chosen her brother over her
but these little things that happen
these little kind of a
decisions we have to make in war there's
a book i read called uh
uh five chimneys i think this woman who
was an auschwitz survivor
and what she talked about what people
don't appreciate it's not
necessarily the slaughter and the
torture it's that
there's no rhyme or reason to it like
she talked about how they had a camp
just for people from uh czechoslovakia
and they were treated better than the
jews and then one day they just killed
them all
right and she's like i still don't
understand
why they're giving them food and
treating them well and then the next day
they're all killed
and we will never get answers you know
and she's and and things like
uh she talks about how they decided to
kill
all the kids and they didn't really
either for some reason they didn't have
the
courage to or they wanted to be cruel so
instead of shooting them they just kept
walking in the snow until they all died
so it's things like this that uh the
fact that you and i
dodged these bullets and that we can be
here
and uh be doing this and you know
running our mouths for a living
uh i i think about it all the time and
um
uh it's it's just very um
uh disturbing to know and i know you
know this as well that there's lots of
places on earth
where if people had a choice they would
kill us on site and be proud of
themselves for it
yeah they're i don't know what to make
of the contrast that you
you were talking about the fact that
you've been truly happy the last
few weeks and months yes there's been a
lot of moments of happiness and joy
and that joy is built on a history
of human suffering like in your roots in
your blood
is a lot of people that were tortured
that suffered so that you could have
this joy
you have both the you have the
responsibility to truly be grateful for
that joy
but it also shows that there's the happy
ending that it does
end in a good note that it does get
infinitely infinitely better
um and that i think there's a i don't
like you saying the word responsibility
but
there is um an opportunity for those of
us
who did dodge that bullet to uh
give testimony to these people and more
importantly to give testimony to the
people who are going through this
now so you know one of the reasons i you
know talk about north korea so much why
i wrote dear reader
is because it's very easy and this is
human nature i'm not
condemning people i don't i think this
is how people are wired
when you see an asian country with asian
people and things are
you know bad over there you you know i
think in the west it's like oh you know
asia they're all crazy there they're
wacky they eat you know they eat dogs or
someone and so forth some weird
stereotype and they think of them as
kind of martians
so it's important for people who aren't
of that
kind of ancestry to kind of speak on
behalf of these people because it's very
different how just people just naturally
react
when you have a westerner talking about
this instead of becoming
there you know them over there it
becomes you know this could have been
uh us very easily i have a friend peter
they hansky great dude
and i was showing him photos when i was
in pyongyang and he goes this looks like
a russian city with asian people it was
it completely disturbed him
so you know that was one of the reasons
i did go to north korea because that was
as close as
i would get to see what your family went
through to see what my family went
through
and they're still living under this uh
a regime and one of the things i fought
very hard to do with dear reader which i
was successful in amazingly and
it just i said like i could die now like
i feel like if you make if just move the
needle a little bit then you've kind of
uh paid your due for
your time here on this earth to have it
change from being a laughing stock
you know and i i think team america did
a good job
they made kim jong il into a clown and
they made a joke of it
but you're going from nothing to joke so
at least now people are aware of it that
it exists right
and then i st and many others took it
from a joke to like
guys this is really really really bad
and none of us can even appreciate how
bad it is and i think now there is an
understanding
other than a few people who are just
looking through a trump lens and wanting
trump to fail because trump's an [ __ ]
and that's fine
to be like these poor people and it's
really unfortunate because there's
a segment of western culture who thinks
that correctly often when you're
complaining about
uh or discussing the plight of another
country
that's just your preludes to war and an
excuse to invade like the kurds in syria
you know we're talked about if we're not
in syria tomorrow it's going to be
another genocide blah blah
i'm not saying let's invade north korea
or anything like that all i'm saying is
you know thank god that this is in your
life
i bring this up all the time the woman
who was my guide when i was there
i'm aware of what she's up to now she's
still
she's extremely rich by north korean
standards but she'll never be in a
position to buy medicine she'll never be
in a position to go on a vacation
uh things that you and i just you know
whatever she
she can't go on the internet she can't
get encyclopedia
uh she can't better herself as a person
other than
through what the state allows and
meaning better yourself as a person
in service to the state so i i i mean
there's it's also frustrating because
there's only so much that i can do
as an individual what's your takeaway
about human nature
from looking at north korea and looking
at how the rest of the world is looking
at north korea
uh i i always this is a great question i
think about it fairly often and i always
say
human beings are animals right when you
say someone's an animal
it's like a slur like he's like a beast
animals are capable of enormous kindness
empathy sympathy you know they look out
for one another
groom one another there's a thing with
with apes where they groom each other
for
parasites and you're suppose even if
there are no parasites they pretend this
parasites just to have that kind of
bonding
uh you see infinite uh photos online of
like cats raising puppies because the
puppies
mom died things like this that's part of
being an animal part of being an animal
is also
just the most uh monstrous cruelty
killer whales you know there's this big
pc move did not call them killer whales
and just call them orcas
they will murder blue whale pups
uh cavs excuse me and play with them and
not even eat them so they just murder
for the sake of fun
so there's and cats you know kill birds
all the time things like this so it runs
the whole gamut
um and i think it's i i'm you know when
yaron and i were on your show i don't
think lord of the flies is accurate i
don't think hobbes is how reality works
when you're in that kind of state um
but i think uh we've seen countless
examples
of human beings especially when human
beings have
power over someone who's powerless of
allowing themselves to engage in
not just harm but cruelty
and that is something as soviets you and
i are very painfully aware of it
it's not just about the oppression which
as bad enough as it is
it's that mediocre person with that
little bit of power
and now they're standing between you and
your daughter having medicine
and they love it to make you dance
to be like oh you need me to get this
medicine make you go
go through hoops because now they feel
like for the first time in their life
they're in a position of strength and
power
i think that is in many ways the more
common nature of evil what hannah aaron
talks about the banality of evil
than someone who's like an ss guard
you're shooting someone in the head
like that i think we could all wrap our
heads around to some extent like okay
i'm a military
it's not easy i have to execute people
pulling a trigger you could kind of have
this mental disconnect between the
finger and the victim
but like that little day-to-day stuff
like are you doing the right thing on a
day-to-day basis that i think is
far more common and far more disturbing
aspect in certain senses of the human
psyche
yeah there's something especially
disturbing about
a weak man
given power yeah and just abusing that
power
there's something about not just weak
but like mediocre and everything it does
or less than mediocre if you a great
example of this which i'm also talking
about the next book is ceausescu
who was the dictator of romania so you
know
the cold war is still somewhat poorly
understood in
you know popular culture but the
different countries in the second world
the soviet bloc
some are more liberal than others some
were more sane than others and
chauchesko
at first was one of the you know more
western friendly more the free ones
then he met the great leader kim sung
from north korea and he had the idea to
impose a personality cult on
romania and it's the kind of things like
forcing people to breed because he
wanted to make people taller
he i think he made like the biggest
building in all of europe the people's
palace but it was just for him
while there's no electricity you know
elsewhere but you look at this guy
you know stalin's a badass right he was
a bank robber if you look at photos of
him as a kid he was a hunk
lennon was clearly intellectual these
were not these are
powerful trotsky these were powerful men
with huge egos huge
force of personality but you look at
this chaucesko guy
and you could like for example on my
driver's license
instead of my address i'm like in my
real dress being like one two three four
fifth avenue by mistake it says one two
three four fifth street right
so you can imagine him being in the post
office and me giving him my id to get my
package and him being baffled
because this says street that says
avenue instead of understand and this
the look on his face this dullard that
you can see how you know how sometimes
i'm gonna can i curse
[ __ ] yes yes so if you know like if
you're in the airport and you see
someone and you look at them an adult
and you think okay this person was born
[ __ ] up just like on site like
something's wrong with them how are they
traveling alone
you look at chauchesku you look at him
you're like something's not right with
this guy not in the sense of like evil
but in the sense that he's a simpleton
right
and now he's in charge of this whole
country and everyone's taught to regard
him as one of the great geniuses of all
time
and it's this the idea this mediocre
nobody this guy would have in any other
culture been accomplished
nothing or or at war would have had an
honest job where he's like okay he works
at the mail mail service and he's batted
it okay fine he's not hurting anyone
and now as a result of this he's
responsible for mass death
secret police and incarceration and uh
you know the one the greatest things
that i've ever seen which i'm sure
many people have seen as well if you go
on youtube it's his speech
and it's the first time the crowd turns
and his head kind of like because they
start booing him
which was unheard of and you know he was
shot with his uh um
dog-faced wife not that long after it
was just a great moment but
it's things like this i agree with you
that that mediocre weak person
is now in a position of power over
somebody else and that sense of
vindictiveness like i'm going to feel
strong for once in my life but it's
going to be at your expense
that i think is you know human nature
it's most primal
and every time i meet a person in this
world you're the first person to get me
to cry on a [ __ ] podcast [ __ ] the
robot gets me to cry what the
[ __ ] is going on every time i meet a
weird person
somebody to me heroism
is also taking a risk to uh rebel
against mediocrity yeah
like in in the most simplest of ways
like the
the license address like taking a risk
to break the little bit of rule that
nobody will know about to take that
little bit of a
leap of like that little protest against
the bureaucracy
well like that nazi remedy where he just
spoke out he's like hey lady
that's a big one oh that's a
restructuring i mean like literally at
the line at starbucks or something like
okay like even in the tiniest of ways
when i see
people just like it's almost like that
little
like glimmer in their eye a wink like
we're in this together
this there's there's all this conformity
all around us
that's at a different time could have
been nazi germany
could have been uh stalin and soviet
union sure
we're in this together we're going to
rebel against that conformity
by just just taking the risk that little
bit of risk
against mediocrity i don't know and that
and then
once again i see this in companies too
when i see the mediocrity i see this you
know i used to work at google i see it
in google
and when the companies grow that
mediocrity is overwhelming
the peter principle right the peter
principle yeah yeah my hope is that all
of us have the possibility
for that glimmer that um that risk
taking
the the leap of faith or whatever the
heck that is
the leap out of the ordinary out of the
conformity out of the mediocrity
so this is where you and i disagree i i
think
most a lot of people do are not capable
of that
they're accustomed to it i don't know if
they're not capable
i i i understand your position i'm
disagreeing with it i'm saying i do not
think they're capable i think a lot of
people
effectively don't have souls they do not
have a conscience in this sense where
they're going to
look at an issue bring their critical
thinking
and say all right i am going to do the
right thing
although i'm taking a risk i don't think
thinking is involved or is it just
taking that leap there
there's something about that basic human
spirit forget the thinking part
it's it's just saying like i'll take
that risk
they're taking that adventure the same
thing that got people to explore
the seas you know that that
uh throughout human civilization explore
land
explore the oceans like that explore
exploration like
we've done stuff this way all this time
i'm going to take a leap and that comes
out of nowhere seemingly but those
people are the heroes but i don't think
that's universal
remember there's i'm going to use a very
gauche example
there was a show called scare tactics
which was basically a candid camera but
they would scare people like they'd have
vampires whatever
hidden camera and people's reactions and
so a lot of but sometimes it the prank
didn't work out like they expected
so there was one where they were hiring
some of the the people who were the
marks you know the contestants so to
speak
was it was hard to be a security guard
okay and you have to watch this
this factory overnight and you get paid
and what the setup was
some people were breaking out of the
factory in the middle of the night like
in rags
and they were saying they were keeping
us prisoner here like blah blah and just
watch the person reaction to this
and there was one security guard where
there
he basically forced them back into the
building and they're like
they're working us 24 7 we're getting
beaten he's like i'm here to do a job
get back in there and you watch this and
it
never even enters his head to be like
something's wrong here
he was given his orders he's following
his orders
and to me that is not uncommon
and that person although they look like
you and i uh
there's something essentially human
missing with them now
very quickly the reaction is well it's
one step from there to
nazism i don't think it's something that
i'm not saying this person should be
killed but i'm just saying
to expect that every human being
has the capacity to have that defiance
especially to cost their own life that i
think is not
realistic uh and i but at the same time
i feel like an octopus on the eighth
hand it is those few of us
or if you want to include me in this who
do make these tiny little protests who
look
the other way when someone is hungry
who's stealing food from the supermarket
right
it's like all right like i i'm gonna
pretend i didn't see anything
that those little elements of heroism
are what move humanity forward and
demonstrate the validity of the human
experience
whereas everyone else is kind of like
scenery i think
almost everybody in the world can derive
deep meaning
and pleasure from having done those
courageous acts
and i also think they have the capacity
to do them
to discover that meaning and happiness
so you're the cynic then why aren't they
doing it
they haven't gotten a chance to like
i've never
tried lsd or dmt
you haven't gotten the chance to try
this amazing journey
which is taking the risk that's
something yes because as you just said
two minutes ago everyone has that chance
every day to do the right thing and we
have the chance to do a lot of things
and we don't realize
there's a lot of stuff right in front of
our nose that we don't realize
right because you have to kind of wake
up to it and sometimes
uh you need the catalyst there needs to
be
some kind of thing that happens that
wakes you up
that the fact that most people
don't take the small acts of rebellion
doesn't mean they
don't have the capacity to both do so
and to
derive a lot of meaning from it then
it's a
discussion about how to create societies
that get more and more people
to be free actors and free thinkers
that's that's the question and that that
probably leads us into a discussion of
anarchism and so on but
yeah i just think we are very young as a
species
we're trying to figure out how to get
ourselves
to first be collaborative but at the
same time be
free spirits and i think both of those
are within human nature
i think another big concern is that
there's enormous disincentives
and this is michael malus speaking yeah
uh for human beings to be kind
and for tenderness and i think
especially when you're young you know
what i mean when you're immature
a lot of times someone will reach out to
you with kindness or vulnerability
and you think it's funny to kind of dunk
the head underwater in a pool or
something like that
yeah and when you get older you look
there you know there's this one
uh example of this this was a this was
in the 90s
and there was a woman she became a like
uh like stripper or something like that
or whatever it was but she had this
amazing body she was just gorgeous
and the show was she was talking about
how when she was in high school she was
bullied a lot
and that there was this football player
he messed with her every single day
and like at one day she even threw
pickles in her hair and her hair smelled
like pickles and it was laughing at her
and this really screwed her up i mean up
to that show and they took her backstage
and they brought out the football player
now he's a dad
and a regular dude and he's like do you
know like do you know why you're here
and he's like no and they're like oh
what were you like in high schools like
i was kind of a jock
you know bully whatever and they brought
her out and he didn't even remember her
really
and she just starts crying about the
pickles and whatever and there's
something that affected her for like 20
years and i've never seen
a clear example of someone who wants to
kill themselves in this guy
like the guilt on his face and he's
looking at her
and he's desperate to be like what can i
do
to take your pain away to make it better
uh
like i i he was just crippled by it
because he knew there's nothing he could
do
he knew he 100 did the wrong thing he
knew he did the wrong thing unthinkingly
like you can imagine you know i gotta
screw over this lady to feed my family
you know that that's fine
but for it was at the time it meant
nothing to him so of course he didn't
remember
and he was just paralyzed by this sense
of crippling guilt one of the reasons i
always try to do the right thing isn't
because
i'm an inherently good person which i do
not think i am i don't think anyone is
inherently good
but because i will feel guilty about it
for a very very
long time because if you do the wrong
thing this is a very common idea
if you do the wrong thing to a good
person
that's really really bad because what
kind of person are you
in the same way that everyone can be
that guy who takes someone out for their
birthday
everyone has that ability for someone
who did the wrong thing
to someone who's a normal person and do
you want to be that guy as well
my friend uh um bitstein he's a um
uh big gold uh excuse me bitcoin person
my biography ego and hubris is like 500
now on ebay it's like hard to find came
out in 2006
and he had told me that you know you can
get it on on torrent it's it's
downloadable and i'm like oh i thought
if you were my friend you know you'd
want to buy it
at the time it was not 500 i assure you
and he goes i did buy it
i'm just telling you that you could also
get it for free this information that
you might want to use
and i felt i'm like i snapped at this
kid
who was doing right by me and i felt
it just stuck in my head i'm like you're
an ass yeah and then years later i
apologize he didn't have no memory of
this at all and i'm glad to be able to
reiterate the apology again
but you know this is you know a lot of
times i'm extremely aggressive
on twitter and in other venues i always
try to and maybe i fail and that's
my moral failing always do it as a
counter-attack
if you're gonna start going personal if
you're gonna start being aggressive
against an individual i'm not going to
necessarily
hold back when i reciprocate and it's
something that is very common
on social media but i don't think it is
normal i
just because a lot of this you're
talking about the the quiet little
rebellion
just because everyone else around you
thinks it's okay
to just go up to people and attack them
in the most personal ways
imprompted because of their views really
just
take a step back and realize what you're
engaging with now if that's the fight
they want
then you know my soviet cruelty can come
out and that's
kind of why i don't drink because i do
enjoy it yeah but at the same time
be aware of what you're doing and and
and again this goes back to camus
um sense that conscience really is what
makes us human beings
yeah that's the thing was saying i don't
think most people think in terms of
conscience they don't think it
they we are taught this is that this is
that that creeping cynicism
that oh grow up when you're an adult you
have to make sacrifices
blah blah blah and even if i buy that
for a second which i don't
but if i have to make sacrifices
sometimes
that doesn't mean it's okay for me to
make a sacrifice of my values in
this moment if i have to maybe be at
work
and my boss is a jerk to me and calls me
names i have to be humiliated but i got
to put food in the plate
that doesn't mean it's okay later if i'm
at a party and i'm just
you know extremely offensive to someone
for no reason
you know my own flavor of a little bit
of rebellion
sometimes i use the number two
is uh you know you're very witty on
twitter and thank you
my and twitter
likes mockery and wit
and uh counterattack
is uh twitter loves that somebody who's
skilled at it
my own flavor of a bit of a rebellion is
to say things
very simply bordering and cliche
with with uh with a authenticity
and like genuinely meaning the words i
say
but knowing that those words would be
are easy to attack sure and that
sometimes those attacks can hurt because
people would just
mock me sure people don't like
earnestness because they've been taught
to be
too cool for school yeah so there's this
pressure for me to be
sound way more sophisticated yeah use
bigger words
sometimes throw in um a criticism
of institutions or something like that
like uh
like almost as if i have a deep wisdom
about the way the world is broken
but when you speak very simply about
beautiful
things in life it's very easy to sound
like you don't know what the hell you're
talking about sure and
i kind of i stick by that
i don't know where that's going to end
up but it's like the idiot from this day
it feels like that's the right uh that's
the right thing
even if it hurts when i'm attacked for
it i i do something similar sometimes
which is i'll have some innocuous
comment about like bubble gum i mean
just it's not even political
and a lot of times people it's a few
people will respond to this paragraph of
just invective
yeah about like blah blah and then this
and you say this and you're an ass and
just really trying to get at me
and what i in those situations there are
very specific circumstances
i will respond and i mean it every
single time i will say i i
wish your parents had been kinder to you
or your mom or your dad
because if someone is some even if i'm
some idiot on twitter right if we just
talk about bubble gum and this is your
res i'm not talking about politics where
i can see how people get emotional coven
my grandma died now you're talking
and you i realize this isn't about me
like i'm someone you've never met making
some inane point about nothing
and you're getting agitated about this
it's clearly something
else that's going on here and someone
taught you someone had to teach you
that this is how to respond in this kind
of very kind of harsh way
and a lot of times they'll you know they
won't say anything or get deleted
and i hope every single time
there's no asterisk here that they take
a second
and they realize that the way that they
were talked to
growing up was not acceptable that
they don't have to carry this forward
and that
they don't have to be kind to me i'm
nobody of them but take a second and ask
if this is the kind of mindset you want
to be your norm
as opposed to a weapon you pull out of
your pocket sometimes where it's
warranted or even when it's not
warranted
i think there's a lot of those people
out there you know and we forget
uh how you know how
um hard it is for a lot of people to
grow up
how they're trained from their parents
or the single parent
that the only way they're gonna get
attention is by acting out
that when they do good things it doesn't
get comment but if they do bad things
they gotta smack upside their head
that i think is far more common than we
realize
and that's such a it's not even it's not
hitting the kid that's going to last
it's the pain is going to give five five
seconds
but when you're training this child
helpless child
is something that's really really bad i
don't know if it always can be mapped to
that
i always wonder about them like what
their motivations are
and i just kind of like whenever i think
about them i think only positively
and i don't even think about the
childhood thing i think
i don't know i i i kind of imagine that
all of us can go through that stage
where we enjoy the derision of others
we go through stages of being i i enjoy
the derision of others but it has to be
you know billy i'd have that quota like
i like it when people are mean to me i
stopped pretending to be nice
but like what's the worst thing someone
can say about you you're not what harm
are you doing
uh maybe your podcast is garbage and the
people are the conversations suck and
the people are losing well okay
no the main the main thing i would say
is i'm way more popular than i deserve
to be
what does deserve mean the reality is
there's people out there that just enjoy
hating on others
and i don't um
i don't fault them for it like i don't
even think of them as
haters i think of them as just people
that in this particular part of their
life
are enjoying this activity of uh
of deriding others on the internet
i'm i'm not sure what to do with that i
i just don't want to
i i don't want to allow myself to think
badly of them i guess is the thing
i'm the one saying don't think badly of
them i'm saying that i don't think
they're inherently bad people i think
that their thinking is screwed and that
i'm i'm i'm steel mining them i'm saying
let's assume everything you're saying
about lex is true
this is an opportunity for you to out
dulex like it's
no but are you saying they should stop
hating because i'm saying like maybe
they shouldn't
just keep i i don't believe in should
right i'm an anarchist what i'm saying
is like if this is your belief about lex
you know what it is i made this comment
in my book than you write when people
make fun of andy warhol
and they're like oh my god he painted a
soup can and now he became a millionaire
i could do this
well why don't you yeah so basically if
i go up to you
with a check and i say i will give you a
million dollars you could see the check
you got to paint a soup can what am i
waiting for
so clearly there's a disconnect in their
thinking between what they're perceiving
and the reality because if it was as
simple or as maybe not simple but as as
possible for them as they perceive it to
be why are they leaving comments instead
of
uh outdoing you how great would it be
for them
to have your bigger audience and drive
you into the ground i don't know how
that would work because it's not the nba
but no
but you want to point out you do this
too on twitter you want to point out
the hypocrisy
the fraudulence of others right yeah
what are you you're not claiming
anything other than this is
the following is the conversation
between me and
and yeah michiki whatever his name is
right i got the voice down dude
i got it down i've been walking around
my house doing my lex impression
i've been leaking motor oil everywhere
yeah
but yeah i don't know i i don't know i
don't know what to make of it because uh
i think there's a more general statement
to be made like i see twitter this way
too
when i read a tweet i try to
read it with like the best possible
interpretation
meaning like what is the wisdom in this
tweet
right as opposed to what i think a large
number of people
not a large but some fraction
try to see what is the worst possible
interpretation of this tweet
and they want to they they want to
destroy you
for that worst interpretation like they
want to um
there's people i'm already aware of this
with me and certainly with a lot of
people they're waiting for me to fail
they want me to be like this guy talks
about love all the time
you want me to be some dark like uh
abilities
pain yeah they want you to be in pain
because they die i'll tell you exactly
why
because this is why i'm so for being
white-pilled and being for hope
because if you are black-pilled meaning
if you think
it's pointless we're all done you're
just wasting your breath
if you have any counter examples to this
thesis if there's even a little bit of
hope
your entire hypothesis falls through
right so if it's
it's kind of how like you have all these
stories of people who are like painting
swastikas who aren't nazis but just to
show that
oh there's all this nazism so i'm gonna
you know kind of force the conclusion
so for them when they see you thriving
you are
as a mediocre person with a crappy show
but you're demonstrating that people can
succeed this bothers them
so you are anyone can succeed that
bothers them yeah so
because then why haven't they so now
you're a counter to their world view
and that is going to cause anxiety when
you have data
that contradicts other data in your in
your world view this is the
in your mindset this is a big issue for
them yeah so anyone listening to this
they're annoyed by the look of my face
remember
that you could probably do way better
than me and you should but also what
would you
failing look like like let's suppose
this podcast went from whatever views
you had
to 100 views in episode that's still
success
you are talking to people you like
having conversations about important
issues you're having a good time
they're giving a good time how is that a
failure if i have dinner with a friend
of mine
there's zero viewers and we enjoy that
time
that is the height of human success
when you are sharing happiness happiness
joy
joy over love so what's the difference
between joy and love
michael malus uh i think joy is easier
to attain
it's more common you could share it with
everyone
give me an example of joy like what was
the moment of joy for you recently
i could give you a great example of joy
and this is part in the absurdist
mindset
okay i love having a bad meal at a
restaurant
and i'll give you you can see why you go
with your friend
it takes you 45 minutes to get seated
okay
i'm starving waiters not at paying
attention to you
they bring your water it's got a hair in
it they get the food wrong
yeah it comes out again it's ripe but
it's cold at a certain point
you're like okay i'm hungry i'm living
an anecdote
this is something that you if you were
at dinner we could talk about this for
years because
how great is it that the worst thing
that's happening to me
is i gotta wait an hour for this meal
that's gonna be cooked wrong
right that to me is joy is holding on
to that idea that happiness and thriving
are possible
even when in the moment it's uh
everything's going the wrong way
doesn't every moment have the capacity
to uh
fill you with joy then yes so yes the
shitty moments and the good moments
yes but that see that's the way i
usually talk about love is
like i love life
yes and in because life can generate
every
everything the pain the loss but also
just like simple or complicated bliss
all of that i just love all of that and
that because it fills me with it with a
kind of
i guess joy but joy has a connotation
that's supposed to be somehow positive
like you're supposed to be smiling
uh to me you know man search for meaning
with victor
frankl you know just it's you're
you're in the holocaust you're in a
concentration camp
just having a little bit of food that
you didn't expect you will have
uh or even just thinking about food or
what about there's a kid there you tell
them a funny story you crack them up
yeah like you take away this child's
pain for like five minutes that
is the height of joy yeah so to me like
all of like life is
like infinitely full of possibility for
joy yes
and that's what i mean by love because
oftentimes like romantic love is what
people
think about when they think love but to
me it's all like part of the same thing
and it's almost like love romantic love
or
love with a friend friendship is like
you both notice each other it's like
dogs they look at each other and then
they look at the thing they're
interested in you both notice each other
and
that moment of joy you share that moment
of joy together yeah like the restaurant
yeah the restaurant
yeah if you're both almost without
uh conspiring notice the
absurdity of how shitty this meal is and
like that again that little glimmer of
realization
that's that's what makes life beautiful
you mentioned uh
your grandmother and levovov you were
thinking of returning there
the plans got a little bit delayed but
what are you hoping from that trip of
going back to russia
going back to ukraine what do you
hope to get out of it but what do you
think you will feel
uh a lot of things first of all i'm
going with
my buddy chris williamson he hosts the
modern wisdom podcast
he is one of my closest friends we've
never met
oh really we've never met he's br he's
in britain he's tried he's
trying to get his ass over here to
austin uh he's filling out his form
he's too good-looking a crime we call
him i call him apollo and i'm loki
so right away you have a buddy comedy
because we're gonna film it right you
have these two guys who on paper
you're very dissimilar but we're very
very close in which way are you
similar i think we're both very intense
people
uh very strong emotionally um
uh we're both very ambitious in the
sense that
uh not in terms of career but like we
want to grab life by the short hairs
kind of thing
um we're just both like good experiences
uh he uh bench more than you or oh yeah
he's
he's of course i mean the guy's jacked
he's just because you know he he's so
good-looking he could be one of those
guys
who's mostly biceps and oh no no no he's
not
if you look at go to his instagram chris
will x is his
handle it's like head head it's it's
head to toe it's just sculpted
he's perfect in every way that's great
he he
what flaws does he have because i need
that taste of friends
and his accent is all crazy
yeah uh he pronounces it uh he's an
under a muddle
now i spell it mudl so just us two
british and american and just two
different dudes it's going to be a lot
of fun although to be fair
as you know i'm an underwear model now
as well so yeah yeah
we're going to talk that in a second
maybe but um yeah
thunderbird.com yeah uh this episode is
brought to you by sheath underwear are
we going to get some pictures
eventually i think we might yeah uh yes
i have them on my phone we're gonna
we'll have them we could we could
shouldn't write
uh you could slice it in right here so
to be able to go
with someone who is a very close i mean
we meet him talk like every day right
so to someone who generally cares about
you
who uh who's he's very very grounded
right so like a lot of times i'll have
like some concern
and he's really good and if you listen
to show at slicing through the noise and
being like hold on a second i can't do
the accent yet
have you considered a b and c because
you know whenever i had the situation
this is what i did so he's really good
with that um
so to have a first of all just like two
buddies on a trip is a really a lot of
fun
second of all i know that if it's gonna
get be very intense
so for you you left russia much later
than i did how old were you 13
13 right so you remember it i'm sure
very very well i left when i was one and
a half two i don't remember at all
to go to the streets
where you know my family had to go
through this stuff to see the you know
they they came to live up they
slaughtered all the jews i mean to have
that little memorial there that's there
now
and to just look around and know
yesterday best basically
they came here they rounded everyone up
and also from the other side you had the
stalinists coming in and starving all
the people
it's it's just to know that so much
horror and death there's this quote i
saw once
about a woman who went to auschwitz and
she just made the comment like grass
grows here
because we think you know that when it
comes to the nature of evil that you're
going to go there this is going to be
this
pits of hell or whatever there's birds
you know
there's you know robin's hopping around
looking for the worms or whatever they
think it's perfectly nice and you you
you stand there to understand that so
much suffering happened here
or there is going to be very jarring
i know that it's going to be an issue
because i speak russian and not
ukrainian
and to speak russian to ukrainians is
like a big deal so that's gonna be a
concern
i'm also worried about going to russia
because every russian
has this idea that even though they've
just met you they feel it
they feel that they're in a position to
tell you what you're doing wrong with
your life what you should be doing if
they're a cab driver
i have no tolerance for unsolicited
advice on a basis at all
that's gonna be horrible they're gonna
be telling me i need to speak russian
better because think about
i'm not hearing it i'm not interested in
hearing it so
that i think and also you know given my
upcoming book
the white pill and covering what
happened back in the day under stalinism
and later
to see this was the leblanc this was the
basement where they would you know you
know once this is something that
people might not realize there's a
superb film uh the death of stalin which
is kind of that's what i do with north
korea
you know he puts a humorous spin on and
then when you take a step back and you
realize what they're actually saying
it's just like it's very very disturbing
how when stalin was dying he had a
stroke he's laying there in a pile of
his own past he's unconscious
he'd be right before he died he thought
the doctors were all plotting against
him
so they were being tortured to confess
that they were trying to murder him
they had to get the doctors out of the
torture chambers
to attend to him and they did it so this
kind of thing to like
go there like red square and see this is
where it happened
to see lennon's body like this is the
guy who emma goldman yelled at
it's gonna be really um because i've
worked so much in this space jarring and
intense and emotional and that's
as intense as for me sitting here
talking to you about it to see it and to
see the faces
and to see cyrillic everywhere you know
other than brighton beach and brooklyn
um
it's gonna i'm sure it's gonna do a huge
number on me because
uh as we as western and as the tupoi
mirikanets as the russians will say i am
this is still where i came from yeah so
no matter
to see it face to face i don't know how
i'm gonna react but i don't think it's
gonna be like
meh you've assembled uh a number of
essays
from anarchist thinkers in a new book
called the anarchist
handbook you mentioned emma goldman
what interesting things do these
thinkers agree on and what do they
disagree on
the anarchist handbook.com is the
website it covers from the 1790s to
i think my essay is the last one from
2014 which uh
a friend of mine who's uh kind of a
mediocre scientist is going to be
reading for the audiobook
um also podcasts and vodka i never
but it's not a podcast anyone would have
heard of it's like tom wood's been even
worse
so what they all agreed on
was the illegitimacy of government
and also the malevolence of state actors
and the consequences of governments
so they range in terms that most people
would easily regard as either left or
right wing
but it tackles the nature of government
and
also creates positive non-state
alternatives
from really many different angles the
slogan i have is the black flag which is
the traditional flag of anarchism
the black flag comes in many colors so
they were really all over the map in
terms of what they're for
but their disagreement is about the
nature of state and the nature of power
um and it's very edifying because this
is an ideology that's been
in many ways swept on the rug no one
takes this seriously grow up
um that i can allow people to sit down
and read these essays
and see for themselves just how
beautiful this tapestry
over the decades and centuries uh has
been woven about people who genuinely
believed
in freedom as the most important
and how to maximize that uh uh for
society
so maybe it's useful to talk about a few
contrasting thinkers in there so
one is uh leo tolstoy oh yeah
who um i think not many people know
is uh an anarchist yes uh a christian
and a christian anarchist yeah so he
uh came to despise government for his
deceit and his violence
but to him the the christian principles
of non-violence i think
are important oh yeah this kind of
pacifist kind of mindset
of uh you know it's better to someone to
punch you than to punch them back
so he's in that way at least i read he
influenced mlk and gandhi
what do you think about this flavor
color
of the anarchist flag of non-violence ah
nonviolent opposition
i i i will put the caveat that
it bothers me when people bring up mlk
because he's become so corporate
yeah and everyone just brings him up
without knowing about him one of the
things that martin luther king
did so very well was that he forced
people to face the consequences of what
they were putting forward
you want to be racist you want to be for
jim crow you wanted for segregation
okay it's easy for you to do that from
your living room now turn on your news
and you see men and women in suits being
attacked by dogs
being attacked by fire hoses and beaten
by cops
just so they could sit on the front of
the bus and now for a lot of people
who were still racist who were still had
animus toward black people are watching
this and it's gonna be a lot harder
to be like i'm okay with this i'm okay
with human beings even ones i regard as
somehow bad or inferior
to be beaten and attacked by
trained dogs and they're not doing
anything in response
that strikes to i think a very basic
nature of especially american like
okay whatever you're for i'm not for
people getting beaten and attacked
when they're not really doing anything
so i think
pacifism is something that's very easy
to make fun of
but people don't underestimate how
powerful it is for someone to say
you can do what you want to me i'm not
going to fight you back
i just want to live peacefully and have
the same rights as you
and to say screw you you should get
beaten
that's a hard pill for a lot of people
to swallow so i think he was
really and gandhi of course as well were
excellent in that regard there's a
little bit of machiavellianism to it you
know they've both been beatified
regardless saints
but their strategy worked very very well
for their purposes so i think uh
just all of us when you see someone you
know in this kind of christian
i know iran obviously it's nothing very
highly christianity but if he's someone
who's willing
to you know take a punch and just say
you could do whatever you want to me
i'm not going to hurt somebody else
instinctively
that maybe this is kind of a hack most
people want to side with that guy
step in between and be like oh okay
let's take a step back because whatever
led to this is not tenable we need to go
back to the drawing board if the
consequence
is people are having these as a result
of my decisions and actions so
i think that aspect of anarchism uh
is very very in certain context healthy
and much smarter and more sophisticated
than people give it credit for and let's
also point out
that tolstoy wrote warned peace and he
wrote anna karenina
so this was not some naive or innocent
whatever word you want to use
he knew the nature of evil he knew how
bad things get
so he wasn't saying at all that human
beings are inherently nice and kind
he was saying it's much more effective
to not fight back
and to force them to face that i i i'll
give you another example
i was talking to i was on the show of
trigonometry
and i was talking to the hosts and one
of them talked about how
someone he knew had been uh in the gulag
or
his mom was born the gulag grandma and
after stalin died and the soviet union
liberalized
and lots of the people in the gulags
were freed by khrushchev and and so on
and so forth
he i didn't know this many of the or
some let's say some
of the guards of the gulags killed
themselves because they had genuinely
believed
that everyone in these camps was there
for a reason and when they found out
that these people were completely
innocent didn't even have trials
and that they were the ones forced them
to work themselves death and starve
they couldn't deal with that guilt so
when you are
a pacifist or non uh a non-retaliatory
and you're forcing someone who's using
force like look what you're doing
look what you've become for some people
some people don't care
you know like the guy in scare tactics
like i mentioned earlier where for a lot
of others
they're gonna be like okay is this who i
wanted to grow up to be they will have
that little flame of conscience that you
and i talked about earlier
there will be like how did i get to the
point where there's this lady
who wants to ride the bus and she's you
know lovely dressed
put together and i have a sending a dog
on her
what kind of person am i for some of
those people
they're gonna be like okay i can't be a
part of this i don't even understand the
politics
i still am racist but i'm not going to
take part
in this atrocity well that was uh for
him
from the individual perspective perhaps
he
he calls that christian but listening to
that voice of conscience
like whatever that is in you
so for tolstoy it seems like
anarchism from the individual
perspective
is uh silencing the rest of the world
and listening to the
the for him probably god-given voice of
conscience yes
and so that that's what it means to live
embody anarchism and to embody
christianity i would think he would say
but he would see those as basically yes
correct uh
yeah so in terms of forms of government
the christian government is one that's
no government
yeah correct uh
what do you think about that as a device
for an individual turn the other cheek
do you think uh
i tend to believe that that's a really
good way to live
i think it's very underrated and this is
me talking
i think a lot of times when someone
let's suppose you're having an argument
and but you have to you have to pick
your battles right let's suppose you're
having a heat argument if someone says
something very cruel to you
we have attempted to double down and hit
back twice as hard
but if it's someone who at all cares
about you when they're just in the
moment and you just stop and you just
say
did you hear what you just said to me
for some cases
that person will take a step back and be
like just like me when i snapped at
michael
uh at bitstein years ago i'd be like wow
okay this is bad this is bad i'm sorry
and they kind of
you know it's kind of like they have to
get to 10 before they re
control or delete to use your language
thank you yeah
but for overflow i appreciate that but
and for some they're gonna
they're gonna just twist the knife but i
think this is a very useful
technique and also you can also sleep
well at night
because you could be like as much as
this person tried to hurt me
i still didn't reciprocate and yeah i
took that punch and it sucks
but at least i never said anything that
i could feel guilty about
exactly do you think that's ultimately a
good way to implement
anarchy in your personal life anarchy
implementing anarchy in your personal
life just means
uh respecting people's boundaries it
means
uh um uh not forcing people to do things
they otherwise wouldn't want to do
i think you then have to take uh
case by case like there's so many human
interactions that are required for life
and there's tension and all those kinds
of things it's not always
being so naive no should i put the hat
on
the hat's on the other head now well i
had to take off the hat cause it's like
photo with the ring i was starting to
feel
like powerful i wanted to give you
orders and i want
no i i just i think there's uh ways of
dealing with the tensions that are
natural to human interactions
that can't be simply um
you know it's not as simple as saying
you want to respect
the freedom of others and uh the
boundaries of others
it's like you both have to agree on
stuff and work something out
and the mechanisms of that agreement the
game theory of that agreement
requires different hacks and strategies
and the the
the question is for an anarchist
collective
that's well functioning what kind of
hacks
uh what kind of ways of behavior
are more likely to be productive and not
you know that that's almost like the
question do you want to turn the other
cheek or do you want to stand your
ground really firmly
when somebody is an [ __ ] to you you
walk away
or when somebody is an [ __ ] to you
you turn the other cheek and give them a
chance to rise to the best version of
themselves
and then find a common ground kind of
thing it's
it's an open question of how to form
those collectives when there's people
with with difficult childhoods and
all that kind of stuff but it also comes
down to what is your relationship with
this person
right is this out of character if you
and i got into a disagreement all of a
sudden you started getting very personal
first i'd be very hurt
yeah but then i'd be like this is out of
character for lex i'm sure i could be
like
let's take a pause here like you're
getting heated i'm trying to work this
out
what's going on here and you get a kind
of a meta conversation but again you and
i have a relationship with mutual
respect so
as opposed to if it was a stranger you
know who's
just wants a piece of you it's just like
i don't you are coming at me not correct
i don't have to reciprocate in kind i'm
not going to shoot you
but i'm not going to pretend that you
deserve respect when you're treating me
with such contempt
i i do defer especially with people i
know
because it's just this is smart
long-term game theory as well as the
right thing to do
i do try to give them the benefit of the
data first right yeah because if you're
gonna go aggro you can't go back
but you could always go from like let me
hear them out and then then i could go
aggro so there's a big asymmetry
there yeah and that's i mean i don't
think anyone
has the answer to this question is is
that the right strategy
to me game theoretically it seems the
right strategy is to uh with reciprocity
is what game theory says is the right
strategy they did the prisoner's dilemma
and they found tit for tat is the one
that's the most advantageous
so that's for when it's perfectly
rational actors but when you have
i mean there's noise the the
there's uh i think benefit to just
even if they keep being shitty to you
still
being nice to them well then there's the
universe where girls are turned off
some people are like if you're in a
relationship and not just girls but girl
like
some people when you're kind to them
they find you less attractive
right that is kind of this weird what am
i supposed to do like you're only into
me
if i'm mean to you i don't want to be
mean but then i'm getting punished for
doing the right thing that's another
tricky one
and i mean this is nothing that
necessarily do with anarchism so much as
like you know human beings are
infinitely complex
we don't often know the back story like
for example just yesterday jay
who's here is one of my closest friends
i had
a dinner with a bunch of people i
couldn't bring a plus four
so i didn't he wasn't invited he didn't
know the circumstances he just thought
we were having dinner without him he was
hurt
once i spelled it out he completely
understood it i felt horrible because
for me
to have any of my friends feel left out
is just a very very cruel thing
um and i was i felt bad and i'm glad to
apologize again publicly that that's end
up being the circumstances but yeah it's
it's
it's a lot of times we're also in
plato's cave when you're dealing with
somebody else you have very very limited
information about their background and
circumstances
and that's why i will always if it's
someone i even have a little bit
of a relationship with try to give them
benefit of doubt because
i've found especially this comes from
being a co-author when you co-author
books and you're walking other people's
shoes
you don't know what's a lot of the
information so if
it's a lot of times it's just a
misunderstanding but isn't that a
fundamentally anarchist question
of uh how we figure out this puzzle of
human complexities in order to form
voluntary collectives like we have to
figure that out how to make
people feel good how to make people i
agree that's fair
and that i think i think not only
anarchists have to think about this as
my point
of course well but we have to think
about it more than others do
right i feel like i should try to argue
against anarchism
at some point out of love out of love
and
so because people out of joy do people
enjoy
seeing me um what is it when like ben
shapiro
argues against like a 20 year old
feminist destroys high school students
so this is this is this video of uh
michael males destroys uh
a a marxist russian communist
pig so anarchism as opposed to
hierarchies
well that's left anarchism yeah
anarcho-communism yeah the state but
there are many hierarchies that are not
the state you we have a hierarchy here
this is your show on differential to you
right but they're okay rigid hierarchies
forced hierarchies is the first time yes
forced hierarchies okay
so do you think it's possible that
humans when left on their own
chord they they form hierarchies
naturally yes inevitably it might be
inevitably which is why i disagree with
the left anarchist
i think it's not a coherent thing to
argue for uh
non-hierarchical relationships even in
theory it doesn't make sense to me
and i i know the the the old school
anarchist will call me stupid or
uninformed but i
i've never been able to even wrap my
head around this claim that you could
have relationships with that hierarchy
right so i guess there's a certain sense
in which we're living in
anarchism now and i don't mean just like
because the the nations as
you've said are uh in anarchism relative
to each other
but isn't the united states just a
collective that was formed
in anarchy and this is just the
collective that we're
operating under this hierarchy that was
naturally formed it wasn't well the
united states was not naturally formed
it was formed by force and and by fiat
but to your point um i i stress this
throughout the book
uh i always say this anarchism is not a
location it's a relationship
so yeah you and i do have a hierarchy in
that this is your show
but not but neither of us really has an
authority over the other like i'm here
voluntarily you can kick me out if you
want
i can leave it anyone neither of us has
the power to force the other to be in
this relationship we've chosen
my lawyer uh you know i defer to his
judgment he's not forcing me to do it he
gives me his advice and i can take it or
leave it
same with the doctor so there is a
clearly like who's in charge and who's
not in charge
but they're not in a position to impose
their will and everybody else and you
could very easily see
uh john is stephanie's lawyer and
stephanie is john's doctor
and in each of those contexts one has
this position of ostensible authority
over the other so
anarchism is in fact not some utopian
crazy thing
it is the norm of human relationships
where you meet people
you're not necessarily equal someone's
gonna be taller someone's gonna be
stronger someone start smarter wealthier
with others
but you're not at all thinking i am here
and i could tell you what to do and you
are legally or morally obligated
to follow my wishes that that is the
basis of anarchism
so in what way is the united states
imposing
by force something on you do you think
uh if you leave your house you will go
to jail
uh 40 of my money being taken from you
by taxation
right but don't you have the freedom to
not operate under that
no but that's like yeah like technically
if someone comes up to you and
mugs you and says your money or your
life you are making a choice
but what the anarchist argument is
they're not a position to force you
to make that choice that is not morally
binding even though they have
practically the power
to force you into that dilemma but you
have the freedom to live
on the united states or not so so even
i see yeah the argument is if you don't
like it leave right
not necessarily leave like
geographically but there's
there's ways to live outside
the force of the united states there's
ways it's just very difficult to operate
that way but that's like saying you
could outrun the mugger which is true
but the issue is does that mugger have
the right
to tell you at gunpoint you're either
giving me your money or i'm gonna shoot
you or
secret plan c you get to run away is
that person a moral actor and the
anarchist answer is never
and the difference one more thing the
anarchist view is the difference between
that mugger
and the government is only an
air of legitimacy literally they're
morally identical so is it possible
that every hierarchy that gets big
enough
and successful enough such that it can
monopolize
a bunch of services it provides isn't it
always going to be
a moral in your sense the way the united
states government is immoral well i
i don't want to say just like the united
states government is immoral because
that implies the united states
government is uniquely or especially
immoral very governmental
i just want to clarify that because i
know you didn't mean that i don't want
that to be an implication
um can you repeat the question so like
won't every okay so that's right this is
so that's progressive economics yeah so
the argument is
in any market at a certain point things
tend to centralize
and then that organization de facto can
dictate price can dictate so on and so
forth
that is completely historical if you
look at any market the trend is always
towards
decentralization the music industry
right when we were kids
there were four or five record labels
they were the ones who made all the
songs that you're going to see in the
billboard top 100 with a few exceptions
now anyone can go to direct to market if
you look at tv stations right it went
from cbs
nbc abc then you got fox then you had
cable which is 100.
now you have satellite which have sounds
around the world and you have youtube
which is literally infinite
so as technology improves and as wealth
increases which is a function of free
enterprise
you are going to always have more and
more choice
even within a monopoly coca-cola right
uh
uh this is an example i used i think and
then you write when we were kids
every terrible comedian would be like oh
now that i've got
diet uh caffeine-free coke what's next
and it's like
yeah that's good you want to have uh
what was his name uh
caiman the guy who invented the segway
if you go it dean came in if you go into
some restaurants right now you will have
those machines where you have like 80
kinds of cokes
and then you could have whatever flavor
you want to add to it grape cherry lemon
lime
so on and so forth so in any field
you're going to have more and more
competition you're going to have
less competition and less choices when
the state gets involved because the
state wants control
the state wants one big neck with one
leash around it
and that way it could just pull that dog
in one direction another and you saw
this last year
with the lockdowns carol roth wrote this
amazing book called the war in small
business
and she talked about we have seen for
the first time in history
a massive wealth transfer from small and
medium business
towards organizations like target and
amazon who made
trillions of dollars last year whereas
mom and pop which to me at least is like
the acme
of american achievement you come to
america you have a fruit stand a
laundromat
uh you make you socks whatever it is
you're that unique artisan creating
something special
they're the ones who didn't last whereas
target amazon did so when you have the
state
involvement it will always be in favor
of jeff bezos and for the simple reason
that
it's going to be a lot easier for jeff
bezos to get nancy pelosi and mitch
mcconnell on the phone
than it is for me making socks on etsy
but your sense
is that there'll be less and less over
time jeff bezos says
like whatever the industry will look at
there's be less
there's a trend towards decentralization
across
all industries and when i say
decentralization i just mean choice
right so if you look at again networks
you're gonna
if you were in the 80s and you had a
network just for uh lgbt issues
first of all it's going to be completely
heretical that's not going to happen
and there's not going to be enough
necessarily people identify as that to
have an audience
then there was something called logo
they have that there's lots of other
shows like that in this the way
so more specific look at websites yeah
i'm positive that you and i if we wanted
to look up
uh breeding guinea pigs would find
thousands of websites about different
breeds and all this other stuff
20 years ago 30 years ago like you're
gonna have two books
yeah and they're not gonna be dynamic as
these new uh um
uh breeds are developed so at the same
time it does
following on your argument it does seem
easier to move
and immigrate from from state to state
within the united states
and to other countries do you think
that's a form of freedom
that embodies anarchism where you can
resist
the uh the force of state by choosing
where you live
to some extent but the line people some
of these boomers will got me on twitter
if i'm going after the police or
something and be like if you don't like
america
get out of here and i tell them freedom
means i do what i want not what you want
freedom means i don't have to move you
don't have to move
free speech is a good example it doesn't
mean i have to be on twitter right
twitter has the right to ban me
but what i'm saying is i'm saying
something and you don't like it
too bad you're the one who has to
accommodate me
because i have a right to do what i want
with my person as long as i'm being
peaceful
so i guess i'm trying to get to the
difference between the state
and what you would naturally want in
anarchy
which is like a security company sure
all those things
they will as they become successful
start looking more and more like the
state because you get to
elect you give them money they uh i got
you they have leaders
what's the difference between a
government
and a very successful service provider
in in anarchism this gets a little
confused in america's big companies
necessarily are in hand in hand with the
government ended up in bed with them
the answer to this question is a long
complicated one and thankfully it's all
in the anarchist handbook
there was an essay by murray rothbard
who dave smith is this is the essay that
converted dave smith
so maybe it's not as good as it could
have been otherwise called anatomy of
the state
and mary rothbard points out that state
is the only
agency in a country which gets its goods
through force the state is the only
agency that is not a producer
but inherently a parasite because it
does not get its money voluntarily
but through taxation and by imposing its
values on a country
that is what makes a state uniquely
different from let's suppose an amazon
or a barnes noble or a target jeff bezos
does not have the authority or the moral
legitimacy
to get an army and go into somebody's
house whereas
andrew cuomo or ron desantis donald
trump and barack obama certainly do
but is it possible that
to refrain so jeff pesos does if he
if he hires a security force right also
is it possible to reframe taxation as a
form of payment like it
uh if it was done much better if you
could pay
this collective that we call government
in ways where you could pay for things
that you care
for so much your money would be
much more directly contributing to the
things you care for whether
if you care for a service like
healthcare you'll be able to
buy essentially insurance from the
government uh why am i buying insurance
from the government as opposed to
insurance from insurance company
what do you perceive as a difference
between a tax and a price do you see the
difference
yes i know on the surface level i'm
trying to get deeply to say
there's a lot of similarities but what
i'm saying is there's one
essential difference which is taxes are
imposed on you
and you have no choice as here's an
example my my book ego and hubris my
biography
uh it goes for 500 on ebay someone paid
for it some crazy person
people are showing me that it's on
amazon for three thousand dollars
something like that
you could put a million for it it's you
could charge whatever price you want the
question is is someone paying that three
thousand ford is someone paying that
million for it
and if it's actually the buyer who
establishes the price because the seller
can put any price tag he wants
80 trillion dollars but unless someone's
paying that amount and clearing the
market
uh that price has literally no real
meaning right it's not an indicator of
value or worth or market price
taxation on the other hand is by fiat
i can decide it's fair that you lex have
to pay 40
and joe has to pay 45 joe and lex are in
no position to be like this price is too
high
that not only is that money uh set just
completely out of their hands
it's taki for people who are employees
it's taken out of their paychecks before
they even see it
so they don't have the choice to be like
you know what i agree that the
government has the right to pay taxation
here's my check for forty percent it's
going on it's completely different
uh paradigm than you are when you're
playing the government provides a lot of
services
in the current system right but there's
no service the government provides that
cannot be
that would not be provided better more
efficiently and with more choices in a
market
well that's a hypothesis no that's very
likely no well that's not
this i can demonstrate this to you very
easily
i love it when you get flustered this is
this is what this is what people like
it's so cute the robot don't make me put
on the head
uh robot has the fire the smoke coming
out of his ears
what is price
there okay so it will tax love you know
like you know people like
i i think of the government as a kind of
subscription service
no no that's the anarchist view the
anarchist view of gov of
a private security would be a
subscription service so that's exactly
correct but everyone hates
when uh you sign up to a gym and then
you realize in the contract
it's very difficult to cancel that uh
membership and then they up the price
i mean that's there's a lot of
unpleasant things with with uh with a
subscription service
that then you can elect to go to another
sure you're or you could go and yelp and
complain and if there's enough people do
that the gym will be receptive
look at the power of yelp versus the
power of the vote well this
we could talk about that too so you're
saying yelp is more effective
than voting yes the thing is
i agree with you but you go
take a further step you say that yelp is
ethical
and moral and voting is amoral or like
not voting but
government is immoral so like it's not
only is one more efficient than the
other
you're saying like because i would say
government sucks
at doing what it does and it's gotten a
lot better at it
and i believe it can get keep getting
better
uh as it gets smaller and leverages
companies more and more
but you're saying no no government is
fundamentally as an idea gets in the way
of companies that should be doing those
things anyway right
i i just think that companies when you
take away government will start looking
like government
they just because something looks like
something does not mean it's the same
if someone puts out a yamaka into
fill-in and they go to shul they're not
jewish
right the the basic objection you have
with government
because you can leave like i i i
apologize that
this is that stupid twitter cliche
statement but
your opposition to the this idea of
leaving the united states
is that it's just it's a lot of effort
it's
it's it's too much friction not the
opposite the option the opposition is
i in the introduction to the book yeah i
say anarchism can be summed up in one
sentence
you do not speak for me everything else
is application
so the claim that somebody i've never
met or who i voted against
let's say i hate donald trump i despise
him
you know i want hillary clinton to be
president too bad trump's your president
that's not what i want yeah the idea
that this person can come on me and make
any claims onto one second of my time
as opposed to trying to persuade me that
is something that i
at anarchists regard as inherently uh
evil and nonsensical but to operate
large
organizations like you you see this with
cryptocurrency there's governance
you have to make difficult decisions
there's a block size wars for bitcoin
sure so you will there is a voting
mechanism often with membership when
your subscription service but
see the thing is you're using these
words and you're switching definitions
because like
if i go to a store i can technically say
i'm voting for tropicana orange juice
as opposed to another one but to kind of
say oh
well you're making a choice therefore
every choice is a vote i i don't i think
that that's something that
the venn diagram is not no i literally
mean vote in this case not money
okay there's some decisions like should
bitcoin
have increases block size okay there's a
bunch of different
uh they're called soft forks they're
hard forks oh i'm not saying you should
never
vote like stockholders have to vote
right exactly but there's no
pretense here's let's look at this if
you want to build robots
right you would sit down with the
company you would you guys would be like
we should do this kind of rubble i
should do this kind of robot
the stockholders would have a vote or
the board in proportion to their
investment in the firm
me who knows nothing about robots uh i
am
the idea that i'm in a position to walk
in and be like this is what you should
do
is crazy and bizarre and wrong because
i'm not in an informed position
so what democracy does is it forces
people who
run businesses well to run businesses
poorly
by people who don't know how to run
businesses at all that's the
that's one of the many concerns but
you're saying that's the fundamental
property of the state
i have a sense that the state could
become as effective as what we think of
as companies i mean
as this is why they can't because the
state does not have access to
data the way that firms do and this is
one of ludwig von mises great points
what he called the calculation problem
if i'm looking at comic books right and
i have detective comics
if detective comics 26 is a thousand and
detective comics 28 is a thousand
and detective comics 27 is 50 000
that is telling me that even if i don't
know anything about comics
that detective comics 27 is either very
very scarce for some reason
or very very desirable it's the first
appearance of batman whatever but
you don't need to know that to just look
at this data and be like okay this is
the market tell me something
if prices are set by the government
which the government is a monopoly
i have no way of picking those winners
or losers i don't have that data of
supply and demand
of an entire nation or a world of people
making individual decisions
and having price be dynamic and
informing me
as the the organization where i should
allocate my resources
so the price is a really strong signal
yes that allows you to uh
to operate a voluntary collective where
people get what they want
and don't get what they don't want and
it tells me what to produce what not to
produce
and it also is great because if i see
this podcasting industry which didn't
exist five years ago
and now these people are making bank
that tells me as
someone who is an investor okay they're
making 50
pro whatever 10 profit on their capital
in in the
plant industry it's 2 if i i'm going to
further my capital into this 10 percent
and that's going to lower the profit
rate as that
builds up and that is how uh markets are
regulated
voluntarily but the word government i
just think
it's possible to have collectives that
of
human beings that represent others based
on their voluntary
they yes of course you have private
governance absolutely private governance
any company you can have a ceo you're
gonna have a board directors yeah but
then you
i just it starts to look
very similar to me a successful private
governance mechanism at a scale of the
united states
starts looking a whole lot like the
current government of the united states
what's what's how even amazon i don't
think is anything close
to the center size-wise or budget-wise
or power-wise
no so you're saying you just
it's not even state it's almost like
anything at that size you want to keep
things smaller
and i don't i their markets are not
going to
combine to that level of the state
because no
jeff bezos will never even position to
tell everyone in america
i'm going to take 40 of your money
before you even see it that to me is
actually unclear
we don't know that to be true or that
google or amazon
can't grow to the size if you take away
the us government i'm not sure that
amazon can't grow to the size okay so
worst case scenario
is we're back where we started right uh
that's not worst case scenario but the
concern is that
google is going to be the federal
government that's not the concern i'm
saying like this is what it looks like
when google is the federal government
it's not a
it's like to me the
the us government is our best attempt so
far to have large-scale representation
of people's interests
it really sucks but it's our best
attempt so far and the question is how
to improve it
like if you take away all the if you
take away the us government
i'm trying to see how do we improve on
that
level that scale of representation of
people's
let me give you one example that's that
people could wrap their heads up very
easily i'm against government police
monopoly
i'm for private security right you don't
have to be an anarchist to understand
this
can everyone agree or at least as a
hypothesis
everyone can wrap the heads around and
here's a big concern 9-1-1
right there i've heard this 9-1-1 call
it's very chilling there's a kid in a
closet his family's being murdered
outside right he has to call 9-1-1 he's
whispering it's it's horrifying to hear
there's no reason why the number i call
for my families being murdered is the
same number i call for the fire
department is the same number i call for
an ambulance
what if instead it operated like uber
you had buttons on your phone
if there's a real emergency like
someone's gun flyers someone's being
killed you press this
and it sends instead of the one police
district
whatever company is nearby you have a
bunch of them and they're the ones who
are going to come to your house to save
you
people can wrap their heads around that
very easily that is one
very clear way to go from having a
government security monopoly
towards having a more free enterprise
system so when you apply that to pretty
much anything it doesn't become that
complicated of alternative
so what i would criticize this
but i believe the government it's like
the parenting thing we've talked about
earlier
i think it creates a safe space
for govern for uh i'm for safe spaces so
i'm not going to laugh you about that no
i want people to be safe but for uh a
safe space for entrepreneurship
so i believe that good government hold
on
give me a second give me a second sure
i'm sorry i'm sorry you're right you're
right i'm sorry
uh i think government gives
opportunity for companies to out-compete
it
yes so yes fedex 100
not a question so i believe you need to
have private school
government to give a chance for
ups fedex for spacex always an x in
there
uh to uh to to pop up and then
government will naturally back off from
that place
so like you but you need the innovator
to step in and build the thing
okay like you can't just when has
government ever backed off though
that never happens back well from from
from what from fedex and ups from uh
spacex from
amazon hold on the u.s postal service
still competes with fedex and ups
so here's the other thing not nearly not
well but they still exist
and the point is they're dying but ups
and fedex are
taxed so not only are they paying for
their own company
they're paying for this competitor this
is the essential difference imagine if
you
didn't have ups excuse me the federal
government no post office
so you had fedex you have dhl you have
u.s post service and many others
how about in this scenario ups
has the capacity to take 20 of fedex's
dhl
and couriers money and put in their own
pocket and they never have to do
anything in return
this is going to be an enormous
advantage of ups and then when you add
the addition that ups
is not necessarily going to be more
efficient the others this is going to be
a huge distortion in the market
can you imagine if your podcast you just
automatically got 20
of the views of everybody else i mean
would there be any incentive for you to
be great or you could just sit in your
laurels and do whatever you want even
more than now
it's hard to imagine more than now i
didn't say your robot and lack
imagination
i i think there just has to be uh
it's of course you can do it completely
without government but government's all
i need to hear okay that's all i need to
hear show's over
is uh like that safety net that's needed
for entrepreneurship that's needed for
uh i'm sorry to say but i have a sense
that there needs to be a bit of a safety
net for freedom
i i'm much more comfortable with saying
you need a safety net for freedom then
you need one for entrepreneurs
the beauty of markets is with your
startup if you have a startup
and it completely fails the only person
who's screwed is you and your investors
if i'm a government and i make a startup
the entire society fails like the iraq
war
right if i have this cockamamie plan i
don't everyone else doesn't have a
choice they are both funding it and
sometimes even drafted or forced into it
right
the safety net the antlers getting back
to the early anarchists one of the
things that i
admire about them the inaugural
communists the old school left
anarchists
is people don't remember what context
they were in they were in context
without a welfare state
they're immigrating in huge numbers from
eastern europe people are you go to the
tenement museum in new york
people like 12 to room kids are working
factories or
they either work in factories or they
have to starve it's not their parents
didn't love them
is that the parents didn't have birth
control which was a felony and they also
were in a position to put food in the
table for their kids because they're
uneducated
and the jobs are paying nothing so you
could understand why emma goldman
alexander berkman prudone
uh and and all these other figures were
like this is untenable
we see carnegie with 80 000 mansions
whereas this lady whose husband died at
age 30
who's never been to uh high school or
even junior high school
has 10 kids how is she going to put food
in the table it's not going to happen
you could understand why they would be
like all right we need to seize this
money
and distribute around the people that
makes a lot of sense in a contemporary
context
where food is much cheaper where shelter
to some extent is uh more available
when medical care people we're so
oblivious to how bad things were that we
see things are bad now so we assume that
they were better than in some context
they were much much worse there in many
contexts so
if you're going to make an argument for
government for me
the strongest argument is like food
stamps or like uh
free lunches for children because i
agree that would be
very inefficient and it's gonna probably
make them obese because you're gonna
have
uh nabisco lobbying to make sure that if
you're gonna have this uh
protein you wanna you're not gonna give
the kids an oreo aren't you these kids
are
poor you want them to have some pleasure
and that's gonna have deleterious
effects but if the choice is an
inefficient government program
and mass starvation that is one where as
an anarchist i
i could easily see making the argument
for that one
even though i think very clearly private
charity would be more efficient and
distributed more effectively but i
at that point i don't really care about
efficiency i if you're throwing out food
to make sure these kids get fed i don't
care so would the
engagement in military conflict be one
of the biggest
negative things about the state
to you yeah of course war is wars war is
the state at its worst
so if we take away
yeah i mean wouldn't that be a huge step
forward yeah instead of regarded
we're always this is what drives me
crazy we're taught as kids in school
that war is a last resort and i agree
with that
and yet when you look at the corporate
press war is always the first
response and these people do not
talk about what war means they'll show
examples during the bush years of
soldiers coming home
in caskets which already is an
unacceptable price in many cases for me
but they don't even pretend to care
about the people overseas whose
countries we've ransacked
and uh lives we've ruined and it's just
like well what are you gonna do not
ransack those countries
so that war is it to me is the state at
its worst
see i think that there is value from
small government that doesn't engage in
wars i do think that
the kind of collectives that you imagine
functioning well would look
like the best version of government that
i imagine
so okay what a great endorsement why i
see them as the same
i think a lot of this is just
terminology i have no problem
saying that i'm using the word anarchism
incorrectly and
to go for what you want i have no
problem with that or anything really
because like i said life is beautiful
but nevertheless
you wrote the essay why i'm not
not going to vote this time or ever yeah
i think i won't vote this year or
any other year or any year uh and the
basic i hope you do a better job reading
it than you just read that title
i guess you'll take as many takes as
necessary
[Laughter]
i'll read it in russian and then pay
somebody to just translate it
this isn't even russian at all you just
make up words
where'd you find this guy um you get
what you pay for
exactly uh this is anarchy
this is what you wanted uh like your
basic summary is
uh let me see if pressed the simplest
explanation i have for refusing to vote
is this
i don't vote for the same exact reasons
that i don't take
communion no matter how admirable he is
or how much i agree with him the pope
isn't the steward
over my soul nor is any president the
leader of my life
this does not make me ignorant or evil
any more than not being a christian
makes me ignorant to evil
if i need representation i will hire the
most qualified person to do so
yeah isn't voting our current best
developed way of hiring the most
qualified person to represent you on
some things
no because because if i have a lawyer
and the lawyer screws up i can fire him
if i vote for someone i don't get who i
want i get for
who my neighbors want so what that makes
no sense but representation means
i want you to speak for me whereas
voting is like
i kind of want you but i'll take what i
can get and i'm going to take what i
could get regardless of what's the point
what in governance again that's what
with bitcoin
is you want to be represented in
deciding
what to do but once wait bitcoin isn't
picking a person
they're not picking a president of
bitcoin they're picking an idea yeah
it's more like a referendum
right and to me a referendum is much
more represent is much more coherent
and defensible than it is voting for
representative because
if i'm voting for joe biden i'm saying
this person speaks for me for abortion
taxation environmental policy
immigration war right
the odds that unless you're a complete
npc that this one person
will speak for you for everything and
will and will deliver what he promised
as and has the power to deliver what he
promised is not true whereas if i have
brexit if i say i want britain to be
remain part of the european union to say
yes or no question
that makes a lot more sense to me but
even that is not pure democracy because
going back to the idea of the
circulation of the elites which james
burnham talked about pareto and moscow
and all them
you're still going to have someone
telling you what you can and can't vote
for and how these questions are framed
so the contradiction to what the left
anarchist said
some element of hierarchy is always
going to be inevitable
so listen i agree with this aspect
very much so that we should be voting
for ideas and
issues not voting for leaders for for
leaders to represent us across
the full spectrum of issues right it
seems to make no sense
okay good man this is great but i do
think there should be
a leader i i do believe in voting for
representatives to
debate to be communicators of ideas to
us but that you
here's here let me interrupt you but you
can you could you could have those two
things for example wouldn't this be an
improvement if
they have that now you have a referendum
do you want tax rates to be 30 or 40
whatever percent yeah
you have the guy leading the campaign
for 50. fight for 50.
then you have the lady leading the
campaign for 45 for 40.
they'll go out there they can have
debates they can talk about the issue
but you're still not voting for one of
them you're voting for the issue that
makes much more sense to me
then i'm going to vote for him and hope
that he puts forward 50 and that depends
on 99 other senators
exactly and but but also i mean i do
like the idea of voting for certain
people to debate certain ideas yes
i think that's a major improvement but
the final vote should be based on the
idea so
okay so we agree that would be nice to
have plus no wars
and then then uh you'll stop tweeting so
uh
aggressively and to decriminalize things
that
don't hurt people drugs crimes drugs
especially prostitution
is a big one if there's and this is me
talking mr
mr all cops are criminals there is no
one or or maybe other than like abused
children
who needs access to the police other
than sex workers
they're the ones who are the most likely
to really put themselves in dangerous
situation
so they need to be able to call security
because that's why they have pimps
because you're a woman dealing with some
strange dudes who are
a lot of the time gonna have weird kinks
you wanna be able to be sure
even if you don't approve of
prostitution think it's horrible that
she's not gonna be raped and murdered
and have no consequences
and if you're gonna say oh well she's a
prostitute she can't be raped
i uh just think for a second if you're
agreeing to sleep with somebody
and then he starts choking you and
beating the crap out of you and saying
it's now it's a dumb situation
that is clearly a beyond the pale
assault and the same thing with drugs
uh heroin cocaine do you crack do
you um the people that need
help the most are the ones who are
addicted to those drugs even the ones
who need punishment let's suppose you
think drug dealers should be
in jail right it is very hard for me to
say that
someone who sells uh cocaine should be
treated or in the same building
as someone who rapes children or is a
murderer these are not
similar types of evil even if you
believe that that drug dealer is an evil
person
yeah i have um i mean there's an essay
in there called by alexander burkman who
is
emma goldman's partner crime on crime on
prisons and crime
and this is leftism at its best for
getting the person who's forgotten
and the fact that we have the world's
largest prison population
the fact that so many people are just
like oh you commit a crime just put them
in jail throw away the key
at the very least if you want to be
totally immoral about it's expensive
and second of all the the concept that
all criminals should be locked in a room
together in these kind of
largely inhuman conditions and that's
going to help people i don't think that
that's the ideal
mechanism yeah i tend to believe i
usually don't
speak so negatively about politicians
but i do think that
politicians have done more evil
in the war on drugs than did the people
that are supposed to be the criminals
in this picture and i'll give you one
another example of how this is the
anarchist critique of power
hunter biden and i'm not gonna i'm not
making fun of him not taking shots at
him
he had an article in uh the new yorker
where he talks about when he was in la
he was buying crack
and there was a misunderstanding or like
he left the crack pipe in the hertz car
and then blah blah there's an issue
he's admitting to a felony in writing to
a reporter and i'm sure this was within
the statute of limitations
there was no possibility he was going to
have consequences kamala harris who was
a cop
talked about when she was in college
through smoking weed
and it's like i don't begrudge you guys
smoking your crack or smoking your weed
but
for other people who are poor or maybe
just had the
short end the stick this is years of
their life being
uh destroyed at the very least even a
rest is a traumatic situation
yeah if you have a weed or cocaine or
crack you're arrested that's really
going to screw up
it's going to do a number on you being
locked up so to have that double
standard to me is completely
unacceptable
and that has nothing to do with
republican or democrat that george w
bush was
i i coke head back in the day he talks
about overcoming his addiction and i'm
glad that he did more power to him
but just to have this kind of you know
it's just really kind of um disturbing
to me and this is my anarchist brain
like how prevalent drug use is in
college there's that i think this joke
on south park like there's a time and a
place to try drugs and that's called
college where people experiment
but all those college kids which are
going to become next generations elite
don't really have that worry that if
they get caught then anything's going to
happen to them
but that kid in the street uh who did
not have that good upbringing
even if he's a piece of crap like he's
not gonna have a different punishment i
i think that's just really
that is based on american so in contrast
to tolstoy
let me ask you about emma goldman you
wrote that uh
if anarchism believed in rulers then
emma goldman would be the undisputed
queen yes
what uh ideas define her flavor of
anarchism
would you say emma was really
an old-school radical she was a radical
among radicals
i don't know what ideas i mean what
would diabetes find her was anarchism
obviously there's the violence i mean
she was more
open to the idea of violent opposition
versus somebody like tolstoy oh sure for
sure so basically emma and alexander
berkman their mentor was someone named
johan most
and johan most was a very early free
speech not very early but he was a free
speech concern because he published a
pamphlet in europe
that was translated in the states about
how to build dynamite
because his idea was all right you have
this oppressive government this
oppressive police force
that use batons and bolts against us the
only way for us as the working class to
level the playing field
is through dynamite and here's how you
build it so the question is all right is
this something that could be allowed to
be legal
now that you're allowing the layman to
in his own house build bombs
so uh johann most turn basically they
had a big parting of ways
because when alexander berkman tried to
assassinate uh
frick johann said no no this is not uh
something i'm for and in fact they
thought uh with this assassination this
failed assassination this would be the
thing that's fired off the revolution
because you have this strike the
pinkerton's interval pinker's getting
killed
strikers are getting killed you know
this is what marx predicted
you know they're gonna light the spark
and everything's come falling down
he ends up going to jail for 13 years
instead alexander berkman does
uh and then goldman and berkman had a
big
issue because when leon salgaz killed
mckinley in 1901
it was really it's kind of humorous in
retrospect he gets arrested and they're
like why'd you kill the president he
goes
i was radicalized by emma goldman and
she's like god damn it
so she's on the run she's like i don't
even know this guy
and she made the point about like
why is it worse than the president being
killed and somebody else we're all equal
and you would think if you're against
capitalism against the ruling class this
would be your first target
but berkman who went to jail who was
tried
to assassinate someone he had said
mckinley this is your villain he's just
a party hack he's like a symptom of the
times he's
this is this is foolish and goldman
disagreed with him she thought it wasn't
necessarily um justified but it may have
done
something that was defensible so the
three of them uh
you know had their differences on the
use of violence and in fact when she
came back from russia
and was denouncing it in her book my
disillusionment russia and my further
solution rostra
the last chapter she goes look i'm not
saying i'm against violence
when there's the revolution comes we're
gonna have to use force she goes
but it's not the force of the state
against the working class against the
masses this is exactly what we're
opposed to this is a complete
obscenity to our principle so that was
interesting the fact that she was a uh
her periodical mother earth was a
clearing house for many prominent
uh you know ideas of the day that
weren't anarchists but were certainly
radical so she was a bit and also she
was like tiny she was like 5-1
so to have this little woman who was so
feisty
um and talk back to lennon talk back to
lennon
uh would she took on lennon woodrow
wilson jander hoover was the one who
deported
her uh someone who just and the thing is
you have to be careful
because i think just like war it's very
easy to glamorize
violence and to regard it as something
admirable or heroic like you're fighting
for the cause
but if you take it out of the
romanticism you're like you're killing
someone who had kids you are you know
killing someone with the family
you're making your if you're gonna shoot
someone they're probably gonna retaliate
twice as hard
violence sings its own song and this is
a very dangerous word you're going down
so
you you really need to be uh careful
about what you're what you're preaching
here
um and you know she kind of had this
mixed feelings about it but
that is certainly not uh emma goldman
her best
emma goldman her best was about the
ultimate freedom of the individual of
caring about people who were desperately
poor
who despised the corporate idea that we
all had to be made into cookie cutters
and be interchangeable and all have to
start work at the same time
and basically our entire lives slave for
corporation that have nothing to show
for it
while they get wealthy and you you have
no opportunity for either uh
productive work or creative work so uh
that i think the valorization
of kind of the lowest of the low is
something i find very admirable there's
a quote of hers which i think
even for those of us who are you know
for property rights
is anarchy left anarchism at its best
but she goes
go and ask for work if they don't give
you work
ask for bread if they don't give you
bread take bread
so the idea that like if you're that
poor and you're honestly trying to work
and work isn't available
and you steal food to keep alive that
you shouldn't feel guilt about it
i don't know that i would disagree with
that i i think that there's something to
be said at that point where it's just
like
you know if property rights come between
that and mass starvation
it's gonna be very hard for anyone to
make the case for property rights now my
argument is
when you have free enterprise food
becomes so plentiful that now obesity is
an issue
but at the time she did not of course
have that data to
you know access is there somebody you
left out
from the book that you thought about
leaving in
like uh some interesting figures
yeah there there's a couple so um
chomsky would have been one
of course because he's a you know one
he's probably the biggest standard
because one of the biggest anarchist
thinkers in contemporary times
um i was on the fence about herbert
spencer because he's not an anarchist
chris williamson is reading the chapter
for the book he coined the term survival
of the fittest and the
chapters called the right to ignore the
state from his book social statics it
was deleted from later editions people
found it and reprinted it
um and uh
randolph-born he was an early
progressive he was the only one or one
the very few fighting against entering
the great war
and he had an essay called war is the
health of the state which is basically
about how
states love war because it gives them an
excuse to increase their power
and it's very hard to argue against
increasing state power in a time of war
but since he was not himself an
anarchist and there was plenty anti-war
in there already
i didn't include him but those would be
the ones is there some people that
you think uh the public would be
surprised
to learn that they are at least in part
anarchists like i saw that howard zinn
is supposed to be an anarchist
i mean is there um like just like
tolstoy isn't it
anarchist is there some people like that
that you think in our modern life
that would be surprised to learn their
anarchists i can't think of any off the
top of my
head i mean you could say carl hess who
was like barry goldwater speechwriter
from the 964 campaign but he's hardly a
household name
yeah um i mean i think a lot of people
would not ascribe to that term but are
certainly informed
with this complete distrust of all
authority
murray rothbard had an essay if i didn't
include anatomy of the state i was going
to include this one it's much much
shorter
and his question was who are our allies
and who are enemies
and the point he makes is there's lots
of people who would call themselves
anarchists who are of little use whereas
someone who
is still like a minor kisser for
government but genuinely hates the
question
rothbard had is if there's a button and
you could press that you would end the
state would you press it so fast your
finger would get a blister
those are allies even if they're uh you
know somewhat of a minericus
so i think that is a kind of a better
lens of looking at it
and i don't think anyone needs to really
ascribe to anarchism as a whole ideology
insofar as you're seeing right now many
people in certain fringe elements
are just essentially or are decreasingly
fringe and increasing mainstream
elements
are realizing that this idea that
whatever the state does is somehow
morally binding or legitimate
is something that a b at least bears
strong questioning
sure and i mean i i guess there's a lot
of
groups like the libertarians for example
sure have
some element of that oh sure for sure of
harsh questioning of the ways
of government and also i think what's
what i love
i mean if there's one issue where i
would want people to have this kind of
analysis it is war
and it is like okay are you really sure
uh
because this is a hundred percent gonna
result in a lot of people being killed
a lot of people being traumatized a lot
of people who are never gonna recover
children innocent people are you really
sure this is the right thing to do
and i think a lot of times if the answer
is well it's the profitable thing to do
and that is i think again government at
its absolute
most venal and worst
you michael mouse in many ways are a new
yorker
oh yes i'll give you one example i don't
know where austin is on the map
no idea not even kidding but does it
even matter it doesn't matter
but nevertheless you've decided to move
to austin yes
why do you think you're moving to austin
or why do you moving
both to austin and away from new york
this was one of the both i hate it when
people talk like this but i'm gonna do
it anyway
this was one of the hardest and easiest
decisions of my life
it was hard because i've lived in new
york since i was two
other than college it's the only home
i've known i know it intimately
i know all the cool spots i love it with
every fiber of my being or i did
it was very much you know ingrained in
my personality my outlook
about what cities can be and can't be
and should be and shouldn't be
um deciding to move was not done
but when you see your crew your your you
know chosen family one
by one whittling away it's not easy um
they all left
uh there's just a couple of us left in
new york and
i don't see any mechanism by which new
york is going to improve things are
getting much worse
all the time it's just completely
outrageous here i would have a
i have a huge crew i didn't realize how
much cheaper real estate is
than in new york this is another way
many so new yorkers are the most
provincial people on earth who are
completely oblivious to the rest of the
country
so for a long time the argument was new
york versus l.a right for certain types
of people
and they would say la's cheaper in terms
of rent so new york let's suppose the
rent is a thousand la was 700 but you'd
have to get a car i'm like this is kind
of a wash
so i assumed austin would be like 80 of
new york prices
and i'm looking at these houses and for
like 700 000
you could get a house here that would
cost like 3.5 million in new york
yeah so and you could have a gun and
it's just like i could have a yard
and i could have a dog and i have a
three bedroom and i could have you know
aquariums and my
weird plants so to have all that and
it's just to have i am very very
lucky that i have such a supportive crew
and they're also very smart because they
sat me down and they said
whatever excuse you have not to move
here
we are going to make sure that doesn't
count so my buddy matt
said because i have a huge library he
goes i will go to your house
and i will pack every single book you
own myself
so you can get that as an excuse out of
the way i don't know how to drive near
this uku
um she's like we're gonna take driving
lessons together
there goes that excuse uh how do i find
an apartment they're like
we'll go to with the realtor we'll take
pictures for you we'll report back you
could trust our judgment
and i'm like that's very i would do that
that sounds like fun shopping for house
i'd have to buy them
yeah then matt just yesterday had the
idea goes
come here rent a furnished apartment
for a few months you don't have the
pressure of buying and it's just
it's going to be an easy transition the
rent's not going to be anything compared
to new york i'm like these are all
very valid things you're here lots of
other people by the way that's what this
is is uh i made sure that's
renting month to month oh this is rental
this is rental
well you didn't realize this i thought
you bought this no no no it was a rent
to hawk
why i thought you bought it no it's
rental well i really value
freedom so who are you talking to
i've heard this thing freedom it's
really great
[Laughter]
but not everybody the implementation of
freedom is different for everybody
of course for me i i don't want to
uh make a statement about others i'll
just speak for myself
i think when you buy a house that is not
just a wise financial decision
or all those kinds of reasons that
people have investment all those kinds
of things
i think it's also a hit on your freedom
because the positive way to frame that
is you make it a home
you have a deep connection to it but the
negative way to frame it is
you're now a little bit stuck there yeah
and you may stay there way
longer than you should when much better
opportunities for life
come up there are stages in life when
you're not sure exactly what the future
will hold i would argue that's very
often the case
uh basically at every stage in life and
i just want to make sure i maximize the
freedom
to uh to embrace the most ambitious
the uh the craziest the wildest the most
beautiful
opportunities that come by you've
actually brought this
up to because i i said i really enjoyed
the conversation with you and
euron yeah like you
talking to you and somebody else
yeah i think you make a really
significant effort you've said this
before but
it really is true and it stands in
contrast to
other folks who are also good
conversation you really make an effort
for that person like to unders like to
meet the person oh for sure
and that's uh you made me you made me
realize it's kind of a
uh it's an art form uh
but it's also just it's a thing worth
doing
of putting in that effort and that leap
of humanity to like reach the whether
you're talking to dave rubin
or alex jones or joe or me
just yeah those are different human
beings and they're taking that leap it's
it's fascinating i mean
do you have um how do you think about
that
i i'm a huge introvert as as you are i
think
um i i feel very very very lucky
that i get to get on a mic
and run my mouth and for some people
some reason people like this
so i know
what it's like to have a good convo and
i know what it's like to have a bad
convo
so before i'll do a show i will have
like some
things i would want to talk about and
then i'll think about how to say them in
an engaging way
so i do my homework in that regard i'm
also very
good at or i pride myself at taking
people who are cerebral or intellectual
and making them a little bit silly but
also making them feel safe to be silly
because i'm not going to be making a
buffoon of them that we're having
fun as opposed to disrespecting the
person i think we all saw that with
yaran
who's very cerebral very serious but we
were all cracking jokes
um and he was having a good time and he
knew even if i'm making fun of him to
his face
it is coming from a place of kindness
and he's in on the joke and we're all
having fun
that is something i try to do as
uh much as possible i had an episode of
my show
a couple of weeks ago and someone who's
been a friend of mine for a long time
and someone i admire a lot elizabeth
spyers
she was the founding member of um gog
founding editor of gawker
you know she's she's worked for the
observer for jared kushner she's her
resume's second to none and she was on
my show and she was talking
you know her politics are pretty
straightforward like corporate
journalist blue pill
politics and my audience was very upset
that i wasn't pushing back or like
whatever i'm like
my job if someone is coming to a place
where like the audience is at least
going to be somewhat hostile
is not to make her have negative
consequences
for doing something that she didn't need
to do my job is to make sure that the
experience
is a positive one for her as the host so
when i'm the guest
i always feel that my job is to make the
host look good
and make the host not feel like it's
work and the audience really likes that
because instead of it being an interview
or intense it is a conversation nine of
us know
what's going to happen and so this is
something i think about a fair amount
and i try to apply and insofar as it
successfully
i'm delighted and there's times when
it's not successful and that's a shame
but
all we could do is uh do our best yeah i
really enjoyed that conversation with
her i was surprised
by uh the dislikes and all that kind of
stuff well one of the things i always
talk about
is i don't i don't care what my friends
politics are i care about if someone's
if i'm having a bad day can i call them
up and ask for advice and elizabeth has
been there for me in the past
and then when i do it on a camera in
front of mike's people freaking out i'm
like
i'm practicing what i preach uh my
the relationships are more important
than someone's political views
and it's not hypocrisy at all to
demonstrate that and not not to push
back and there was great humor there
you're both a bit of trolls and yeah in
very different ways but
nevertheless that connection the humor
and the mutual respect and love
that was all there yeah yeah it's just
fascinating um
you've talked to alex jones a couple
days ago sure yeah you've talked to him
many times before but you've had him on
your podcast
um this week yeah this week i was kind
of surprised that um
he mentioned that human animal hybrids
was like
the number the main conspiracy that
people should
look into to open their eyes to the
you know to the globalists all the
conspiracies that are out there
was that surprising to you um no
because i came in there with questions
and i was very focused on corralling him
and having it be
like a kind of a coherent intellectual
conversation that was a really really
good it was only an hour but it was a
very good conversation yeah thank you
the response was overwhelmingly positive
and i'm like all right
i'm in a unique position because alex i
i met alex well that's not true but i
was on alex
with alex on tim pool a couple of times
it was mayhem
it was anarchy and i'm like all right
let me get but the thing is what people
enjoyed is i was the one who was
basically
able to translate alex ease he's
obviously very performative
and a lot of times alex will say things
that are not really
uh particularly controversial but he'll
say them in such a way
that it sounds crazier than it is you
know i think joe's made this observation
as well
so what i wanted to have him on when on
my show
is all right let's go through all these
conspiracies which have validity which
don't
and i knew if i asked because he's got a
lot of historical knowledge even if you
want to think of a lot of it's
nonsensical
let's sort out the wheat from the chaff
you know because everyone has someone
crazy in them i have this expression
you take one red pill not the whole
bottle you take the whole bottle of red
pills you assume literally everything in
the media is a lie
that that's just not a coherent position
to have is the weather alive when they
tell you the
temperature's gonna be wrong tomorrow so
that was fun to watch him go through
that
and he felt bad because he felt
incorrectly in my opinion
that he was needlessly aggressive and
disrespectful toward me on tim i didn't
feel disrespected at all it got heated
but i didn't take it personally people
have heated debates all the time
so i think he he promised me he wouldn't
interrupt and would be deferential
but that because he promised to be on
his best behavior
that gave me an opportunity to address
him seriously
and not to bring the clown aspect out of
him which is easy to caricature him
my friend ethan supply who i'm sure
people know played a basic
character based on him in the hunt
because eric alex is kind of this
cartoon
archetype so it was really fun to get
another side of him
um and and also it's just fun
being on his show just him being
bombastic and just trying to be the calm
voice of reason
and for once the trickster was apollo
well i like this
this thing he said before and that's
what
makes me the most interested in alex is
the uh the nietzsche quote about the uh
you know gazing into the abyss i think
he said on your show that he has become
the abyss or something like that
i think that makes him fascinating that
when you really take conspiracy theory
seriously
the kind of effect it has on your mind
that to me is fascinating well can i say
one thing
the term conspiracy theory if you ask
any layman
like it's like this you say do you like
puppies i hate them do you like baby
dogs oh they're the best right people
the human mind is capable of doing this
yes so if you ask people
do you think extremely powerful people
often get together and manipulate data
or rules
in order to further their power and
control and maintain it i think 90 plus
percent of people be like
of course then you say oh so you believe
in conspiracy theories oh no that's for
crazy people
those concepts are identical now that
term
is used for people who are like all
right uh
um you know there's conspiracies in
government to experiment on people like
tuskegee this is not in dispute the cia
has you know unsealed things operation
mockingbird so on and so forth
and at the same time conspiracy theory
applies to people who say
9 11 never happened and those are
holograms now it's the same word for
both
but these are not at all equal truth
claims and they do not at all have equal
evidence to them
but it's very useful for powerful people
to have that term in the zeitgeist
because then i don't have to explain or
defend it's like only lunatics are going
to look further on this
do you really want to be a lunatic kid
and that takes care of the issue
i i unfortunately the same problem
applies with language applies to a lot
of other
100 that's the nature of language yeah
it's used not just to communicate but to
obfuscate
obviously that could be fixed by coming
up with different words
to uh to label conspiracy theories that
are much more
likely to be true yeah power elite
analysis
is another it's basically conspiracy
theory this is the black pill
versus white pill question sure with the
abyss
do you think thinking about these things
can can destroy the mind
can uh make you deeply cynical about the
world
yeah because if you are thinking that
you are not aware of or
no one is aware of who's controlling
things and that
the level of their control it gives you
the sense of powerlessness and
hopelessness
yeah and my counter is the people in
charge one of the reasons i'm an
anarchist
are nowhere near as smart and crafty as
you think they are
and certainly maybe the the ones
completing the shadow maybe are but the
ones who are in the public face most
certainly are not
as social media has demonstrated when
you look at how senators and harvard
professors tweet
these are not you know intellects that
you're in awe of to put it mildly
so i think that kind of takes the bloom
off the rose to a great extent
you mentioned that you've been doing a
lot of amazing things been truly joyful
recently yeah what uh
i don't know if you have a bucket list
is there items on the bucket list you
haven't done yet
are you are you pretty much satisfied
and happy
and if you die today i if i murder you
you'll be happy
i could die today is there an item on
the buccal list you want to get done
um i don't yeah uh deep sea
submersible that would be number one in
a bucket list
why because that's where all the most
interesting zoology is
and to be um in a place where
like virtually no human being has been
and to see these
god's mistakes in their natural
environment my friend coined that term
god's mistakes if you look at deep sea
creatures you can imagine god
making some animal being like oh god
this is hideous i'll just throw the bomb
the ocean no one's gonna see this
um so that would be my number one bucket
list thing
i would say go to the white house as a
guest would be a bucket list thing
russia go to russia would be a bucket
list thing
um i want to go these are secondary like
go to eritrea
it would be a buckless thing i've got a
long list of books i need to write
that's that's i don't know that's really
a bucket list per se
um uh there's not that much what i'm at
a point in my life
is once you cross off certain things you
basically instead of driving the car
start surfing
and just amazing i talked to you about
this medical thing you know before we
started yeah
at a certain point and i'm sure this
happens to you because your platform's a
lot bigger than mine
all sorts of things start coming your
way that you never would have thought of
and you're like this is pretty darn cool
so to be and that's happening at an
escalating rate like i'm at a point now
where i get stopped every day um by
people so that's going to be a weird
thing for me
to get adjusted to i ever like
without exception everyone who has ever
stopped me on the street has been cool
and it's been a pleasant experience
there was one exception in an event
where someone
was genuinely on the spectrum and they
didn't understand like
distance and you don't touch people and
that but that's as bad as it got
so that is something that's going to be
weird for me to have to deal with
um over the next couple of years but you
know it's the price you pay and
it's it's hardly a small price when
people come up to you and say you've
made my life better but it's just weird
when you go and like like i was at the
gym
and then someone tweets like did i see
you at the gym just now
it's kind of weird and i'm sure it's the
same for you when you're walking around
and you don't think about it but people
know who you are and you don't know who
they are that you're being watched even
though it's not malevolent it's still
just
you don't get prepared for that michael
there were
there will be two really big names that
uh wanted to do this podcast we'll do
this podcast that i considered to do
episode 200 with
but then i realized why the hell talked
to somebody
um famous when i could talk to somebody
i love
that nobody knows or cares
you just hit a random number generator
yeah
just i listed all the russians i know
and who's the easiest to get
you're the yeah who's the most desperate
he's got a shitty book out we could talk
about that for five minutes
this garbage cut and pace that he did
yeah
uh it turned out okay i think
slightly above average michael i i love
you you're an incredible human being
it's an
honor that you would talk to me and
you'll be my friend thanks so much for
doing this
uh the respect that i got uh when you
asked me to be the guest for the
anniversary episode was similar to the
respect when my two friends josh and zoe
they were going to get married
at city hall and they said we want
someone to witness it they ask you
so it's one thing when people tell you
they like you and respect you which
i had growing up it's nothing when they
show it and this is something that i do
not take lightly and i hope no one takes
slightly and if someone does right by
you
and shows you respect going back to kind
of taking out for dinner
thank them buy them a candy bar buy them
a soda
do something to show that you don't take
it for granted because i think what you
and i both want to do
is increase human kindness as much as
possible and
i'm going to look at the camera be kind
to yourself
because a lot of you deserve it
thanks for listening to this
conversation with michael malus and
thank you to
gala games indeed betterhelp and
masterclass
check them out in the description to
support this podcast
and now let me leave you with some words
from jack kerouac
that perhaps begins to explain the
nature of
and the reasons for my friendship with
mr michael malus
the only people for me are the mad ones
the ones who are mad to live
not to talk matt to be saved desirous of
everything at the same time
the ones who never yawn or say
commonplace thing
but burn burn like fabulous yellow roman
candles
exploding like spiders across the stars
and in the middle
you see the blue center light pop and
everybody goes
thank you for listening and hope to see
you next time
you